<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Violence हिंसा on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/violence/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Violence हिंसा on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/violence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Abortion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/violence/abortion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/violence/abortion/</guid>
      <description>The Dharmic texts enunciate how though Jiva is present within the mother from the time of conception, it enters the Hrdaya of the fetus only towards the fourth month of pregnancy. Hence, the fetus, which is a non-living matter becomes endowed with Jivahood only towards the end of the fourth month of pregnancy. Thus, only the abortion performed after the 16 weeks of pregnancy or after the Jiva enters the Hrdaya of fetus (which can be known from unique desires that mother develops), can be compared to a killing of person, while abortion before 16 weeks is just preventing Jiva from self-identifying with the fetus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/violence/human-sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/violence/human-sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>Vedic Human Sacrifice puruSha-medha, and para-vedic traditions consider in veda repo pages. Collection of a skull for chayana during a yAga, described here, could involve killing. (Almost) sacrifice of Śunaśśepha by ambarISha. shunaskarNa+agniShToma where the yajamAna/patnI sacrifice themselves Non-vedic human sacrifice For better harvest (Assam 2015) here. For spiritual and other reasons : [TC]. Comparison: Guru Gobind Singh famously called for human sacrifice volunteers, the panj pyare. among the unmatta-s, abrAham almost sacrificed issac.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Suicide</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/violence/suicide/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/violence/suicide/</guid>
      <description>Forms prAyopaveshaNa - starving oneself. sallekhana among jains. Burning oneself on a pire as a paschAt-tApa/ prAyashchita. The pAla king, the tale of the maNDana. garuDa heroes following their kings in South India [IM]. Following the husband by satI-s (details in anugamana page). Injunctions &amp;ldquo;That it goes against the Sruti statements like “Therefore, one should not depart before one’s natural lifespan” (Shatapatha Brahmana 10.2.6.7), which prohibit suicide.&amp;rdquo; - Nithin &amp;ldquo;exceptions to the general prohibition against Atma-tyaga will reveal these cases have no resemblance to Suicides.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>दण्डः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/violence/daNDaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/violence/daNDaH/</guid>
      <description>परिवारे बृहदारण्यकोपनिषदि बलेन गमनम् उक्तम् - विस्तारो ऽत्र । मनुस्मृतौ 299 भार्या पुत्रश् ...{Loading}... भार्या पुत्रश् च दासश् च
प्रेष्यो भ्रात्रा च सोदरः ।
प्राप्तापराधास् ताड्याः स्यू
रज्ज्वा वेणुदलेन वा ॥ ८.२९९ ॥
गङ्गानथ-मूलानुवादः ...{Loading}... The wife, the son, the slave, the servant and the uterine brother shall be beaten with a rope or a split bamboo, when they have committed a fault.—(299)
मेधातिथिः ...{Loading}... प्राप्ता अपराधं प्राप्तापराधाः । अपराधो व्यतिक्रमः नीतिभ्रंशः । स यदा तैः कृतो भवति, तदा ताडयितव्याः ।</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
