<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Asada anugamana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/asada-anugamana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/asada-anugamana/</guid>
      <description>“Suicide of an Officer&amp;rsquo;s Wife.&amp;quot;
The Tokyo papers report the suicide of the wife of Lieut. Asada, who was killed in the last Manchurian campaign undertaken by Gen. I &amp;ndash; in order to recover Feughwau.
Mrs. Asada was a daughter of Major Okami, who commanded the third battalion of the Maruyama force. She was brought up under a rigid system and had only married the lieutenant the year before last. She was very virtuous, and was regarded by all who knew her as the model of a soldier&amp;rsquo;s wife.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GA on anugamana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/ghorAngIrasa_on_anugamana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/ghorAngIrasa_on_anugamana/</guid>
      <description>Some interesting points about sati:
It seems to be a kSatriya practice of NW provenance as far as bhArata is concerned. However, the practice definitely had external roots.
Initial reaction by brAhmaNas, prominently medhAtithi, was stern opposition as the shruti condemns those who end their life before the expiry of its natural term. Even if brAhmaNas couldn’t prevent sahagamana’s popularity among kSatriyas, they disliked it for their own women. Subsequent rise in prominence &amp;amp; support for sahagamana rests on secondary citations of smRtis as exceptions to the shruti’s general rule against suicide; most of which are not traceable to the cited sources.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>John Jones - sati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/john_jones_sati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/john_jones_sati/</guid>
      <description>My aunt was dressed in a red silk sari, with all the ornaments on her person; her forehead daubed with a very thick coat of sindur, or vermilion; her feet painted red with alta; she was chewing a mouthful of betel; and a bright lamp was burning before her. She was evidently wrapped in an ecstasy of devotion, earnest in all she did, quite calm and composed as if nothing important was to happen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nithin Shridhar - perspective</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/shrIdhar-nitin-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/shrIdhar-nitin-perspective/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
विस्तारः (द्रष्टुं नोद्यम्) Author’s Note: This is to clarify that the purpose of the article is to understand the practice of Sati-Anugamana as it was practiced in the past using value-system prevalent at those times. The author neither suggests that Sati has to be revived today nor supports any such attempts by anyone in current times.
Nithin Sridhar
Nithin Sridhar has a degree in Civil Engineering, and having worked in the construction field, he passionately writes about various issues from development, politics, and social issues, to religion, spirituality, and ecology.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
