<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 Textual Studies on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 Textual Studies on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Vedic *Homa* and the Standardization of Hindu *Pūjā*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/01_The_Vedic_Homa_and_the_Standardization_of_Hindu_Pj/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/01_The_Vedic_Homa_and_the_Standardization_of_Hindu_Pj/</guid>
      <description>Timothy Lubin
INTRODUCTION The homa, the ritual offering of food in a fire, has had a prolific career in Asia over the course of more than three millennia.1 In various forms, rites of this type have become a part of most of the religions that arose in India as well as their extensions and offspring from Samarqand to Japan. All of these homas ultimately descend from those of the Vedic religion, but at no point has the homa been stable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Oblation, Non-conception, and Body</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/02_Oblation_Non-conception_and_Body/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/02_Oblation_Non-conception_and_Body/</guid>
      <description>SYSTEMS OF PSYCHOSOMATIC FIRE OBLATION IN ESOTERIC BUDDHISM IN MEDIEVAL SOUTH ASIA
Tsunehiko Sugiki
INTRODUCTION Brahmanism developed various forms of external fire oblation rituals from the beginning of its history.1 Meanwhile, some traditions in Brahmanism (especially the Upaniṣadic tradition) attempted to internalize fire oblation rituals and developed various theories on the internal practice of fire oblation.2
The same attempt can be seen in Buddhist esoteric traditions. The Mahāvairocana-sūtra (ca. seventh century) is the oldest Buddhist scripture that systematically teaches inner forms of fire oblation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 The Three Types of Fire Sacrifice According to Kāṇha’s *Śrīcakrasaṃvara-homavidhi*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/03_The_Three_Types_of_Fire_Sacrifice_According_to_Khas_rcakrasavara-homavidhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/03_The_Three_Types_of_Fire_Sacrifice_According_to_Khas_rcakrasavara-homavidhi/</guid>
      <description>David B. Gray
THE TIBETAN EXEGETICAL traditions on the Cakrasaṃvara-tantra and related literature that developed by the end of the period of the second transmission of Buddhist teachings (phyi dar), as exemplified by authors such as Tsongkhapa Blo-bzang-grags-pa (1357–1419 C.E.) and Jo-nang Tāranātha (1575–1634 C.E.),1 placed great emphasis on works attributed to three great Indian Mahāsiddhas. These three figures, the lo dril nag gsum, were Lūi-pa, Ghaṇṭa-pa, and Kāṇha-pa. Lūi-pa is the reputed author of the Cakrasaṃvarābhisamaya, an extremely influential sādhana that is the subject of a dozen commentaries preserved in the Tibetan Tanjur.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Fire Rituals by the Queen of Siddhas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/04_Fire_Rituals_by_the_Queen_of_Siddhas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/04_Fire_Rituals_by_the_Queen_of_Siddhas/</guid>
      <description>The Aparimitāyur-homa-vidhi-nāma in the Tengyur
Georgios T. Halkias
FIRE, IN ITS creative and destructive potency and in its luminous immediacy, has inspired a variety of ritual activities across religious settings and mythological contexts. We may briefly recall the lame god Hephaistos (Grk. Ἥφαιστος; Lat. Vulcan), master of weaponry, metallurgy and volcanoes worshipped by the Greeks and Romans, and Hestia (Grk. Ἑστία; Lat. Vesta), the virgin goddess of the hearth bestowing blessings on the altars of the faithful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 *Homa* Rituals in the Indian *Kālacakra-tantra* Tradition</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/05_Homa_Rituals_in_the_Indian_Klacakra-tantra_Tradition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/05_Homa_Rituals_in_the_Indian_Klacakra-tantra_Tradition/</guid>
      <description>Vesna A. Wallace
INTRODUCTION The diverse homa rituals attested in the Kālacakra-tantra and in its commentary, the Vimalaprabhā, represent an amalgamation of theories and ritual practices unique to the Kālacakra tradition with others that are appropriations and redefinitions of Vedic fire ritual and the Sāṃkhya theory of the material world (prakṛti) and its properties (guṇa). The appropriation and adaptation of Vedic homa ritual by Buddhist and Śaiva tantric traditions are well attested.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Ritual Subjects</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/06_Ritual_Subjects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/06_Ritual_Subjects/</guid>
      <description>HOMA IN CHINESE TRANSLATIONS AND MANUALS FROM THE SIXTH THROUGH EIGHTH CENTURIES
Charles D. Orzech
THE EARLY NINTH-CENTURY monk Huilin 慧琳1®describes homa as follows: “In Tang language this Indic term is called ‘fire offering.’ Substances used to make food offerings for the worthies and sages are incinerated in a fire, just as in the four suburban and five marchmount sacrifices, etc.”2
As a disciple of the esoteric master Amoghavajra (Bukong jin’gang 不空金剛, 704–774), Huilin was well aware of the importance of homa not only in esoteric ritual but also as a key instrument in esoteric Buddhism’s support of the imperium.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
