<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>dharmashAstra-place</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/articles/dharmashAstra-place/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/articles/dharmashAstra-place/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.indica.today/long-reads/place-of-dharmashastras-in-hindu-worldview/&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Place of Dharmashastras in Hindu Worldview&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Nithin Sridhar July 1, 2021&lt;br&gt;&#xA;india facts&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction-current-situation&#34;&gt;Introduction: Current Situation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Shastras play a central role in Hindu tradition and society. However, due to the effects of colonialism, Hindus have become deracinated and have lost touch with this core aspect of our civilization.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The deracination is so deep that while detractors of Hinduism with ideological agendas continue to use Hindu Shastras as a tool to undermine Hinduism, the response from the Hindu side has been clumsy, disoriented, and one that involves denouncement of our Shastras as not relevant and outdated.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>mahAperiyava 5 directives</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/articles/mahAperiyava_5_directives/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/articles/mahAperiyava_5_directives/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.rattibha.com/thread/1661158266708324352&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The five directives given by Kanchi Paramacharya swamigal to the community&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The perfect age for upanayanam is eight, therefore should be performed at most before ten years of age. The boy who has undergone upanayanam before 10 years of age, instead of attending a regular school, should stay and serve in a home for a year, where one of these is performed - Shiva pujai or agnihotra or vaishvadevam. In that one year, if possible he should learn and understand his veda shaka from a guru and complete his veda vratas. At the least he should memorize sandhyavandhanam, samidAdhanam, brahmayagnya puja mantras.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Men and women over 45 years of age should find a guru near their place of residence, get initiated into practicing Shiva nama or Rama nama Japam. They should practice nama japam on a daily basis. If a suitable Guru is not available, shall start nama japam at a nearby temple and continue to practice daily.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Permission to perform rituals during auspicious and inauspicious times should be sought with submission from a person who has learnt one veda samhitai in its entirety. During weddings, the worldly rituals like percussion pandal feast thambulam procession etc should be completed at the bride’s home in one day. The same day blessings should be taken and that night pravesha homam should be performed with aupasana agni at the groom’s house or a mandpam. The next three days aupasanas should be done without any fanfare and the final day rituals should be completed with sesha homam or nagabali.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Proselytization by other faiths should be checked/stopped in a peaceful manner. People following our dharma should be discouraged from conversion as far as possible.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sale of cattle to slaughterhouses should be actively campaigned against and prevented.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
