<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 Symbolic and Comparative Studies on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/02_Symbolic_and_Comparative_Studies/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 Symbolic and Comparative Studies on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/02_Symbolic_and_Comparative_Studies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Ritual Interplay of Fire and Water in Hindu and Buddhist Tantras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/02_Symbolic_and_Comparative_Studies/01_The_Ritual_Interplay_of_Fire_and_Water_in_Hindu_and_Buddhist_Tantras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/02_Symbolic_and_Comparative_Studies/01_The_Ritual_Interplay_of_Fire_and_Water_in_Hindu_and_Buddhist_Tantras/</guid>
      <description>Holly Grether
SHORTLY BEFORE HIS untimely death in 1994, Sinologist Michel Strickmann turned his attention to the study of homa fire sacrifices, specifically in the East Asian context. Strickmann questioned why, given the surplus of material and opportunities for direct observation, Western scholars have neglected a comparative study of homa for so long. He makes the case that the basic structural homogeneity of homa transcends sectarian, geographical, and cultural boundaries, and thus it clearly calls for a comparative study in its own right.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Buddhist Permutations and Symbolism of Fire</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/02_Symbolic_and_Comparative_Studies/02_Buddhist_Permutations_and_Symbolism_of_Fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/02_Symbolic_and_Comparative_Studies/02_Buddhist_Permutations_and_Symbolism_of_Fire/</guid>
      <description>Tadeusz Skorupski
THIS ESSAY OFFERS an unpretentious survey of the conceptual and yogic permutations of fire and is based on a selection of Vedic and Buddhist sources. Part One provides an overview of the Vedic perceptions of fire and fire sacrifices, and is intended to serve as a background scenario to the Buddhist interpretations of fire. Part Two ascertains the Buddhist reinterpretation of the Vedic fires and sacrifices, and sketches the Buddhist assimilation of the god Agni and homa rituals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 The Structure of Japanese Buddhist *Homa*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/02_Symbolic_and_Comparative_Studies/03_The_Structure_of_Japanese_Buddhist_Homa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/02_Symbolic_and_Comparative_Studies/03_The_Structure_of_Japanese_Buddhist_Homa/</guid>
      <description>Musashi Tachikawa
THE SACRED AND THE PROFANE The understanding of religion I continue to find most useful is that it is a form of purposeful action performed with consciousness of the distinction between the sacred and the profane. The distinction between sacred and profane will be familiar to most readers as that of the late Professor Mircea Eliade.1 Although this fundamental idea has been critiqued by various authors in the years since Eliade’s productive life, I continue to find it heuristically useful for analyzing the ritual process.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
