<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;05 Gaṅgā Snāna on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;05 Gaṅgā Snāna on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Puṇya and Pāpa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/01_puNya_and_pApa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/01_puNya_and_pApa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A background for the introduction to Puṇya and Pāpa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“What do puṇya and pāpa mean? Generally no one ponders about that. The words—&lt;em&gt;‘Puṇya&lt;/em&gt; is accrued”, “&lt;em&gt;Pāpa&lt;/em&gt; has perished”—uttered by people casually, sometime sound as though they have better knowledge than those who have understood them clearly. But, are they visible to the naked eyes like the coming and going of, say a cow or a calf? Then what are they? A solid? Liquid? Gas? What is their form? Where are they located? How long do they exist? They are not meant for animals right? If they are applicable only to human beings, where do they remain and how long? Don’t they get reduced to ashes along with the person who has earned them, after he dies? Such questions naturally arise. They can be comprehended only when they are seen through the discriminating eyes of jnānis. Merit and sin are a kind of distinctive marks (impressions) recorded on the gramophone plate of the mind. They are also called &lt;em&gt;Samskāras&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Vāsanās&lt;/em&gt;. The impressions causing happiness are called &lt;em&gt;Puṇya&lt;/em&gt; and the ones that cause misery are called &lt;em&gt;Pāpa&lt;/em&gt;. Both these are marks imprinted on the mind. It is almost impossible to erase these inner impressions. They do not perish even when the soul leaves the body. As evident from the words “मनष्षष्ठानीन्द्रियाणि प्रकृतिस्थानि कर्षति”, the mind also goes with him. All the old records of impressions will be present in the mind. They stay with the person as long as the relationship between the &lt;em&gt;jīva&lt;/em&gt; and the mind exists. These marks do not touch the person who crosses the wheel of mind itself and flies to the place of Brahman. In all other persons, the impressions of &lt;em&gt;puṇya&lt;/em&gt; bring happiness and the impressions of pāpa bring misery, and this phenomenon exists for ever. Deeds performed to imprint the marks of merit lead to happiness, and the ones contrary to that, lead to misery.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Gaṅgā eminence</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/02_gangA_eminence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/02_gangA_eminence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The eminence of the holy waters of Gaṅgā&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt; means something which gives &lt;em&gt;mukti&lt;/em&gt; (‘सद्गतिं गमयतीति गङ्गा’) The word applies to a goddess and also to the river presided over by that goddess. &lt;em&gt;Śāstras&lt;/em&gt; and traditions openly praise the holy bath in the sacred river in similitude with the (&lt;em&gt;dhyāna&lt;/em&gt;) of that goddess. They profusely praise not just the holy bath in the river and drinking of its sacred water, but also the very sight and the remembrance of it. (A few of) such extolling statements are collected as under.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Gaṅgā - ailments and health</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/03_gangA_-_ailments_and_health/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/03_gangA_-_ailments_and_health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;03 Gaṅgā - ailments and health&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The power of Gaṅgā to cure ailments and to bestow health.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many Ayurvedic texts tell us that, besides absolving people of sins, and blessing with &lt;em&gt;Sadgati&lt;/em&gt;, the water of &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt; is very tasty, removes a number of diseases, and helps to acquire good health.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“All the rivers which take their origin on the slopes of the &lt;em&gt;Himālaya&lt;/em&gt; mountains have medicinal value. Their waters consumed by &lt;em&gt;devarshis&lt;/em&gt; are really beneficial” says &lt;em&gt;Caraka&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Modern views</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/04_Modern_views/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/04_Modern_views/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Views on the quality (properties) of Gaṅgā by people belonging to other religions, and experiments by modern physicians and their opinions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;History tells us that the healthy qualities of the waters of &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt; have attracted not just the Hindus, but the followers of other religions also who were cognizant of its use and were dxiligently consuming it. A travelogue writer by name Iben Batuta tells that Mohammed Bin Tughlak used to get &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt; water from Doulathabād regularly. And it would take forty days to reach him. (Gibb’s Translation, P. 183)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Gaṅgatīrtha qualities</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/05_gangatIrtha_qualities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/05_gangatIrtha_qualities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A Discussion on the praise of the qualities of &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgatīrtha&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a) A discussion on its capacity to cure diseases&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We have already noted scriptural evidences and also the statements of modern physicians based on experiments, which declare that &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgatīrtha&lt;/em&gt; has the potential to remove sins and cure physical ailments. Here, some people argue “Only because it has the power to cure bodily ailments and improve health, it is called holy water.” And they comment—“The reason for this belief is the presence of some special chemicals in that water which absorb the bacteria in the water and kill them. The cholera bacteria themselves get dissolved and die in it! The human body is benefited most by the use of this kind of water! That is why our ancestors who understood this, called &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt; holy and attached religious importance to that.” But this is a wrong opinion. Because, many substances prescribed as medicines which fecilitate health and nourishment are prohibited for consumption when one is healthy. And they are not considered sacred just because they are healthy. On the contrary, persons who pursue spirituality seriously are barred from consuming them, when their health is alright.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Representative of Principles-a symbol</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/06_Representative_of_Principles-a_symbol/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/06_Representative_of_Principles-a_symbol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;06 Representative of Principles-a symbol&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“The river of &lt;em&gt;jnāna&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; itself is the spiritual &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt;. This is nothing but the image of God in the form of water.”-So say the &lt;em&gt;jnānis&lt;/em&gt;. Also, we come across compositions of &lt;em&gt;jnānis&lt;/em&gt; which express the following sense.-“The &lt;em&gt;Idā&lt;/em&gt; nādī in our body is &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Piṅgalā&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;Yamunā&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Sushumnā&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;Sarasvatī&lt;/em&gt;. And the place of confluence of these three viz. the place of meditational immersion between eyebrows (&lt;em&gt;bhrūmadhya&lt;/em&gt; is nothing but the &lt;em&gt;tīrtharājaprayāga&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 The map of tattvas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/07_The_map_of_tattvas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/07_The_map_of_tattvas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Śrī Raṅgamahāguru used to expound-“The basin of Gaṅgā and the holy pilgrimages along its banks are indeed the maps drawn in the land of Bhārata by mother nature. This can be made clear by one or two examples.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lord &lt;em&gt;Mahādeva&lt;/em&gt;, who had held &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt; captive in his head, laid her down at &lt;em&gt;Bindusaras,&lt;/em&gt; to bless &lt;em&gt;Bhagīratha&lt;/em&gt;. We see in the &lt;em&gt;Rāmāyaṇa&lt;/em&gt; that the river branched into seven streams while descending.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 The forms and features of Goddess *Gaṅgā*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/08_The_forms_and_features_of_Goddess_gangA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/08_The_forms_and_features_of_Goddess_gangA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;08 The forms and features of Goddess &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Āgamas&lt;/em&gt;, history and &lt;em&gt;purāṇas&lt;/em&gt; proclaim Goddess &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt; as a river of divine knowledge, a stream of &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; and an embodiment of the supreme power of the Almighty. In the &lt;em&gt;dhyānaśloka&lt;/em&gt; of that river, it is described that &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt; has a unique third eye, holds a lotus, a pot and a rosary in her hands, sports &lt;em&gt;varadamudrā&lt;/em&gt;, and has a crocodile as her vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 Ordinary view</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/09_Ordinary_view/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/09_Ordinary_view/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Answers coming from an ordinary vision&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When viewed ordinarily, these appear to be the forms imagined by a poet. “As &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt; is in the form of a river, a water filled pot is placed in her hand. The small quantity of water that can be filled in the &lt;em&gt;kalaśa&lt;/em&gt;, later expands and flows as a great river.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“The term &lt;em&gt;tīrtha&lt;/em&gt; also means &lt;em&gt;āgama&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;vidyā&lt;/em&gt; (निपानागमयोस्तीर्थं). To suggest that the garland of letters i.e. the alphabet is the mother of all learning, the poet has presented an &lt;em&gt;akshamāla&lt;/em&gt; (rosary) in one of her hands.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Exrta-ordinary view</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/10_Exrta-ordinary_view/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/10_Exrta-ordinary_view/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;10 Exrta-ordinary view&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Answers that are perceptible to the extraordinary vision&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But, when the disposition (of a person) is purified and the &lt;em&gt;tattvas&lt;/em&gt; are pursued with an inner vision, it can be realized that they (the form of &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt; and the parapheralia) are not mere imageries but sublime forms that are clearly and naturally visible in the divine ground. In the chapter &lt;em&gt;‘Devatā vigrahatattvādhikaraṇa&lt;/em&gt; of the &lt;em&gt;Brahmasūtras&lt;/em&gt;, the subject matter viz., whether the gods have forms or not, has been discussed, and it has been established that they do have forms. And, just because of this, one need not believe that (gods have forms). It should be clearly understood that they are forms which have been seen, being seen and are going to be seen, directly, by pious persons who undertake a spiritual inward journey in the body called &lt;em&gt;Brahmapura&lt;/em&gt;. Also, it is not impossible that those principles and their paraphelnalia could be seen manifestly, by the will of God who is the almighty, &lt;em&gt;Satyakāma&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Satyaksaṅkalpa&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 Some problems</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/11_Some_problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/11_Some_problems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some problems posed by the stories relating to &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt; is a river which takes its birth at the top of the &lt;em&gt;Himālayas&lt;/em&gt;. Let us believe that its water has the power to cure a number of ailments. But &lt;em&gt;Itihāsas, purāṇas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;āgamas&lt;/em&gt; pronounce strange statements about the river. “It is the holy water which was in the &lt;em&gt;Kamanḍalu&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Brahma Deva.&lt;/em&gt; When he (i.e. &lt;em&gt;Brahma&lt;/em&gt;) the Lord of &lt;em&gt;Satyaloka&lt;/em&gt;, washed the lotus feet of &lt;em&gt;Trivikrama Nārāyaṇa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Gaṅgā&lt;/em&gt; took birth (there). There-after, she ascended the head of &lt;em&gt;Śiva&lt;/em&gt; the most auspicious, and later, due to the efforts of the great ascetic &lt;em&gt;Bhagīratha&lt;/em&gt;, she was made to descend to the earth and the nether worlds. She also happened to flow out of the ears of the sage &lt;em&gt;Jāhnu&lt;/em&gt;. The gods took her, who was a sibling of &lt;em&gt;Umā,&lt;/em&gt; to heavens for their work.” We come across such statements about her origin (&lt;em&gt;Rāmāyaṇa&lt;/em&gt; 1-53 to 65-&lt;em&gt;Śrīmadbhāgavata&lt;/em&gt; 8-21).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
