<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 Pātaka, Prāyaścitta, Karmavipāka on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 Pātaka, Prāyaścitta, Karmavipāka on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Pātaka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/01_pAtaka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/01_pAtaka/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER I&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PĀTAKA, PRĀYAŚCITTA AND KARMAVIPAKA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Sins, expiations and the residual consequences of sins).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bootlot w&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER I&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;bosalogatott&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;20 The Article on sin in Hasting&amp;rsquo;s Encyclopædia of Religion and Ethics (vol. 11) will clearly show how the idea of sin varies from religion to religion, from age to age and from coun try to country. We are concerned here with the growth and developinent of the doctrine of sin in India from Vedic times to the medieval digests and commentaries on Dharmaśāstra, do&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Means of Reducing Consequences of Sins</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/02_Means_of_Reducing_Consequences_of_Sins/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/02_Means_of_Reducing_Consequences_of_Sins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER II&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;MEANS OF REDUCING CONSEQUENCES OF SINS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER II&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;MEANS OF REDUCING CONSEQUENCES OF SINS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Confession-In Ap. Dh, S. I. 9. 24. 15, 1. 10. 28, 19, 1. 10.29.1 it is prescribed that the person undergoing a penance for being an abhiśasta or for unjustly forsaking his wife or for the murder of a learned brāhmaṇa has to declare his misdeed while begging for alms to support himself. The Vedic student who was guilty of sexual intercourse had also to proclaim his lapse while begging at seven houses (Gaut, 23.18, Manu XI. 122 ).98&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Prayaścitta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/03_prayashchitta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/03_prayashchitta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER III PRAYAŚCITTA; ITS ORIGIN, DERITATION&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;AND JEANING&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER III PRĀYAŚCITTA; ITS ORIGIN, DERIVATION&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;AND MEANING&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is now necessary to turn to prāyaścittas as removers of sin. A number of subjects will fall to be treated here,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, an attempt must be made to understand the etymo logy and meaning of the word &amp;lsquo;prāyascitta&amp;rsquo; in ancient times. There are two forms of the word, prāyaścitti and prāyaścitta, which occur in Vedic works without distinction of meaning and both forms are fairly old, though prāyaścitti appears to be the older of the two. The form prāyascitti frequently occurs in the Tai, S. (as in II, 1.2,4, II. 1 4.1, III. 1,3,2-3, V. 1.9.3, V. 3.12.1) 136a. In some of these passages no question of sin arises. The word means &amp;lsquo;doing some thing which would get rid of some accidental happening or mishap such as the breaking of an ukha (a pot or saucepan for boiling or cooking) or the sun&amp;rsquo;s losing its brilliance,&amp;rsquo; In Tai. S. V. 3.12.1 the word is used in the sense of an expiation for a sin. So even in very old books the word had two shades of meaning. The Kausitaki137 Br. (vi, 12) states : &amp;ldquo;&amp;ldquo;they say &amp;lsquo;whatever mistake or excess occurs in the sacrifice that affects the priest brahmā, that he treats with the three fold learning (i. e. the three Vedas)&amp;rdquo;. The word also occurs in the Atharvaveda XIV. 1.30, Vāj. S. 39.12 (in close proximity to niskrti), in the Ait. Br. V. 27, in the Sat. Br. IV.5.7.1, VII. 1.4.9, XI. 5.3.8, XII. 4.1.6 and in other works also. The form prāyaścitta occurs in Kausitaki Br. V. 9, VI 12 and elsewhere. The Āśv. Śr. III. 10.38 and śānkhāyana Śr. III. 19.1 respectively employ the words prāyascitti and prāyaścitta138 In Pār. gr. I.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Penances for Particular Sins</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/04_Penances_for_Particular_Sins/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/04_Penances_for_Particular_Sins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER IV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PENANCES FOR PARTICULAR SINS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER IV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PENANCES FOR PARTICULAR SINS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is now proper to turn to the penances prescribed for individual sins of different types (grave sins, minor sins and the like). It may be noted that the smrtis contain numerous prāyaścittas for the same sin and that it is often difficult to reconcile all the dicta. The commentaries and digests such as the Mit, and the Prāyaścitta-viveka therefore try to assign to each penance an appropriate provision, looking to all the circum stances noted above (i.e. they are bent on &amp;lsquo;visayavyavasthā&amp;rsquo;).206a In this work, it is not necessary to set out in detail the numerous penances for numberless lapses that are prescribed in the several smrtis and digests. In the Sabdakalpadruma (part III) there is an analysis from the Prāyaścitta-viveka alone of the several lapses, the penances for them, the number of cows to be donated as substitutes, the monetary equivalents when even cows cannot be donated and the daksinā in each case, which occupy pages 321 to 364. Setting out all these lapses together with the penances for them would only be a matter of academic interest and of no practical value, as almost all the prāyaścittag have become antiquated and are hardly ever performed now except in the form of gifts of cows or money to brāhmanas, pilgrimages and recitation of Vedic mantras or japa of the names of some favourite deity such as Visnu or Siva. Therefore only a few typical sins alone will be taken for treatment here and later on a list of all penances with brief descriptions will be furnished&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Names of All Prāyaścittas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/05_Names_of_All_prAyashchittas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/05_Names_of_All_prAyashchittas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER V NAMES OF ALL PRĀYAŚCITTAS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER V NAMES OF ALL PRĀYAŚCITTAS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now all the prāyascittas mentioned in the smrtis and digests will be arranged in alphabetical order (Sanskrit, transliterated into English), excepting mere hymns, fasts, &amp;amp;c. and brief explanations and references will be added to each.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;AGHAMARSANA-( The hymn Rg. X.190.1-3).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is prescribed as a penance for all sins by even the most ancient Dharmaśāstra works such as Gaut. 24.11, Baud. Dh. S. IV. 2.19-20, Vas. 26.8, Manu XI.259–260, Yāj. III.301, Vispu Dh, S. 55.7, Sankha 18.1-2 and others. They prescribe that if a man recites (for three days, according to Haradatta ) the Agharmarsana hymn thrice in the day while immersed in water for a bath, he is freed from all sins and that this penance is equal in sanctification to the bath at the end of the Asvamedha sacrifice. The Pr. Sāra p. 199 speaks of the Aghamarṣana vrata. He has to fast for three days and stand up by day and sit up by night and donate a milch cow at the end, Sankha 18.1-2 and Visṇu Dh. S.46.1-9 prescribe the details.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Consequences of Not Undergoing Penances</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/06_Consequences_of_Not_Undergoing_Penances/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/1_pAtaka_prAyashchitta_karmavipAka/06_Consequences_of_Not_Undergoing_Penances/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER VI -&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CONSEQUENCES OF NOT UNDERGOING PENANCES&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER VI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CONSEQUENCES OF NOT UNDERGOING PENANCES&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If a sinner did not undergo a prāyaścitta, the Smộtis, Purānas, medieval digests declared that he had to suffer dire and far-reaching consequences. Yāj. III. 221 declares that men addicted to sins, who feel no repentance and who (therefore ) do not undergo the proper penances, fall into painful and horri ble hells. Manu XIT. 54 ff and Yaj. III, 206 ff provide that those guilty of grave (and other) sins after having passed numbers of years in hells and suffered the tortures of horrible hells are born again in this world because of (the remnants of their) evil actions in different forms such as lower animals, insects, trees and shrubs &amp;amp;c. Manu XI. 53 ordains that one should always perform penance in order to free oneself from sins, since those who have not destroyed their sins (by means of prāyaścittas) are born again endowed with disgraceful marks (such as having bad nails, black teeth &amp;amp;c.). Manu XI. 48 also emphasizes that wicked men suffer mal-formations owing to their wicked deeds committed in this very life or in a former life. The Vispu purāṇa 355 echoes the words of Yāj. III. 221. The Visnudharmo ttara declares 356 that those (sinners ) who do not undergo penances nor are punished by the king fall into hell and are born also as lower animals and even after attaining human bodies they become marked (with bodily defects). Viṣnu Dh. S. (44, 1-10) prescribes 357 that evil-doers, having experienced the horrors of hell pass into animal bodies and that those guilty of atipātakas, mahāpātakas, anupātakas, upapātakas, jāti&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
