<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Class, Caste, and Genes</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/2012-01-13_class-caste-and-genes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/2012-01-13_class-caste-and-genes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://westhunt.wordpress.com/2012/01/13/class-caste-and-genes/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Class, Caste, and Genes&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsobserver.com/2012/01/12/1771519/more-conflict-seen-between-rich.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;by Sabrina Tavernise appeared in the &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; a few days ago&#xA;describing increasing perceptions of class conflict in America, and&#xA;there is a lot of recent commentary in the press about&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.economicmobility.org/reports_and_research/other?id=0017&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;report from the Pew Charitable Trust that claims there is less class&#xA;mobility here than in several other northern countries.  It is not very&#xA;clear to me what the complaints really are or what alternatives exist.&#xA;If there is any substantial heritability of merit, where merit is&#xA;whatever leads to class mobility, then mobility ought to turn classes&#xA;into hereditary castes surprisingly rapidly.+++(4)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>chinna-jIyAr on harmony</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/chinna-jIyAr_on_harmony/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/chinna-jIyAr_on_harmony/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: halleyji&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is from a 3yr old video. He has said such content as recently as two days ago. So I am not making it up and all this is public content. It is the traditional stance on Equality as well. Vouched by many other Acharyas. Approximate Translation of Jeeyar&amp;rsquo;s talk follows:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;People keep getting into fights with each other in the name of politics, in the name of caste or in many cases in the name of religion. What shall we do? Shall we remove castes instead? (kula nirmoolana) There are many movements today in the society. They say caste (kulam) is opium. It needs to be eliminated. You keep hearing of such in newspapers. If you remove it will caste go away? Will it just vanish?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>jAti - collective memory</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/jAti_collective-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/jAti_collective-memory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of Dharmaśāstra, jāti is based on collective memory. Medhātithi notes this on Manusmṛti 10.5.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;infinite-regress&#34;&gt;Infinite regress&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Generally the definitions of Brāhmaṇa etc. as presented in Dharmaśāstra-texts, assume the prior knowledge of who a Brāhmaṇa etc. is.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The definitions are like; &amp;lsquo;A Brāhmaṇa is the one born of duly wedded Brāhmaṇa &amp;amp; Brāhmaṇī&amp;rsquo;. Now someone may ask; on what basis is his father a Brāhmaṇa (similar about his mother)? Such questioning and lack of a definitive proof will lead to an infinite regress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>King and pratiloma-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/king-and-pratilomas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/king-and-pratilomas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Bṛhaspatismṛti, the king is told to protect the dharmas of those born of pratilomas, those residing in forts, and the dharmas of specific deśa &amp;amp; jāti. Even though, elsewhere they may be punishable, but for them they shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be so, or else they would develop aversion for the king, which&amp;rsquo;ll lead to destruction of his power and treasury. Following are some examples of dharmas given:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dākṣiṇātya dvijas marry the sibling of their mothers, etc.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the Madhyadeśa, hired workers &amp;amp; artisans eat cow meat.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Those in the east eat fish and the eastern women indulge in adultery.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the north, women drink intoxicating drinks, men touch women undergoing menstruation, and the twin brother marries (?) the widow of his brother.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For these acts, no punishment and prāyaścitta is required.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KL brAhmaNa-expulsion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/kl-brAhmaNa-expulsion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/kl-brAhmaNa-expulsion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;विस्तारः (द्रष्टुं नोद्यम्)&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If a Brahmin fail to observe his or her duties, the kings of Kochi had power to take away all the privilege and banish them from the caste.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Land of Perumals by Francis Day. It&amp;rsquo;s from 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A Brahman should not trade, join in popular conversation, music, dancing, or any thing else inconsistent with a grave deportment: he ought to shun temporal honours, to perform three great actions, read their sacred books, have a son, and offer regular sacrifices: after which, he may in due time, make over his duties to his son. They are not unfrequently expelled their caste, for heinous, and even trivial offences: the ceremonies which are elsewhere employed on this occasion, are here unpractised. A Namboorie woman who is sentenced to lose her caste, is sent to Tripoonterah, where a stage is erected, on which she stands, holding an umbrella over her head. The Dellawah then reads the sentence to the assembled people, declares her expelled her caste, and taking her umbrella, breaks its stick in two pieces. Persons willing to take the woman may now do so, on giving a written pro- mise, to support her whilst she lives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stranger Ari</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/stranger-ari/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/stranger-ari/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: TW conversation between AryAMsha and MT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;hostis-xenos&#34;&gt;Hostis Xenos&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Latin &amp;lsquo;hostis&amp;rsquo; (hostile) &amp;amp; the Greek &amp;lsquo;xenos&amp;rsquo; (xenophobic) did not always have a -ve sense. They originally used to mean &amp;lsquo;guest&amp;rsquo;, someone in a reciprocal relationship with your clan. As the Greco-Romans lost their clannish society, &amp;ldquo;guests&amp;rdquo; became &amp;ldquo;enemies&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;strangers&amp;rdquo;. As their clans grew, cities came up, the polis replaced the basic interactional unit of one dempotis / paterfamilias with another, as they became nations from tribes; the clan-clan reciprocality ended. You were now either &amp;ldquo;in&amp;rdquo; the civitas or &amp;ldquo;out of it&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>V1 - v2, mother - father</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/v1-v2-mother-father/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/v1-v2-mother-father/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thread by @termite_colony on Thread Reader App – Thread Reader App&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thinking about this for a couple of days.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In a way, I think Brahmins and Kshatriyas were the maternal and paternal poles of India society. This analogy helps understand many things&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;how V1s were entirely dependent on the benevolence of their V2 rulers and larger society (the mother is dependent on the patriarch of the house and also the young strong kids for material resources needed for the entire house)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;why V2s felt so protective of their V1s (self-explanatory)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;why it was such a taboo to hurt V1s (&amp;ldquo;would you hurt your mother?&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;why V2s found a confidant, partner, advisor in V1s with whom they could share the responsibility of running the kingdom.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;why foreign powers tried to attack V1s/V1 centers (temples, universities, etc) to weaken the kingdom (if you want to hurt a family you&amp;rsquo;d try to hurt their women) and last but not the least,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;how V1s at times acted as a moral counterbalance against the king and helped all other subjects (from all varnas) state their case in front of or against the ruler (the mother can appeal to emotion (dharma) to get the father to act differently - &amp;ldquo;excessive taxes is adharma&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;capital punishments are adharma&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;stealing people&amp;rsquo;s wives is adharma&amp;rdquo;, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We see (/saw till about 100-200 years ago) so many dharmic V4s because they really had no reason to hate V1s. V1s were compassionate to them when no one else was.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>कलौ ब्राह्मण्यम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/kalau-brAhmaNyam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/kalau-brAhmaNyam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अब्राह्मणेषु सर्वेषु&lt;br&gt;&#xA;सर्वस्मिन् ब्राह्मण-ब्रुवे ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;नाम-धारक-मात्रेषु&lt;br&gt;&#xA;श्रोत्रियेषु महत्स्व् अपि॥१२॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सर्वेष्व् अपि च वेदैक-&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पारगेषु महात्मसु।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ब्रह्मत्वम् एक-सामान्यात्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;तिष्ठत्य् एव ह्यनश्वरम् ॥ १३ ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तन्-महत्-तारतम्येन&lt;br&gt;&#xA;न्यूनं चाऽधिकम् एव च।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;महच् च सुमहच् चापि&lt;br&gt;&#xA;दोष-युक्तं गुणोत्तरम्॥१४॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;निर्दोषम् इति भेदेन&lt;br&gt;&#xA;बहुधाभि(हि)मृतेति तत्(स्मृतं)  ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;सर्व-कर्मैक-शून्ये ऽस्मिन्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;कलौ पापैकसङ्कुले॥१५॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;कर्मानुरूपं ब्रह्मत्वं&lt;br&gt;&#xA;प्रतिष्ठति हि भूतले ।&#xA;तन्न दूष्यं दुराधर्षं&lt;br&gt;&#xA;युगधर्मानुरूपकम्॥ १६&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;कपिलस्मृतिः&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In all (six kinds of) Abrāhmaṇas (lowly Brāhmaṇas), in Brāhmaṇabruva (one who merely says, &amp;ldquo;I am Brāhmaṇa&amp;rdquo;, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t perform actions of a Brāhmaṇa), in those who merely possess the name (Brāhmaṇa), in the great Śrotriyas, and in the noble experts of Vedas, the indestructible Brahmatva (Brāhmaṇatva) stays as being one thing which is common. Through gradation, it is greater, great, more, less, faulty, more in quality, faultless, and hence through (such) difference, it is ? . In this Kaliyuga, where all (scripturally ordained) actions are absent, and where sin alone is abundant, Brahmatva shall remain on the earth in accordance with actions (performed by the aforementioned, as more or less), and it shall not be condemned, (because) it is invincible and as per Yugadharma.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
