<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;GA on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/GA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;GA on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/GA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Defining Hindudharma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/GA/2021-03-28_defining-hindudharma-the-tanunaptra-metaphor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/GA/2021-03-28_defining-hindudharma-the-tanunaptra-metaphor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://aryanthought.wordpress.com/2021/03/28/defining-hindudharma-the-tanunaptra-metaphor/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Defining Hindudharma: The Tānūnaptra Metaphor&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;How can we understand Hindudharma’s unity? Why is it not artificial but theologically and divinely meaningful?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the outset it must be stated that this piece is not an exercise in discursive reasoning, or some carefully worked argument based on some first principles or axioms. The “reasoning” here is rather analogous and more amenable to those with the intuition to grasp ideas through analogies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convert privilege</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/GA/convert-privilege/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/GA/convert-privilege/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While certain paths are open to MahāmlecchādayaH by initiation, a problem they undeniably present is that they can’t be content with being passive spectators. They have to be leaders &amp;amp; reshape the path/system in their image. No ritual space can be closed off to them.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A certain Āṅglika Mantravādī of the “Adhvamata” of the Cīnas in this realm is a good example of this tendency.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Another example is this priest +++(rAmi sivan/ rAma rAmanuja?)+++ initiated into the Pāñcarātra, who has taken it upon himself to waive off the applicability of adhikāravidhi for… well… himself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convert&#39;s caste</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/GA/conversion_to_hinduism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/GA/conversion_to_hinduism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Conversion to Hindu Dharma: Past Precedents, Present Challenges and Future Possibilities&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;August 23, 2022&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Ghora Angirasa and Kavita Krishna Meegama&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Can one (particularly a non-Indian foreigner) convert to Hindu Dharma? How does caste feature in this (if at all)? What are the basic duties of a Hindu convert, who may not have any particular sampradāya affiliation?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;conversion-to-hindu-dharma&#34;&gt;Conversion to Hindu Dharma&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is an ongoing quest, especially among those who practice yoga and meditation, to dwell deeper into the secrets of life and living. The more they tend to reach out sincerely the closer will they get towards vaidika dharma or sanātana dharma, Hinduism if you will. Once they stand on the threshold of this oldest continuous surviving tradition which is at once a philosophy, spirituality, religion, way of life and culture, they have reached home. Yet many among such seekers do not know how to navigate their way about such vastness, in awe of such freedom and grandeur they tend to lose interest and revert back to what they are comfortable with, or take solace in blaming Hindu dharma for being so complicated and illegible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tanunaptra in/exclusions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/GA/tanunaptra-inclusions-exclusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/GA/tanunaptra-inclusions-exclusions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/GhorAngirasa/status/1706341251610763536&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hindudharma is akin to the Tānūnaptra Covenant of the Śruti. As the Śatapatha warns us, we must be careful about whom we admit into the Tānūnaptra as there will be a commingling of one’s desired assets with those of others which we may not like.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The questions which arise: Have we allowed the tradition in contention into the Tānūnaptra-like covenant of Hindudharma &amp;amp; therefore become bound to protect it? If yes, is there any clear act of betrayal of the Tānūnaptra, which would justify its ouster by us? The Tānūnaptra metaphor is a very useful way of approaching the problems, which are specific to an accretive model of religious development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
