<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;4 Tīrthayātrā on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;4 Tīrthayātrā on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>11 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/11_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/11_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;TIRTHAYĀTRĀ (pilgrimages to holy places)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institute&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SECTION IV CHAPTER XI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;TIRTHAYĀTRĀ (pilgrimages to holy places )&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All religions have laid great emphasis on the sacredness of certain localities and have either enjoined or recommended with great insistence pilgrimages to them. Among the five incumbent practical religious duties1237 of a Moslem, pilgrimage at least once in his life to Mecca and Medina, the birth place and burial place of the prophet Mohammad, is one. The four places of pilgrimage for Buddhists have been the place of the birth of Buddha (Lumbini or Rummindei), the place where he attained perfect enlightenment (Bodh Gayā), the place where he set in motion the wheel of dharma by delivering his first sermon (at Sārnāth near Benares ) and the place where he passed away into the state of nirvana (Kusinārā). Vide Mahāparinibbānasutta (S. B. E. vol. XI. p. 90). For Christians Jerusalem has been the holiest place and no religious com munity except the Christians undertook in historic times several great military pilgrimages. The crusades were launched to free the Holy Land of Christians from the domination of Moslems. In spite of what Gibbon says 1238 somewhat cynically about those who joined the crusades, it must be admitted that there were thousands among the crusaders who risked their lives and fortunes in the pursuit of an ideal. In India holy places have played a very important part. Large rivers, mountains and forests have always been venerated as sacred1239&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 The Ganges</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/12_The_Ganges/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/12_The_Ganges/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THE GANGES&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XII omodoro&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THE GANGES&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Since the Ganges is the holiest of rivers and since such highly esteemed tirthas as Kanakhala, Haridvāra, Prayāga and Kāśi are situated on it, it would be most proper to begin the treatment of individual tirthas with the Ganges.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;It has been already seen (p. 556) how the Ganges is the first among the many rivers invoked in the famous Nadāstuti hymn (Rg. X.75.5-6). In Rg.1323 VI. 45.31 we have the word &amp;lsquo;Gāngyah&amp;rsquo; which most probably means &amp;lsquo;growing on the Ganges&amp;rsquo;. In the Satapatha Brāhmana XIII. 5.4.11 and 13 and Ait. Br. 39. 9 the victories and sacrifices of Bharata Daussanti on the Ganga and Yamunā are mentioned. In Sat. Br. XIII. 5.4.11 and 13 an ancient gātha is quoted &amp;lsquo;At Nadapit the Apsaras Sakuntala conceived Bharata who after conquering the whole earth brought to Indra more than 1000 horses meet for sacrifice.&amp;rsquo; The Mahābhārata (Anuśāsana 26. 26-103) and the Purāṇas (such as Nāradiya, Uttarārdha, chap. 38-45 and 51. 1-48, Padma V. 60. 1-127, Agni chap. 110, Matsya chap. 180-185, Padma, Adikhanda. chap. 33-37) contain hundreds of verses eulogising the greatness and the sanctifying activity of the Ganges. The Skandapurāṇa, Kāśikhanda, chap. 29 (verses 17-168) contains one thousand names of the Ganges. It is not possible to reproduce here even a small fraction of what is said in these works about the Ganges. To most men in India great rivers like the Ganges great mountains like the Himālaya present a double aspect, viz, the physical aspect and the spiritual aspect. A great river apart from its volume of water is deemed to have a spiri tual or divine life which animates it. Tylor (in &amp;lsquo;Primitive Culture&amp;rsquo;, 2nd ed.p 477) observes &amp;lsquo;What we call inanimate objects rivers, stones, trees, weapons and so forth-are treated as living intelligent beings, talked to, propitiated, punished for the harm they do.&amp;rsquo; There are separate treatises devoted to the glorifica tion of the Ganges and the pilgrimage to it such as the&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;POONA&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 Kāśī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/13_kAshI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/13_kAshI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;KAŚĪ&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institute&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;KAŚĪ&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is hardly any city in the world that can claim greater antiquity, greater continuity and greater popular veneration than Banaras. Banaras has been a holy city for at least thirty centuries. No city in India arouses the religious emotions of Hindus as much as Kāśi does. To the Hindu mind it represents great and unbroken traditions of religious sanctity and learning. It is a miniature of Hindu life through the ages in all its great complexities and contradictions. Not only Hinduism with its numerous sects has flourished here for numberless centuries, but the principles of Buddhism, one of the great religions of the world, were first proclaimed here by Sākyamuni after he received Enlightenment at Bodh-Gayā under the Bodhi tree. Thousands of verses are found in the epics and purāṇas about Banaras. Several volumes have been written about Banares during the last hundred years.1405 It would be impossible to do justice here to this vast mass of literature on Banaras. I shall briefly deal with the important topics relating to Banaras. In olden times the name was spelt as Benares, but recently as Banaras, which will be retained here (except in quotations).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 Gayā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/14_gayA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/14_gayA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XIV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;GAYA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institute&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XIV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;GAYA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Gayā occupies a unique place in the hearts of all pious Hindus even in these days. Hundreds of pages have been written about the history, the antiquities, the architectural remains of Gayā, the sacred places in and round about Gayā, the śrāddha rites performed in Gayā and about Gayāwals (the priests of Gayā). It is not possible to deal with this vast mass in this work. But it is impossible not to say a few words about the many conflicting views on certain important matters put forward by scholars for about three quarters of a century. Those who are deeply interested in the history and antiquities of Gaya should carefully read the following books and papers; Dr. Rajendralal Mitra&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Buddha-Gaya&amp;rsquo; with 51 plates (1878); General Cunningham&amp;rsquo;s ‘Mahābodhi&amp;rsquo; with 31 plates at the end (1892); L.S.S. O&amp;rsquo;Malley&amp;rsquo;s District Gazetteer of Gayā, vol. XII and J.A.S.B. for 1903 LXXII, No. 3, pp. 1-11 on &amp;lsquo;Gayāśrāddha and Gayāvals;&amp;rsquo; Indian Antiquary, vol. X pp. 339-340 for a Chinese Inscription at Buddha Gayā dated in a Chinese date corresponding to 1033 A, D, and pp. 341-347 for Inscriptions at Gayā, one of which is engraved in a temple of the Sun near a tank &amp;lsquo;Daksinamānasa&amp;rsquo; near the Visnupada, dated 1813 years after Buddha&amp;rsquo;s Parinirvāṇa; Indian Antiquary, vol. 16 pp. 63 ff Inscription of Yakṣapāla, son of Viśvāditya, which records the building of a temple for certain images in the 15th regnal year of the Pāla king Nayapāladeva who died in 1045 A, D., edited by Kielhorn; Dr. Benimadhav Barua&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Gayā and Buddha Gayā&amp;rsquo; in two volumes (1934) with plates; Journal of Bihar and Orissa R. Society, vol. 24 (for 1938) pp. 89-111 where Dr.J.C. Ghose deals with the antiquity of Gayā.&amp;rsquo; Some of the remarks of Dr. Ghose are most unwarranted and cannot be accepted, such as holding &amp;lsquo;maganda&amp;rsquo; in &amp;lsquo;Pramagandasya&amp;rsquo; in Rg. III. 53.14 as identical with Magadha and the explanation of &amp;lsquo;udantyāh&amp;rsquo;in the Ait. Br. as &amp;lsquo;people of sunrise.&amp;rsquo; Among medieval digests Gayā is dealt with in Kalpataru on Tirthas pp. 163-174, Tyrblade cintāmani of Vācaspati pp. 268-328, Tristhalīsetu of Narayana ) bhatta pp. 316-379, Tirthaprakāśa pp. 384-452, Tirthendi, sekhara pp. 54–59, Triṣthalisetu-sāra-sangraha of Bhattojin pp. 36-38.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 Kurukṣetra and Other Famous Tīrthas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/15_kuruxetra_and_Other_Famous_tIrthas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/15_kuruxetra_and_Other_Famous_tIrthas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;KURUKSETRA AND SOME OTHER FAMOUS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;TĪRTHAS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;COHOOD CHAPTER XV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;aaban&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;KURUKSETRA AND SOME OTHER FAMOUS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;TIRTHAS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;KURUKSETRA (25 miles east of Ambala) is a very sacred tract, the history of which is lost in the mists of anti quity. In the Rgveda X, 33.4 there is a reference to a king Kurusravana, son of Trasadasyu,1538 The Atharva-veda men tions a Kauravya husband (probably a king) who had a talk with his wife.1539 In the times of the Brāhmaṇas Kuruksetra had become a very holy land. The Sat. Br. (IV.1.5.13) narrates the legend that the gods performed a sacrifice in Kuruksetra and at first excluded the two Asvins from any share in it (S. B. E. vol. 26 p.275). The Maitrāyani Samhitā (II. 1. 4., devā vai sattramāsata Kuruksetre) and the Tai. Br. (V.1.1., devā vai sattram-āsata teṣām Kuruksetram vedir-āsit) also say that the Gods performed a satira in Kuruksetra. The idea underlying these passages appears to be this. The Vedic people of the Brāhmana period held yajñas to be the dharma par excellence, as stated in Rg. X. 90.16 (yajñena yajñam-ayajanta devāstāni dharmāni prathamānyāsan). Kuruksetra was the centre of ✓ Vedic culture in the Brāhmana period and sacrifices must have been performed there on a large scale. Hence it was called dharmaksetra and as gods were supposed to have attained their position by what men believed to be dharma (yajña, tapas &amp;amp;c.) it is stated that gods performed sattras in Kuruksetra. The same Brāhmaṇa mentions a Kauravya king Bahlika Prātipiya (XII. 9.3.3, S. B, E. vol. 44 p. 269). The Tai. Br. (1. 8.4.1) informs us that the Kuru-Pañcālas went towards the east in winter (śiśıra) and to the west in summer which was the worst season. The references in the Ait. Br. are far more instructive. The legend about Kavaṣa in which Sarasvati helps the sage has already been referred to above (p. 559 n. 1254). The Ait Br&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 List of Tīrthas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/16_List_of_tIrthas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/4_tIrthayAtrA/16_List_of_tIrthas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XVI - - LIST OF TĪRTHÁS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;row or doive Join ons is CHAPTER XVII no nomm&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;O SE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;LIST OF TĪRTHAS ditoints Lotuito&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;target ytov si o&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is merely a list of tirthas from the point of view of Dharmaśāstra and not a treatise on the Ancient Geography of India. The result is that many countries and towns that have no importance or claims as tirthas have been altogether omitted. Bauddha and Jain works on tirthas have only rarely been referred to. Many of the Purānas enumerate the moun tains and rivers of dvipas and var ṣas other than those of Jambudvipa and Bhārata-varsa such as Harivarṣa, Ramyaka varsa, Krauñcadvipa, Sālmalidvipa, but they have been exclud ed from this list. The Brahmapurāṇa (chap. 26 verses 8-83) contains a string of over 520 tirthas without hardly any certain indication of their location and the Bhīṣmaparva in chap. 9 mentions about 160 rivers with practically no indication about their location in most cases. Similarly, the Garuda (I. 81. 1-31) enumerates about 200 and Padma (VI. 129) contains 108 tirtha names. In Banaras alone I have listed about 350 sub tirthas. But there are about 1500 shrines and temples in Banaras alone. These have not been included. Each great tirtha has numerous sub-tirthas as in the Varāha-purāṇa under Mathurā, in Brahma-purāṇa under Gautami, in Vāyu-purāṇa under Gayā. Through sheer weariness or inadvertence some of these must have been left out by me and some were left out purposely on account of the absence of any importance. Besides, several tirthas that are regarded as sacred by modern people are not so treated in the Epics or purāṇas and are not even mentioned in them; many of these have been omitted in this list. Our authorities are often very vague about the location or extent of tirthas. Moreover, a number of tirthas scattered in different parts of India bear the same name (e. g. vide under Agnitirtha, Koțitirtha, Cakratīrtha, Varāhatirtha, Somatirtha). I am under great obligations to Cunningham&amp;rsquo;s *Ancient Geography of India&amp;rsquo; (ed, of 1872) and to Nundo Lal Dey&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;The Geographical Dictionary of Ancient and Medieval India&amp;rsquo; (1927). I have had occasions to differ from both, particularly from the latter. But, the space at my disposal being very limited, I could not enter into even brief discussions&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
