<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Meta-Ritual on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Meta-Ritual on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Benefits</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/benefits/</guid>
      <description>The study and practice of hindu kalpa-s is quite *addictive* and (thankfully) useful - just as some other performance arts are. Even if you discount purported supernatural benefits, many hindu rituals (with their varied mantra, tantra, svara underpinnings) are incredibly well designed.
The US army flag-hoisting ceremony and the Japanese tea ceremony are examples of very moving rituals in non-hindu contexts which may resonate with your past experience, gentle reader.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ritual reality</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/ritual_reality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/ritual_reality/</guid>
      <description>Intro &amp;ldquo;Some idiot Hindus stated that the argument that shrI dharmashAstA in his form as ayyappa is observing naiSThika brahmacharya is not a sensible one as it suggests that ayyappa is “unable to see his women devotees in the 10-50 age group as sisters or mothers”. &amp;hellip; Our deities have transcendental and most subtle bodies. They do not “eat offerings” or “observe brahmacaryam” in the same way mortals would be seen in our mundane level of reality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>saMskAra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/saMskAra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/saMskAra/</guid>
      <description>Rites of passage.
Many of our societies have abandoned such rites of passage initiations and so our children never consciously enter teenhood and then adulthood. The result is that many of them remain psychologically trapped in childhood when they are well into adulthood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>भावः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/feeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/feeling/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;उत्तम-कलानुभूतिः→ तत्र भावः&amp;rdquo; इति दृश्यताम् दैवावेशः कल्प्यतेतराम् कर्मसु। सहृदयरसिकोत्तम-साधकोत्तमयोर् अयमपि भेदो महान्। &amp;ldquo;ज्ञात्वा कर्माणि कुर्वीत&amp;rdquo; इति आर्योक्तिः Do an aesthetic study and understand the thought and feeling behind practices rather than following arbitrary looking traditional instructions - on the way to developing one&amp;rsquo;s own favored practice. I do not wish to give up my freedom to sympathetically probe, understand and decide on what my practice should be - the freedom in particular to respectfully disagree in practice with the learned traditional practitioner when the explanation is unsatisfactory &amp;mdash;and face the &amp;ldquo;consequences&amp;rdquo; from the deva-s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>स्थूल-क्रमः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/sthUla-kramaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/sthUla-kramaH/</guid>
      <description> काल-निश्चयः, मन्त्र-कल्पाद्यवगतिः, यजमान-योग्यता-सिद्धिः (सन्ध्यावन्दनाद्यनुष्ठान-पुनरारम्भेण)। मनः संस्कारः हृष्टमनसा कार्यम्। तत्र - आचमनम्, प्राणायामः, सङ्कल्पः, सात्त्विक-त्यागः … मध्ये कर्मण्य् अपि यथोचितम्। शरीर-संस्कारः स्थल-व्यवस्थापनम्, तत्संस्कारश्च द्रव्य-व्यवस्थापनम्, तत्संस्कारश्च विघ्नोपशमनम्, देवपितृब्राह्मणादिप्रीणनम् तत्र विघ्नेश्वरपूजा, पुण्याहवाचनम्, नान्दीश्राद्धम् … मुख्यं कर्म। कर्मदोषप्रायश्चित्तम् यथापेक्षम्। स्थलशुद्धिः </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
