<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Occupation differences on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Occupation differences on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Archaka job</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/archaka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/archaka/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;brahmana-s&#34;&gt;brAhmaNa-s&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Archaka-posts in certain Agamika temples were reserved for initiated brAhmaNa-s, due to such decision by a deity or a highly revered sage. Rare reservations were made for other communities as well (see &lt;a href=&#34;../ethnic-shifts/Arya-invasion/&#34;&gt;practice page&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;deities-appointing-specific-lineages&#34;&gt;Deities appointing specific lineages&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;[sEkkizAr&amp;rsquo;s periyapurANam, mANikkavAcakar - &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GhorAngirasa/status/916607415667363840&#34;&gt;TW17&lt;/a&gt;, kAmikAgama  6.6 - 6.9 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GhorAngirasa/status/916811078507618305&#34;&gt;TW17&lt;/a&gt; ].&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The vaikhAnasa samhitas mention that this community was created by Vishnu and not thru brahma. The child is initiated at the foetal stage through viShNu-bali.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;bhagavAn explicitly stated his desire to receive vaikhAnasa service only at tirumala. For 12 yrs, moolamurti was not touched by anyone.. Puja done by sri vyasaraya from outside temple, as the only descendant of bimbaadhara, appointed by raamaanuja, was an infant. If a yati of that caliber did not dare enter sanctum sanctorum, who are we?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;the mother at AvuDaiyAr temple (built by mANikkavAcaka) desires that only brAhmaNas of the rare agniveshya sUtra should serve her.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;exemption-from-devalaka-dosha&#34;&gt;Exemption from devalaka-doSha&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Such specific brAhmaNa lineages are said to be exempt from the devalaka-doSha that befalls brAhmaNa archaka-s according to the smRti-s. While others fall in status.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Even the shaivAgama which detests common brAhmaNas doing arcana- gives a max limit of 3 years for initiated common Brahmins and 6 months for uninitiated ones before they become degraded&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;non-brahmana-eligibility&#34;&gt;Non-brAhmaNa eligibility&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Pancaratra allows archakas to be from all castes subject to certain conditions.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;There are many bhajana temples with murtis where saattaadas serve. There are many bhajana temples with murtis where saattaadas serve. But the main archaka in old pancaratra temples has to be a SYV kanva shakha brom of five gotras and initiated in pancaratra diksha by his own father. &amp;hellip; The chief arcaka in shrIraNGam was handpicked from one such gotra by rAmAnuja himself.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kingship</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/kingship/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/kingship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A kShatriya had maximal theoretical legitimacy for kingship. This led rulers to claim kShatriya status, and some brAhmaNa-s (like gAgAbhaTTa - see &lt;a href=&#34;../ministership&#34;&gt;ministership&lt;/a&gt; page) to strive to make space for them within the dharmashAstra framework.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the absence of de-jure kShatriya-s, ability and heridity still brought maximal available legitimacy.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Principles of proper governance very much applied to kings irrespective of varNa status.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ministership</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/ministership/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/ministership/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;general-eligibility&#34;&gt;General eligibility&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;mahAbhArata&amp;rsquo;s prescription (an ostensibly &amp;ldquo;brahmanical&amp;rdquo; source) placed in the mouth of the dying grandfather bhISma, as part of his lectures on statecraft, that a king should have 4 brAhmaNa &amp;amp; 4 shUdra ministers, 8 kSatriya ministers and 21 vaishya ministers. This may be due to the complexity of regulating various trades and crafts in an ncreasingly sophisticated society.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;brahmanas-serving-shudra-kings&#34;&gt;brAhmaNas serving shUdra kings&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;support&#34;&gt;Support&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Kamalākarabhaṭṭa&amp;rsquo;s cousin &lt;strong&gt;Nilakaṇṭha&lt;/strong&gt;, the author of Vyavahāra mayūkha explains the word nr̥pa &amp;ldquo;king&amp;rdquo; [ Vyavahāramayūkha, p. 2] in wording reminding us of Bālambhaṭṭa: nr̥pah prajā-pālanādhikr̥to yaḥ kaścit, na Kṣatriya eva - &amp;ldquo;The word nr̥pa &amp;lsquo;king&amp;rsquo; refers to whoever is in charge of protecting the people, and is not restricted to a Kṣatriya.&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Commenting on a quote from Manu, &amp;ldquo;A king desirous of taking care of the legal affairs along with Veda-knowing Brahmins and ministers should enter the court&amp;rdquo; [vyavahārān didrksus tu brāhmanaih saha pārthivaḥ / mantra-jñair mantribhiḥ sārdhaṁ vinītah praviśet sabhām], the Bālambhattī of &lt;strong&gt;Bālambhaṭṭa Pāyagunde&lt;/strong&gt; [p. 5] says: pārthivah pr̥thivī-patih kṣatriyād anyaḥ api - &amp;ldquo;The word &amp;lsquo;king&amp;rsquo; refers to the ruler of the kingdom, even someone other than a Kṣatriya.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Similar non-Kṣatriya interpretations of the word rājā are found elsewhere in the Dharmaśāstra literature [Dharmakosa, Vol. IV, Pt. II, pp. 780ff.; P.V. Kane 1973: 38-40].&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;disagreement&#34;&gt;Disagreement&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;On the other hand, we must contrast Gāgābhaṭṭas views on the same passages. These are found in his Dinakaroddyota Vyavahārakāṇḍa [manu script 37/1866-1868 at the Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institute, in Pune]. Citing the same verse of Manu: vyavahārān didr̥kṣus tu brāhmaṇaiḥ saha pārthivah / mantrajñair mantribhiś caiva vinītaḥ praviset sabhām //, Gāgābhaṭṭa says: &amp;ldquo;Only a properly consecrated king is entitled to look after the business of justice (vyavahāra). &amp;hellip; Even though the word rāja refers to a particular Jāti, and in Dharmaśāstric passages, the word rāja often comes without any further specification, in those passages the word rāja refers to a Kṣatriya who is properly consecrated, since only such a consecrated Kṣatriya is entitled to look after justice&amp;rdquo; [vyavahāradarśane cābhiśiktasya rājno dhikāraḥ/ rājābhiśeka-samyukto brāhmano vā bahu-śrutaḥ / dharmāsana-gatah pasyed vyavahārān anulbaṇam iti prājāpatyukteḥ / &amp;hellip; yady api rāja-padam jāti-vāci / rājñā sabhāsadaḥ kāryāḥ ityādi bahuṣu vacaneṣu kevala-rāja-sravanam ca / tathāpi tatra rājapadam abhisikta-Kṣatriya-paraṁ - tad adhikārāt /, Dinakaroddyota, folios 7a—8].[24]&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
