<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2.1 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2.1 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>19 Devayajña</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/19_devayajna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/19_devayajna/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XIX
DEVAYAJÑA
Devayajña &amp;ndash;As stated in the Tai. Ār. quoted above ( p. 696 ) the Devayajña was performed by offering fuel sticks into fire. According to the Ap. Db. S. I. 4. 13. 1, Baud. 1688 Db. S. II. 6. 4 and Gaut. V. 8-9, the Devayajña consisted in offering into fire offerings ( of food or at least a fuel stick ) with &amp;lsquo;svāhā&amp;rsquo; uttered after the name of the deities in the dative case.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>20 Vaiśvadeva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/20_vaishvadeva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/20_vaishvadeva/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XX
VAISVADEVA Vaiśvadeva.-offering of cooked food to all Gods ).
Daksa ( II. 56 ) says that in the 5th part of the day a house holder has to allow distribution of food according to his ability to the gods, Manes, men and even insects. Vai vadeva is to be offered according to Śatātapa ( quoted by Medhātithi on Manu V, 7 and by Aparārka p. 142) in the gphya fire if one has preserved it, or in the ordinary fire.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21 Manuṣyayajña</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/21_manuShyayajna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/21_manuShyayajna/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXI NRYAJÑA OR MANUṢYA-YAJÑA.
NȚyajña or Manusya-yajña : ( Honouring guests)-Manu (III. 70 ) states that this consists in honouring guests. In the oldest hymns of the Rgveda fire is described as a guest in the house of the sacrificer. In Rg. I. 73. 1 Agni is described as lying in a pleasant spot and pleased like a guest (syonasir atithir-na priṇāno). Vide Rg. V, 1. 8 1785 and 9, V, 4.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>22 Bhojana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/22_Bhojana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/22_Bhojana/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXII
BHOJANA
Bhojana ( taking one&amp;rsquo;s meals ) :-Dakṣs (II. 56 and 68) states that in the fifth 1809 part of the day the householder should make according to his capacity the gods, pitrs, mon and even lower animals (lit. insects) participators (in food) and after doing that, he should himself partake of the remainder of the food cooked. Thus he was to take his mealy during one hour and a half after noon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>23 Upākarma and Utsarjana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/23_upAkarma_and_Utsarjana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/23_upAkarma_and_Utsarjana/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXIII
UPĀKARMA OR UPĀKARANA AND
UTSARJANA OR UTSARGA.
ning (upakran Asv. g!. III. 3:in the year. Ap.
Upākarma or Upākarana means &amp;lsquo;opening, starting or begin. ning&amp;rsquo; (upakrama as the Mit. on Yāj. I, 142 says) and Utsarjana or Utsarga (in Aśv. gļ, III. 5. 13) means &amp;rsquo;the cessation of Vedic studies for a certain period in the year.&amp;rsquo; Ap. gr. VIII. 1 and Ap. Dh S. I. 3. 11. % employ the word &amp;lsquo;samāpana&amp;rsquo; for utsarjana.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>24 Minor Gṛhya and Other Rites</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/24_Minor_gRhya_and_Other_Rites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/24_Minor_gRhya_and_Other_Rites/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXIV
MINOR GRHYA AND OTHER RITES
The grhyasūtras speak of certain other rites performed on certain fixed days in the year. Most of them have ceased to be performed in modern times, though vestiges of some of them appear even now. Gautama (VIII. 19 ) enumerates the seven pākayajā asamsthās among his forty sarskāras. Out of these seven pākayajñas, aṣtakā, pārvana and śrāddha will be dealt with under śrāddha later on, The seven haviryajñas and the seven somasamsthās will be treated of in the note on Srauta.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>25 Dāna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/25_dAna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/25_dAna/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXV
DANA (Gifts )
Manu ( I. 86 ) and others state that in the four yugas ( ages ) viz. Kșta, Tretā, Dvāpara and Kali, the principal aspects of religious life were respectively tapas, metaphysical knowledge, sacrifices, 1973 and gifts. Manu (III. 78 ) eulogises the stage of householder as the most worthy because all men in the other asramas are cherished and fed with (Vedic ) knowledge (as a teacher of Vedic students) and with food by him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>26 Pratiṣṭhā and Utsarga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/26_pratiShThA_and_Utsarga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/26_pratiShThA_and_Utsarga/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXVI
PRATIṢTHA AND UTSARGA
Pratistha and Utsarga (foundation of temples and dedica. tion of wells, tanks, parks &amp;amp;o, for the benefit of the publio).
The subject of gifts naturally leads on to the topics of pratiṣtha and utsarga. We saw above (p. 157 f. n. 370) how the construction of temples, wells and similar religious and charitable foundations and institutions was included under pūrtadharma and how sūdras were entitled to perform such dharma, The Mit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>27 Vānaprastha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/27_vAnaprastha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/27_vAnaprastha/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXVII
VĀNAPRASTHA (forest hermit )
Vaikbānasa appears to have been the ancient name for Vānaprastba. In the Anukramani one hundred Vaikbānasas are said to have been the seers of Rg. IX. 66 and a Vamra Vaikbānasa is the seer of Rg. X. 99. The Tai. A. I. 23 connects the word Vaikhādase with the nakhas of Prajāpati (yo nakbās te vaikhānasāḥ ), 8115 It appears that in ancient times there was some work called Vaikhānasa sāstra which treated of the rules for forest hermits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>28 Sannyāsa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/28_sannyAsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/28_sannyAsa/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXVIII
SANNYĀSA
Sannyāsa.( the order of ascetics ). That the Chān. Up. was well aware of the three asramas of student-hood, house holder and forest hermit has been shown above (p. 420 ). It is somewhat doubtful whether the Chan. Up. regarded sannyaga as the fourth and the last stage in a man&amp;rsquo;s life when ideally planned. It merely states that one that holds fast by the realization of brahman attains immortality&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>29 Śrauta Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/29_shrauta_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/29_shrauta_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXIX
SRAUTA ( VEDIC) SACRIFICES*
Introductory A deep study of Vedic saorifices is quite essential for the proper understanding of the Vedic Literature, for arriving at approximately correct statements about the obronology, the development and the stratification of the different portions of that Literature and for the influence that that Literature exerted on the four varṇas and the caste-system, on the splitting up of the brāhmaṇas themselves among several sub-castes 88% and on the institution of gotras and pravaras.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 Darśapūrṇamāsa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/30_darshapUrNamAsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/30_darshapUrNamAsa/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXX
DARSA-PŪRŅAMĀSA 2272
The Darsapārṇamāsa gaorifice is the pattern or archetype (pra. krti) of all other iṣtis (which are called vikṛtis or modifications). The srauta sūtras therefore describe first the Darsapūrpamāga at length, though in the order of time agnyadhana comes first. Asy. II. 1. 1 says that all iṣçis, sacrifices in which an animal is offered and those in which somis offered are explained by the Paurṇamāsa iṣti. According to Ap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>31 Cāturmāsyas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/31_chAturmAsyas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/31_chAturmAsyas/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXXI
CĀTURMĀSYAS (seasonal sacrifices ) 2442
TD 1
According to Aśv. II. 14. 1 the term Istyayana comprehends the Cāturmāsyas, Turāyana, Dākṣayana and other iṣtis. The cāturmāsyas are three (or four according to some ), viz. Vai ve deva, Varuṇapraghāsa, Sākamedha ( and Sundsirlya ). Each of these is called &amp;amp; parvan ( part or joint ) of the cāturmāsyas. They are called cāturmāsyas because each of them takes place after four months.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>32 Nirūḍhapaśubandha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/32_nirUDhapashubandha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/32_nirUDhapashubandha/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXXII
PASUBANDHA OR NIRŪDHAPASUBANDH A 2481
(immolation of an animal in sacrifice ).
The animal sacrifice is an independent sacrifice and it is also performed in soma sacrifices as a constituent part (anga ). The independent animal sacrifice is oalled nirūdhapasubandha ( offering of an eviscerated animal) and the subordinate ones are called saumika ( Aśv. III. 8. 3-4). The nirudhapaśu is really &amp;amp; modification of an animal sacrifice in somayage (called agniṣomiya paśu ) 28 Jai.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>33 Agniṣṭoma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/33_agniShToma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/33_agniShToma/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXXIII
AGNIṢTOMA2529
Sacrifices are often divided for convenience into ieti, pasu and soma. Acoording to Gaut. VIII, 21 and Lat. Sr. V. 4. 24 there are seven forms of some sacrifices, viz. Agniṣtoma, Atyagnistoma, Ukthya, Sodasin, Vājapeya, Atiratra and Aptor yāma. The Agniṣtoma is the model (prakrti) of all soma sacrifices. The Agnistoma is a one day (alkābika or ekāba ) sacrifice and it is an integral part of the Jyotiṣtoma so much so that the two are often identified.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>34 Other Soma Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/34_Other_Soma_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/34_Other_Soma_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>GTKCHAPTER XXXIV OTHER SOMA SACRIFICES
The sūtras speak of seven forms ( samstbas ) of soma sacrifices. These seven forms are Agniṣtoma, Atyagnistoma, Ukthya, Sodasin, Vajapeya, Atirātra and Aptoryāma (according to Kat. X. 9. 27, Āāv. VI. 11. 1, Lat. V. 4. 24). The first of these has been described in some detail above. Owing to restrictions of space only a few words can be said about the other goma sacrifices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>35 Sautrāmaṇī and Other Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/35_sautrAmaNI_and_Other_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p2/35_sautrAmaNI_and_Other_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXXV
SAUTRAMANĪ2660 AND OTHER SACRIFICES
This rite is included among the seven forms of bavir. yajñas (Gaut. VIII. 20, Lat. V. 4. 23). It is not a soma saorifice but is a combination of an iṣçi with animal sacrifice (Sat. Br. XII, 7, 2. 10). The chief characteristic of it is the offering of sura ( wine ) in it. In modern times milk is offered in place of sura in the Sautrāmapi.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
