<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/khAdanam_food/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2004 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/khAdanam_food/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Vedic Beer</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/khAdanam_food/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-03-22_vedic-beer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/khAdanam_food/articles/MT_lekhAH/2004-03-22_vedic-beer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2004/03/22/vedic-beer/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whereas beer and other alcoholic beverages were not consumed by the brAhmaNa-s (and ascetics) unlike rest of Arya society, its production was still a part of brAhmaNa lore. The hindus of yore had an elaborate ritual of beer making connected with the exhalted rite called the sautrAmaNI.+++(4)+++&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The adhvaryu priest bought the following items through barter:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;grass blades in exchange for a piece of zinc.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Barley grains for goat wool,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;parched rice in exchange for yarn.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Each bargain the priest uttered the formula “surAsomavikrayin krayyaste surAsoma”.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Then these materials are carried to the prachIna vaMsha altar and prepares fungal powders known as nagnahU.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He then boils the shyAmAka beans and rice and collects the supernatants to which he adds the nagnahU powder and then mixes the two and keeps them away for a while. This preparation is called mAsara.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Then he mixes the mAsara with the boiled grains of rice and shyAmAkas in a large vessel called the surapAtra chanting the mantras svAdvIM…&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He deposits this vessel in a pit at the naiR^ita corner of the prAchina vaMsha altar for 3 nights.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Then a cow is freshly milked with the mantra ashivibhyAM apAkaromi and the milk is poured into the ferment with the mantra parIto si~nchatA…&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He then shreds the rice leaves into fine pieces and adds them to the ferment and lets is stay for a night.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The next morning he milks two cows with the mantra ‘sarasvatyai apAkaromi…’ and adds the milk to the ferment.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He also adds the powder of fresh barley grains and lets it stand for a night.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The next day he adds the milk of 3 cows into the ferment and adds the flour of parched grains into it.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This is let to ferment for 4 days.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He then goes to the southern altar and pours the ferment through a ox hide funnel through a hoof-sieve with the mantra “si~nchati pari si~nchati..” to get a preliminary liquor.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This liquor is further purified by straining through ox and horse hair filters in a pot made of palAsa wood by reciting the mantra “punAti te parisrutaM..”.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This liquor is termed the surA. At this point if a yajamAna or his patni are morbidly reacting to the soma drink by vomitting or flux they are given the surA as a remedy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Animal products</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/khAdanam_food/articles/MT_lekhAH/animal-products/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/khAdanam_food/articles/MT_lekhAH/animal-products/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/blog_supplement/status/1330226994945142788&#34;&gt;MT20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bovine-excreta&#34;&gt;Bovine excreta&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is nothing strange about the consumption of bovine excreta and fecal matter. It is a common adaptation seen across pastoralists of different origins. We know our Indo-European strand of ancestry on the steppes did so; African cattle-breeding tribes do so; it will not be surprising if the Harappans &amp;amp; south Indian Ash mound tribes did something like that given that they were cattle rearers too.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;benefits-if-in-close-contact&#34;&gt;Benefits if in close contact&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Urine &amp;amp; fecal matter, each probably had their own adaptive significance. In the case of former some metabolites might have had useful physiological effect. Well collected mid-stream urine would not have much of health issues due to being mostly sterile.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
