<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;अधि-धर्मम् on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;अधि-धर्मम् on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>&#43;Direction, intensity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/direction_intensity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/direction_intensity/</guid>
      <description>For stories of remarkable feats arising from self-cultivation and control of senses, see kathA page.
Genetics and circumstance One&amp;rsquo;s circumstance determines to a great extant the level of practice and conservativism suitable for oneself. Genetics is a great determinant of conservativism vs liberalism, for example.
Hierarchy in practice The wrong, but unfortunately popular hierarchy of spiritual practice: Adorers of the Absolute &amp;gt; Adorers of personal deities &amp;gt; Adorers of incarnations &amp;gt; Adorers of myriad ancestors, sages and deities &amp;gt; adorers of petty forces and spirits [rAdhAkRShNan T].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Current challenges</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/current_challenges/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/current_challenges/</guid>
      <description>Circumstance and relevance The motivations described earlier still drive us today, and we must do our best to imbibe the spirit (not the letter) of the classical dharmashAstra thought and refine ourselves as individuals and communities. Hindu culture and civilization is facing an existential threat. &amp;ldquo;But it has a dangerous rival – a memetic complex of a pathogenic type that arose in the Afro-Asiatic milieu of West Asia. This rival is the one which has extinguished the system across the former IE world and taken up the riches generated by the IE system as its “secular” property.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non good mysticism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/non-good-mysticism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/non-good-mysticism/</guid>
      <description>Mysticism does not imply goodness
It must be noted that mysticism and ability to achieve mystic highs do not necessarily imply goodness:
muhammad was a mystic, so were sufis of the type described here. mahAyAna rebellion of 515 China [IMG], where the doctrine seemed to include: &amp;ldquo;kill 10 enemies and become a 10th stage bodhisattva; kill all monks in captured monasteries&amp;rdquo; etc.. Many villains in hindu mythology - rAvaNa to narakAsura - were accomplished sAdhaka-s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo orthodoxy</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/pseudo_orthodoxy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/pseudo_orthodoxy/</guid>
      <description>Intro An incomplete understanding of the spectrum of Hindu ideals leads to many errors.
Social level failures Poverty &amp;ldquo;Years ago I visited old agraharas in Mysore it was really bad in 1-2 bedroom small house, built during maharaja&amp;rsquo;s time entire family of purohitas lived. One thing I am glad my mother forced me away from full time vedapathashala to secular education early on.&amp;rdquo; Individual level failures Health loss This could be caused by fanatical ritual strictness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sources</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/sources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/sources/</guid>
      <description>Sources of the dharma include the veda-s, itihAsa-s, purANa-s, the vedAnga called kalpa (which includes dharmasUtra-s, smRtis, dharmashAstra-s and their commentaries). General intro to valid sources of hindu knowledge here. These sources are classifified into shruti (veda-s), smRti texts and shiShTAchAra (practice of learned elders). All of these are ultimately said to derive from the veda-s in some traditions - hypothesizing lost veda-s and brAhmaNa-s in the process. Among the smRti-s manu-smRti and yAJNavalkya-smRti were the most important classically (going by the number of commentaries).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Subversion पाटनम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/subversion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/subversion/</guid>
      <description>Indigenous subversions Many serious internal subversions arose motivated by:
Opposition to the proven vaidika way. Opposition to varNAshrama dharma, and the special role of brAhmaNa-s in conserving Arya ideals. Secularist and abrahamist subversion As the mlecCha rag NYT put in 2017: &amp;ldquo;The tension between the hold of established cultural practices and new efforts by activists to safeguard rights, whether minority, individual or animal&amp;rdquo;. Encouraging schisms along the faultlines of the &amp;ldquo;suppressed and oppressed&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
