<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;सोमेश्वरदेवः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/someshvaradevaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;सोमेश्वरदेवः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/someshvaradevaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>अभिलषितार्थचिन्तामणिः  प्रथमभागः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/someshvaradevaH/abhilaShitArthachintAmaNiH_prathamabhAgaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/someshvaradevaH/abhilaShitArthachintAmaNiH_prathamabhAgaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[अभिलषितार्थचिन्तामणिः  प्रथमभागः&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=NjE2NTU2Mjg0OTYwMzc0&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;lt;MISSING_FIG href=&amp;quot;../books_images/1683197826.png&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;ABHILASHITARTHACHINTAMANI&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Boon-stone of all Desirable Knowledge&amp;rdquo; is, as a title of the work under notice, so wide as to comprehend within it all branches of knowledge known at the time of the author. But a cursory glance over the contents of the work will reveal that the subjects treated of in the book are very few and that a number of subjects, no less desirable than those dealt with here, were left out of notice. The book consists of five Prakaranas of twenty chapters each. In the first Prakarana are explained general and religious ethics, social service, manufacture of idols, and diseases and their remedies. In the second, polity is treated of in detail under the seven heads, such as the king, his minister, his ally, his treasury, the king- dom, forts and the army together with law, both private and interstatal, under such aspects as peace, war, invasion, neutrality, alliance, and war with one and peace with another, not omitting the four wellknown stratagems, such as reconciliation, bribery, dissension, and war. The third Prakarana is devoted to the description of architecture, picture-drawing and painting with minutest details, iconography and pleasures of domestic life. In the fourth and the fifth, various forms of amusements and recreations are described. Incidentally brief reference is also made to arithmetic, the decimal notation, preparation of calendars, astrology, omens, augury, palmistry, train- ing of horses and elephants together with the treatment of their diseases, mining, alchemy, gems and precious stones, marriage and child-rearing, cookery, liquor, beverages, music, conveyance, and scents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
