<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;shrī-raṅgapriya on festivals on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;shrī-raṅgapriya on festivals on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>00 Meta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/00_Meta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/00_Meta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We Dedicate this Sacred Treasure at the holy lotus feet of&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sriranga Mahaguru and SriMata&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The founders of Ashtangayoga Vijnana Mandiram, famously known by the significant name &lt;strong&gt;Sri Gurubhagavan&lt;/strong&gt; (God or the supreme spirit itself in the form of teacher) the supreme Yogis and eminent teachers of spiritual science&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AND&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We dedicate this valuable work with devotion and reverence to our revered parents&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Late Veda Brahma Sri Keshava Subrahmanya Kowshik&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Late Smt. Lalithamma Kowshik&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 dīpāvaḷi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/04_DIpAvali/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/04_DIpAvali/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;उपशमितमेघनादम्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;प्रज्वलितदशाननम् रमितरामम् ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;रामायणमिव सुभगम्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;दीपदिनं हरतु वो दुरितम्॥&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Just as &lt;em&gt;Meghanāda&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Indrajit&lt;/em&gt;) who becomes quieted in the &lt;em&gt;Rāmāyaṇa,&lt;/em&gt; the &lt;em&gt;meghanāda&lt;/em&gt; becomes silent in this great festival. Like the ten faced &lt;em&gt;Rāvaṇa&lt;/em&gt; who is burnt in &lt;em&gt;Rāmāyaṇa,&lt;/em&gt; the tips of the wicks are lighted in this festival. As &lt;em&gt;Rāma&lt;/em&gt; rejoiced in &lt;em&gt;Rāmāyaṇa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Śrī Rāma&lt;/em&gt; and beautiful women enjoy here. This way let the day of &lt;em&gt;Dīpāvaḷi mahotsava&lt;/em&gt; which is delightful like &lt;em&gt;Rāmāyaṇa,&lt;/em&gt; ward off our your sins.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Gaṇeśa chaturthī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/05_gaNesha_ChaturthI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/05_gaNesha_ChaturthI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gaṇeśa caturthī&lt;/em&gt; is one of the most widely celebrated festivals in India. This is a festival that comes generally a day after &lt;em&gt;Gaurī&lt;/em&gt; festival or sometimes comes on the same day of &lt;em&gt;Gaurī&lt;/em&gt; festival itself. Even those who do not celebrate &lt;em&gt;Gaurī&lt;/em&gt; festival, celebrate this festival without fail. &lt;em&gt;Gaṇeśa&lt;/em&gt; is the most popular deity. The proverb ‘&lt;em&gt;Gaṇapanillada Grāmavilla’&lt;/em&gt; (There is no village without &lt;em&gt;Gaṇapa&lt;/em&gt;) is well known. Before elaborating upon the festival, we shall discuss about &lt;em&gt;Gaṇeśa,&lt;/em&gt; the presiding deity of the festival.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Gaurī Festival</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/06_gaurI_Festival/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/06_gaurI_Festival/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gaurī&lt;/em&gt; Festival is one of the most important &lt;em&gt;parvas&lt;/em&gt; that comes in the month of &lt;em&gt;Bhādrapada&lt;/em&gt;. Though it is generally known as &lt;em&gt;‘Gaurī Habba’&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;śāstraic&lt;/em&gt; name happens to be &lt;em&gt;‘SvarṇaGaurīvrata’&lt;/em&gt;. This is because this festival is unique and has distinct features compared to other &lt;em&gt;vratas&lt;/em&gt; pertaining to &lt;em&gt;Gaurī&lt;/em&gt; such as &lt;em&gt;‘Saubhāgyagaurī’&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;‘Sampadgaurī’, ‘maṅgalagaurī’, ‘Lāvaṇyagaurī’, ‘Trilocanagaurī’, ‘Gajagaurī’&lt;/em&gt; etc. Though all these are &lt;em&gt;Gaurī&lt;/em&gt; festivals, &lt;em&gt;‘SvarṇaGaurīvrata’&lt;/em&gt; is the most famous of these, and the practice of calling only this as &lt;em&gt;‘Gaurī festival’&lt;/em&gt; is in vogue. It is like the ordinary people calling the &lt;em&gt;saṅkramaṇa&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;makara māsa&lt;/em&gt; only as &lt;em&gt;‘saṅkranti’&lt;/em&gt; specially, even though &lt;em&gt;saṅkramaṇas&lt;/em&gt; occur every month. Likewise, this festival which is special, is called as &lt;em&gt;‘Gaurīvrata’&lt;/em&gt;. All over India, people in large numbers celebrate this festival.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 ḥanumajjayantī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/07_HanumajjayantI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/07_HanumajjayantI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hanumajjayantī&lt;/em&gt; is an important festival celebrated in the month of &lt;em&gt;Caitra&lt;/em&gt;, after &lt;em&gt;ŚrīRāmanavami&lt;/em&gt;. The deity worshipped on that day is &lt;em&gt;Hanumān&lt;/em&gt;. He is a &lt;em&gt;mahātma&lt;/em&gt;, famously known by names such as &lt;em&gt;Āñjaneya&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Māruti&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Prāṇadevaru&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Tiruvadi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mahāvīra&lt;/em&gt; etc, in the literature of &lt;em&gt;jnānis&lt;/em&gt; and devotees. It is but natural that, after the worship of &lt;em&gt;Śrī Rāma&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;em&gt;Rāmanavami&lt;/em&gt; and on a day very close to &lt;em&gt;Śrī Rāmanavami&lt;/em&gt;, the custom of worshipping this God who is the greatest among the retinue of &lt;em&gt;ŚrīRāma&lt;/em&gt;, who is dear to devotees, dear to scholars and who is very popular, continues even to this day. Not just in the &lt;em&gt;Rāmāyaṇa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mahābhārata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Purāṇas&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dharmaśāstras&lt;/em&gt; and musical and poetic compositions, even in folk literature and sayings such as&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Holikotsava, holi habba, Vasantotsava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/08_Holikotsava_Holi_Habba_Vasantotsava/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/08_Holikotsava_Holi_Habba_Vasantotsava/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;08 holikotsava, holi habba, Vasantotsava&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a famous festival celebrated all over India being called by the names &lt;em&gt;‘Hoḷāka’&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;‘Holikā’&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;‘Holī&lt;/em&gt;‘, &lt;em&gt;‘Phālgunikā’ ‘Vasantotsava’&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;‘Kāmanahabba’&lt;/em&gt; etc. Though there are differences regarding the day of observance and the modalities, it is celebrated throughout India. Thoughin some places the celebration is begun on &lt;em&gt;Vasantapañcamī&lt;/em&gt;. (i.e. &lt;em&gt;Māgha Śukla Pancamī&lt;/em&gt;) it is specially celebrated on the day of &lt;em&gt;Phālguṇa-Pūrṇimā&lt;/em&gt; only. Activities like burning of a pile of fire wood, (splashing) of rose colored water, dancing with happiness and excitement etc, are generally seen in all places. Only in the Bengal region the custom of performing &lt;em&gt;‘Dolotsava’&lt;/em&gt; on that day to Lord &lt;em&gt;Kṛshṇa&lt;/em&gt; is in vogue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 janma dina and puṇya ṭithi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/09_janma_dina_And_puNya_Tithi_of_shrI_guru-AchAryas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/09_janma_dina_And_puNya_Tithi_of_shrI_guru-AchAryas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;janma dina ānd phuṇya ṭithi of ŚrĪ Guru-Ācāryas&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;God addressed by various names, &lt;em&gt;Śrī Rāma&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Śrī Kṛshṇa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Śrī Śiva&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Śrī Subrahmaṇya&lt;/em&gt; and the festival and holy days addressing the distinct deities with distinguishing divine attributes and glories, have been discussed in the preceding chapters. Similarly, there are customs in our culture to observe with devotion and enthusiasm the festivals and holy days addressing preceptors, who have realized the essence of the Supreme Being, who have guided people in the divine realization path and the path of righteous order. Realized &lt;em&gt;mahatmas&lt;/em&gt; like Jain &lt;em&gt;tīrthankaras, Gautamabuddha, Śrī Śaṅkara, Śrī Rāmānuja, Śrī Madhva, Śrī Basveśvara&lt;/em&gt; are some of the elite preceptors. Great souls who having realized the divine principle themselves guide others to realize those divine principles, who conducted themselves in accordance with the canons, and who shone as the guiding lights for the world at large are called &lt;em&gt;‘ācārya&lt;/em&gt;s’ [One who professes what he practices]. Their propitious reminiscences are observed on the lunar day (&lt;em&gt;tithi&lt;/em&gt;) of their birth and their passing away, by meditating on them, offering worship, reading their history, chanting and singing about them. These days have the same reverence and respect as the festivals and holy days addressed to distinguishing divine attributes in the form of deities. We will discuss this topic, briefly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Śrī Kṛśṇa jayantī—janmāśṭamī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/10_shrI_kRshNa_jayantI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/10_shrI_kRshNa_jayantI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī KṛshṇaJayantī&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Janmāshṭamī&lt;/em&gt; is a very important festival, which comes in the month of &lt;em&gt;srāvaṇa&lt;/em&gt;. People call it by different names such as &lt;em&gt;Gokulāshṭamī&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Jayantī&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Śrī Jayantī&lt;/em&gt; etc. It is a great festival observed all over India with joy and devotion. It is a very popular, sacred and very auspicious &lt;em&gt;parva&lt;/em&gt; which is observed by people belonging to all &lt;em&gt;varṇas&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;āśramas&lt;/em&gt; and classes. &lt;em&gt;Śrī Kṛshṇa&lt;/em&gt; is the deity worshipped specially on that day. In this background it is necessary to know a little about the reigning deity of this festival.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 Kṛttikā dīpotsava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/11_kRttikA_DIpotsava_shivadIpa_vishNudIpa_Mahotsavas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/11_kRttikA_DIpotsava_shivadIpa_vishNudIpa_Mahotsavas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;11 Kṛttikā dīpotsava (Śivadīpa Viśṇudīpa ṃahotsavas)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-names-of-the-parvas&#34;&gt;1. Names of the &lt;em&gt;parvas&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We see many &lt;em&gt;Dīpotsava parvas&lt;/em&gt; in the line of festivals of &lt;em&gt;Bhāratīyas&lt;/em&gt; where rows of lamps are lighted in temples, homes, &lt;em&gt;maṭhas&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Āśramas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mandirs&lt;/em&gt;, both inside and outside those places. The most famous &lt;em&gt;parvas&lt;/em&gt; among these are the &lt;em&gt;Vishṇu dīpa&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Śiva dīpa&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Mahotsavas&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;These two fall either on the same day or one of them comes on the next day of the other, and thus they declare the deep relationship of &lt;em&gt;Śiva&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Vishṇu&lt;/em&gt;, to the sentimental devotees. These are also called by the name &lt;em&gt;laksha dīpotsava&lt;/em&gt; in the temples. The &lt;em&gt;laksha dīpotsavas&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Śiva&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Vishṇu&lt;/em&gt; and their &lt;em&gt;parivāra devatās&lt;/em&gt; are observed on the full moon day of &lt;em&gt;kārtika māsa&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Kṛshṇa caturdaśī&lt;/em&gt; or on the day of &lt;em&gt;amāvāsya tithi&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;kārtika māsa&lt;/em&gt;. However in most of the places, these &lt;em&gt;Śiva&lt;/em&gt;-&lt;em&gt;Vishṇu Dīpotsava&lt;/em&gt;s are celebrated only in the &lt;em&gt;vṛścika māsa&lt;/em&gt; of the solar calendar. Though these festivals happen to fall some times in &lt;em&gt;kārtika māsa&lt;/em&gt; and at other times in &lt;em&gt;mārgaśira māsa&lt;/em&gt; as per the lunar calendar, they are celebrated only in the month which is called &lt;em&gt;‘kārtikai māsam’&lt;/em&gt; in the Tamil country as per the solar calendar, and importance is given to &lt;em&gt;kṛttikā Nakshatra&lt;/em&gt; also in the observance of this festival. Therefore these &lt;em&gt;Śiva-Vishṇu Dīpotsava&lt;/em&gt;s are also called &lt;em&gt;‘kṛttikā dīpotsava’&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;‘tirukkārtikai’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 mahāśivarātri</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/12_MahAshivarAtri/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/12_MahAshivarAtri/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mahāśivarātri&lt;/em&gt; is one of the most important &lt;em&gt;parvas&lt;/em&gt; among the festivals of &lt;em&gt;Bhāratīyas&lt;/em&gt;. Just as &lt;em&gt;Prayāga&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Pushkara&lt;/em&gt; are called &lt;em&gt;‘Tīrtharāja’&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mahāśivarātri&lt;/em&gt; is called &lt;em&gt;‘vratarāja’&lt;/em&gt;. This &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt; is observed in all parts of &lt;em&gt;Bhāratadeśa&lt;/em&gt; with concern reverence and devotion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Though this is a festival where the prominent deity is &lt;em&gt;Śiva&lt;/em&gt; and a very special &lt;em&gt;parva&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;śaivites&lt;/em&gt;, even &lt;em&gt;Vaishṇavas&lt;/em&gt; and worshippers of other great &lt;em&gt;devatās&lt;/em&gt; also should specially worship God (&lt;em&gt;Śiva&lt;/em&gt;) on &lt;em&gt;Śivarātri&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Śāstras&lt;/em&gt; say that those who are indifferent to &lt;em&gt;Śivarātri&lt;/em&gt; i.e. those who turn away from it without observing it, and those who abstain from doing worship in the &lt;em&gt;Antarmukha&lt;/em&gt; state but remain &lt;em&gt;Bahirmukhas,&lt;/em&gt; happen to lose all the benefits of worship and become unfortunate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 saṅkrānti , ūttarāyaṇa puṇyakāla</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/13_ShankrAnti_Makara_ShankrAnti_UttarAyaNa_puNyakAla/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/13_ShankrAnti_Makara_ShankrAnti_UttarAyaNa_puNyakAla/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;13 saṅkrānti (&lt;em&gt;ṃakara saṅkrānti, ūttarāyaṇa puṇyakāla&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;name-and-significance&#34;&gt;Name and significance&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;uttarāyaṇa&#34;&gt;uttarāyaṇa&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The name and significance of this &lt;em&gt;parva&lt;/em&gt;:—&#xA;&lt;em&gt;Saṅkrānti&lt;/em&gt; is one of the most important festivals of the &lt;em&gt;Sanātana Ārya Bhāratiyas.&lt;/em&gt; In scriptures it is called by other names such as &lt;em&gt;Saṅkrānti, Makarasaṅkrānti, Makarasaṅkramaṇa, Makarasaṅkramaṇa&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Uttarāyaṇa puṇyakāla&lt;/em&gt; also. In Tamil Nadu it is called &lt;em&gt;Pongal&lt;/em&gt;. Common people also call this as &lt;em&gt;‘Ellina Habba’&lt;/em&gt;. Though the distribution of sesame is in vougue in the next festival also i.e. &lt;em&gt;‘rathasaptamī’&lt;/em&gt;, it is only &lt;em&gt;Saṅkrānti&lt;/em&gt; which is renownedly associated with the significance and fame pertaining to the gifting of sesame, and thus is well known as &lt;em&gt;Eḷḷina habba&lt;/em&gt;. The Kannada proveb &lt;em&gt;“Eḷḷu bellava tindu oḷḷeya māthanāḍu’&lt;/em&gt; owes it’s origin to this festival.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 nāgapūjā- nāgarapañcamī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/14_NAgapUjA-_NAgarapanchamI_Serpent_Worship/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/14_NAgapUjA-_NAgarapanchamI_Serpent_Worship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;14 Nāgapūjā- ṇāgarapañcamī (Serpent Worship)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Nāgapañcami&lt;/em&gt; occupies an important place in the traditions brought forth by the &lt;em&gt;sanātana Āryabhāratīya Maharshis&lt;/em&gt;, This is even considered by some as one of the supreme &lt;em&gt;parvas&lt;/em&gt;, in place of &lt;em&gt;Akshaya tṛtīyā&lt;/em&gt;. This &lt;em&gt;parva&lt;/em&gt; is observed in all parts of this country by people belonging to all sects, creeds and philosophical systems. Though there are differences in the modalities of observance, all of them observe this with great devotion, faith and religious fervor. We see that this &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt; is being observed by all, except by those who have a vow not to observe &lt;em&gt;kāmya vratas&lt;/em&gt; and those who are devoted to only one deity like &lt;em&gt;Śiva, Vishṇu&lt;/em&gt; etc. Even such &lt;em&gt;Ekadevopāsakas&lt;/em&gt; (devoted to a single god) sometimes observe this as a &lt;em&gt;kāmyavrata&lt;/em&gt;. People observe this &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt; with the desires such as - “Let not serpents bite us, Let the peril from poison be averted. Let us have progeny. Let us be bestowed with wealth. Let us be free from skin diseases. Let us attain heaven”, Etc.,. This &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt; is also observed with the objective of awakening &lt;em&gt;Kunḍalini&lt;/em&gt; i.e. &lt;em&gt;Prāṇaśakti&lt;/em&gt; for the early &lt;em&gt;phalasiddhi&lt;/em&gt; (results) in &lt;em&gt;yogābhyāsa&lt;/em&gt;. As the name of the &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt; itself clearly states, the deity that is specially worshipped on this day is &lt;em&gt;Nāgadevatā&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 narasimha jayantī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/15_Narasimha_jayantI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/15_Narasimha_jayantI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;importance-of-this-parva&#34;&gt;Importance of this &lt;em&gt;Parva&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Narasimha jayantī&lt;/em&gt; is a prominent &lt;em&gt;parva&lt;/em&gt; that comes after &lt;em&gt;akshaya tṛtīya&lt;/em&gt; in the month of &lt;em&gt;vaiśākha&lt;/em&gt;. To fecilitate the devotees to have the experience of the glory of one of the important incarnations of &lt;em&gt;Mahāvishṇu&lt;/em&gt;, the great sages of &lt;em&gt;Sanātana Arya Bhārata&lt;/em&gt; who were &lt;em&gt;jnānavijnāna tṛptātmas&lt;/em&gt; have marked this as a nodal day in the body (form) of the almighty in the form of time. It is a great day which is auspicious, holy and the day which reminds (us) of the all pervasivenss and unequalled &lt;em&gt;jnāna, bala, aiśvarya, śakti, vīrya, tejas&lt;/em&gt; and the motherly affection and love of that God towards devotees. It is a day in which the rituals are performed with great devotion in all the places in India where the &lt;em&gt;Upāsana&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Vishṇu&lt;/em&gt; and especially of Lord &lt;em&gt;Narasimha&lt;/em&gt; is in vogue in the homes of devotees, who worship Lord &lt;em&gt;Narasimha&lt;/em&gt; as either their family deity or a tutelary deity, and in &lt;em&gt;maṭhas, āshramas&lt;/em&gt; and in temples. It is the day when his &lt;em&gt;upāsana&lt;/em&gt; is taken up with austereness, both with the fear that any &lt;em&gt;apacāra&lt;/em&gt; (an offence) to God may chance, and with devotion combined with great and full confidence that he will receive the &lt;em&gt;upacāras&lt;/em&gt; with great affection. Some &lt;em&gt;Śaivas&lt;/em&gt; also worship Lord &lt;em&gt;Narasimha&lt;/em&gt; on that day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 Navarātra mahotsava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/16_NavarAtra_Mahotsava/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/16_NavarAtra_Mahotsava/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Navarātra&lt;/em&gt; is a very important &lt;em&gt;parva&lt;/em&gt; in the garland of festivals of the &lt;em&gt;Sanātana Āryabhāratiyas&lt;/em&gt;. There is no doubt that this is the most important of all the festivals celebrated in the &lt;em&gt;Āśvayujamāsa&lt;/em&gt;. This is a festival which is specially celebrated in all parts of India. People of all &lt;em&gt;Āśramas&lt;/em&gt; can celebrate this and even the &lt;em&gt;Mlecchās&lt;/em&gt; who do not fully come under &lt;em&gt;Āryadharma,&lt;/em&gt; are entitled (eligible) to celebrate this &lt;em&gt;parva&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 phrathamaikādaśī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/17_phrathamaikAdashI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/17_phrathamaikAdashI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;*Prathamaikādaśī * is one of the most important festivals observed in our country. The &lt;em&gt;Ekādaśī&lt;/em&gt; which falls in the &lt;em&gt;śuklapaksha&lt;/em&gt; of the month of &lt;em&gt;Āshāḍha&lt;/em&gt; is called by this name. This festival is also called by names such as &lt;em&gt;Ekādaśī&lt;/em&gt;, festival of fasting, &lt;em&gt;mahaikādasī&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;sāyanī&lt;/em&gt; etc. This happens to be a very important &lt;em&gt;parva&lt;/em&gt; observed by virtuous people of all the &lt;em&gt;varṇas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Āśramas&lt;/em&gt;, and people belonging to all sects such as &lt;em&gt;Śaiva&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Vaishṇava&lt;/em&gt; etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 Śrī rāmanavamī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/18_shrI_RAmanavamI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/18_shrI_RAmanavamI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī Rāmanavamī&lt;/em&gt; is the most important festival which comes in the month of &lt;em&gt;Caitra&lt;/em&gt;, just after &lt;em&gt;Ugādi&lt;/em&gt;. It is one of the great festivals which is being celebrated right from &lt;em&gt;Rāmasetu&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Himālayas&lt;/em&gt; by people belonging to all &lt;em&gt;varṇas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;āśrmas&lt;/em&gt; and who follow the &lt;em&gt;Āryasamskṛti&lt;/em&gt;. On this day, the tradition is to get absorbed in &lt;em&gt;Rāma&lt;/em&gt; by various observances such as doing of &lt;em&gt;Pārāyaṇa&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Rāmāyaṇa&lt;/em&gt; in Sanskrit and regional languages, listening to the story of &lt;em&gt;Rāma&lt;/em&gt;, presenting the story in dance, music and musical instruments, worshipping of &lt;em&gt;Rāma&lt;/em&gt; in homes, &lt;em&gt;maṭhas&lt;/em&gt; and temples with many &lt;em&gt;pūjās&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;upacāras&lt;/em&gt;, observing a fast which fecilitates to meditate upon HIM and/or taking the &lt;em&gt;Prasāda&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Naivedya&lt;/em&gt;) after the &lt;em&gt;pūja&lt;/em&gt;, to obtain his grace.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 ratha-saptamī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/19_ratha-SaptamI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/19_ratha-SaptamI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ratha Saptamī&lt;/em&gt; is one of the very important festivals observed by &lt;em&gt;Sanāthana Ārya Bhāratīyas.&lt;/em&gt; It is observed on the &lt;em&gt;Saptamī&lt;/em&gt; of the &lt;em&gt;śuklapaksha&lt;/em&gt; of the month of &lt;em&gt;Māgha&lt;/em&gt;. All the followers of &lt;em&gt;vaidika&lt;/em&gt; traditions such as &lt;em&gt;Śaivas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Vaishṇavas&lt;/em&gt; observe this festival with devotion and faith. The Sun is the adorable deity of this festival. He is an object of worship for all classes of people. In a &lt;em&gt;Bhaktidarśana&lt;/em&gt; called &lt;em&gt;‘Soura’&lt;/em&gt;, the sun alone is the supreme deity. He has been considered as one among the five deities in the &lt;em&gt;pūjākalpa&lt;/em&gt; also called &lt;em&gt;pañcāyatana&lt;/em&gt;. Not only this. The disc of the Sun is a medium of worship for both &lt;em&gt;Hari&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Hara&lt;/em&gt;, like the &lt;em&gt;Sālagrāma&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Śivaliṅga&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 subbarāyana ṣaśṭhī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/20_SubbarAyana_ShashThI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/20_SubbarAyana_ShashThI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Subbarāyana Shashṭhī&lt;/em&gt; is an important &lt;em&gt;Vrata&lt;/em&gt; observed in the month of &lt;em&gt;Mārgaśira&lt;/em&gt;. Though its scriptural name is &lt;em&gt;‘Skandashashṭhī’&lt;/em&gt;, since the Lord is famously known by names such as &lt;em&gt;‘Skanda’&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;‘Shaṇmukha’&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;‘Kumāra’&lt;/em&gt; etc, is called &lt;em&gt;‘Subrahmaṇyeśvara’&lt;/em&gt; in tradition, the &lt;em&gt;vrata parva&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Shashṭhī tithi&lt;/em&gt; (related to his special) worship is called &lt;em&gt;‘Subbarāyana Shashṭhī’&lt;/em&gt; in custom, where the word &lt;em&gt;Subbarāyana&lt;/em&gt; is the kannada version of the Sanskrit word of &lt;em&gt;Subrahmaṇya Rāja.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-when-should-this-vrata-be-observed&#34;&gt;1. When should this &lt;em&gt;Vrata&lt;/em&gt; be observed?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;Vrata&lt;/em&gt; should observed on the &lt;em&gt;Shashṭhī&lt;/em&gt; of the month of &lt;em&gt;Mārgaśira&lt;/em&gt; in the &lt;em&gt;śuklapaksha&lt;/em&gt;. If this &lt;em&gt;Shashṭhī&lt;/em&gt; happens to be touched by the &lt;em&gt;Pañcamī&lt;/em&gt; of the previous day, it is much superior.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 Yugādi\* Festival</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/21_UgAdi_Festival/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/21_UgAdi_Festival/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ugādi&lt;/em&gt; is the very first festival which comes on the first day of the month of &lt;em&gt;Caitra&lt;/em&gt; every year. This is a great festival which is celebrated all over India and considered an important festival in the &lt;em&gt;Śāstras&lt;/em&gt;. The multifaceted importance of this festival can be summarised as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This day is an auspicious beginning of the year, season, month, the fortnight and above all, is in the form of an introduction for the whole year. This is a day on which a plan of activities for the whole year is to be drawn up and an auspicious resolve to be made to act accordingly. And a day, when a discreet arrangement has to be contemplated after reviewing the performance of the previous year. There is a belief that resolves made on this day will be entirely very influential. Resolves for that matter, made on any day by men of great will power can be strong and effective. But, in the case of laymen, it is quite possible that the resolves and vows taken on this day, by virtue of the glory of the beginning day of the year to cause a deep impact on all their endeavours.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some have a feeling that any incident good or bad, happening on this day, may recur throughout the year. Whatever may be the fact, it will help people to feel inspired, to look for the good fruits of &lt;em&gt;Dharma&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Karma&lt;/em&gt; throughout the year, as their minds will be in a good state as a result of laudable contemplations and deeds performed on that day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 ūpākarma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/22_UpAkarma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/22_UpAkarma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Upākarma&lt;/em&gt; is one of the most important &lt;em&gt;parvas&lt;/em&gt; which is observed in the month of &lt;em&gt;Śrāvaṇa&lt;/em&gt;. This is a very important &lt;em&gt;parva&lt;/em&gt; which is observed all over India. The people of North India say—“Four very important &lt;em&gt;parvas&lt;/em&gt; are observed in our country. They are &lt;em&gt;sravanī-Upākarma&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;daśaharā&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Navarātra, Vijayadaśamī&lt;/em&gt;,) &lt;em&gt;dīvālī&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;dīpāvalī&lt;/em&gt;) and &lt;em&gt;Holī&lt;/em&gt;. Though these four are important for all, they are especially important to brahmins, &lt;em&gt;Kshatriyas, Vaishyas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;śūdras&lt;/em&gt; respectively”. &lt;em&gt;Karmas&lt;/em&gt; are of three types. They are &lt;em&gt;kāmya, nitya&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;naimittika. Kāmya karmas&lt;/em&gt; are the ones which are performed only if there is a desire for something; otherwise they need not be performed. &lt;em&gt;Nitya karmas&lt;/em&gt; are obligatory deeds which have to be performed every day. And the &lt;em&gt;Naimittika Karmas&lt;/em&gt; are the ones which should be performed compulsorily on some particular days which are significant because of the &lt;em&gt;Tithi&lt;/em&gt;, star and the planetary position of the day etc. &lt;em&gt;Upākarma&lt;/em&gt; belongs to the third category. It is a &lt;em&gt;parva karma&lt;/em&gt; which should performed every year on a particular day. It is a commendable auspicious &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt; related to the study of the &lt;em&gt;vedas&lt;/em&gt;. Some &lt;em&gt;Maharshis&lt;/em&gt; consider this as one of the eighteen &lt;em&gt;Mahāsamskāras&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 ūtsarjana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/23_Utsarjana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/23_Utsarjana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is necessary to take note of another important observence regarding the study of &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt;. It is called ‘&lt;em&gt;Adhyāyotsarjana&lt;/em&gt;’ or shortly &lt;em&gt;utsarjana&lt;/em&gt;’.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What is this &lt;em&gt;Utsarjana&lt;/em&gt;? &lt;em&gt;Utsarjana&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Udvāsana&lt;/em&gt; means leaving off or sending off. Leaving off what? It is the (leaving off of) vedic studies. On the day of &lt;em&gt;Upākarma&lt;/em&gt;, after the worship of sages and deities, &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; have to be begun (again) as per precepts, and having studied thus for a period of time constantly, the studies should be suspended temporarily, and the duration of studies also has to be limited. But that time, (at the disposal of the student) should not be idled away. It should be well utilized for the special study of &lt;em&gt;śāstras&lt;/em&gt; which are the limbs of the &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt;. And again on the day of &lt;em&gt;upākarma&lt;/em&gt;, the study of the &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; should again be begun as per precepts. Thus, for the purpose of the special study of the &lt;em&gt;śāstras&lt;/em&gt;, the constant study of the &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; is suspended in an auspicious way. This itself is &lt;em&gt;Utsarjana&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 utthānadvādaśī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/24_UtthAnadvAdashI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/24_UtthAnadvAdashI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-importance-of-kārtikamāsa&#34;&gt;The importance of &lt;em&gt;Kārtikamāsa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The most famous festival in the month of &lt;em&gt;Kārtika&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;Utthānadvādaśī&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As is evident from the lines&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“कार्तिके ज्ञानसिद्धिः स्यात्” कार्तिके तु कृता दीक्षा नृणां जन्मविमोचिनी”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the entire month of &lt;em&gt;Kārtika&lt;/em&gt; is conducive to &lt;em&gt;jnānasiddhi&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mantradīkshā svīkāra&lt;/em&gt;. And, as evident from&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“ज्ञानं महेश्वरादिच्छेत्”, all the Mondays of this month are very dear to Lord &lt;em&gt;Śiva&lt;/em&gt; who is renowned as the deity who bestows &lt;em&gt;jnāna&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Kārtika śukla navamī&lt;/em&gt; is the day stipulated to perform &lt;em&gt;Vishṇutrirātra vrata&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Kārtika śukla Caturdaśī&lt;/em&gt; known as &lt;em&gt;Vaikunṭha Caturdaśī&lt;/em&gt; is best for the worship of &lt;em&gt;vaikunṭha Nārāyaṇa&lt;/em&gt;, and again well known as the day of installation of &lt;em&gt;Viśveśvara&lt;/em&gt;, is best for the worship of &lt;em&gt;Śiva&lt;/em&gt; also. &lt;em&gt;Kārtika pūrṇima&lt;/em&gt; known as the day of &lt;em&gt;Matsyāvatāra&lt;/em&gt; is excellent for the worship of &lt;em&gt;Nārāyaṇa&lt;/em&gt;, and, also known as the day of &lt;em&gt;Tripurotsava&lt;/em&gt;, is excellent for the worship of &lt;em&gt;Śiva&lt;/em&gt;. “पौर्णमास्यां तु सन्ध्यायां कर्तव्यस्त्रिपुरोत्सवः”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 Varamahālakṣmīvrata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/25_varamahAlaxmIvrata/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/25_varamahAlaxmIvrata/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Varamahālakshmīvrata&lt;/em&gt; is considered as one of the most famous &lt;em&gt;vratas&lt;/em&gt; observed in the month of &lt;em&gt;śrāvaṇa&lt;/em&gt;. In case the month of &lt;em&gt;śrāvaṇa&lt;/em&gt; occurs twice in the form of &lt;em&gt;nija&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;adhika&lt;/em&gt; (regular and intercalary), this &lt;em&gt;Vrata&lt;/em&gt; is observed only in the &lt;em&gt;nija śrāvaṇa&lt;/em&gt;. Even though it is not enjoined among the regular &lt;em&gt;vratas&lt;/em&gt; like &lt;em&gt;Ekādaśī, Śivarātri&lt;/em&gt; etc which should be observed by all, this &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt; is observed to please Goddess &lt;em&gt;Jaganmātā&lt;/em&gt; with great devotion and religious fervour by a large number of devotees in our country.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
