<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Clans on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Clans on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Criticism and counters</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/criticism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/criticism/</guid>
      <description>Counters to western criticism of the caste system (FB15,) There is a fundamental problem here. The assumption that the &amp;ldquo;caste system&amp;rdquo; (not as you imagine it, but as it actually existed), was an inferior and immoral social system. This is a claim no one here seems to challenge, by which I presume that they&amp;rsquo;ve bought into it.
&amp;ldquo;Caste system&amp;rdquo; was not a fair system (in many meanings of the word &amp;ldquo;fair&amp;rdquo;).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Future</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/future/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/future/</guid>
      <description>Justification for change jAti-varNa system emerged as a social convenience, and hindu-s are free (and happy) to change it after the need for it has expired. As shrI-golvAlkar said: &amp;ldquo;varNa-vyavasthA is a social vyavasthA, not an avasthA&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;The two occasions on which the Purusha Sukta is invoked in its first chapter there is a rider attached to it &amp;ndash; “for the sake of prosperity and flourishing in the worlds” in the first case (.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lineage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/gotras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/gotras/</guid>
      <description>Utility Pride in ancestral accomplishments can be a great motivator in one&amp;rsquo;s own life (especially when it comes to following dharma).
Examples &amp;ldquo;If brAhmaNa archaka-s serve in those village temples suffering paltry salaries lower than what the watchman or sweeper gets, it is because of kulAbhimAna and sense of hereditary duty than anything else. Were it not for this familial urge and pride, the shAkha-s of veda which have come down to us would not at all have survived.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non brAhmaNa gotras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/abrAhmaNa-gotram/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/abrAhmaNa-gotram/</guid>
      <description>Summary As late as the 11th c. AD, in the Gotra-Pravara-Manjari of Purusottama-Pandita, it is written as still prevalent that the gotra-pravara system applies to brahman (arsheya) lineages only: the Baudhayana-Pravara-Adhyaya mentions that the (biological) descendants of the seven rishis plus Agastya as the eighth are called gotra: this is the arsha-gotra (pita-putra parampara).
The conventional sense is used as laukika-gotra (guru-shishya parampara/which non-brahmans use). Over the centuries, during to social and cultural changes, various groups in India have adopted the gotra system, but the pravara system still applies only to brahman gotras.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
