<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 Textual Studies on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 Textual Studies on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Vedic *Homa* and the Standardization of Hindu *Pūjā*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/01_The_Vedic_Homa_and_the_Standardization_of_Hindu_Pj/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/01_The_Vedic_Homa_and_the_Standardization_of_Hindu_Pj/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Timothy Lubin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;images&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt;, the ritual offering of food in a fire, has had a prolific career in Asia over the course of more than three millennia.1 In various forms, rites of this type have become a part of most of the religions that arose in India as well as their extensions and offspring from Samarqand to Japan. All of these &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt;s ultimately descend from those of the Vedic religion, but at no point has the &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; been stable. Like fire itself, it has flickered with many flames, glowing under the ashes in one place while flaring up in another, spreading, marking, and transmuting what it touches. Within the Vedic tradition, Agni played diverse roles: “Flesh-eater” in the funeral, “Offering-bearer” when yoked for sacrifice, then rewarded as “He Who Has Offered Well,” praised as “Everyman’s” because he is active in every hearth and in every heart.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Oblation, Non-conception, and Body</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/02_Oblation_Non-conception_and_Body/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/02_Oblation_Non-conception_and_Body/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SYSTEMS OF PSYCHOSOMATIC FIRE OBLATION IN ESOTERIC BUDDHISM IN MEDIEVAL SOUTH ASIA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tsunehiko Sugiki&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;images&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Brahmanism developed various forms of external fire oblation rituals from the beginning of its history.1 Meanwhile, some traditions in Brahmanism (especially the Upaniṣadic tradition) attempted to internalize fire oblation rituals and developed various theories on the internal practice of fire oblation.2&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The same attempt can be seen in Buddhist esoteric traditions. The &lt;em&gt;Mahāvairocana-sūtra&lt;/em&gt; (ca. seventh century) is the oldest Buddhist scripture that systematically teaches inner forms of fire oblation. Several esoteric scriptures (i.e., tantras) compiled after the &lt;em&gt;Mahāvairocana-sūtra&lt;/em&gt; expound a variety of different kinds of Buddhist systems of inner fire oblation. For example, in his &lt;em&gt;Jyotirmañjarī&lt;/em&gt;, Abhayākaragupta (eleventh to twelfth centuries) presents a typology of Buddhist systems of inner fire oblation: (1) mental fire oblation (&lt;em&gt;yid kyi sbyin sreg&lt;/em&gt;), (2) internal fire oblation (&lt;em&gt;nang gi sbyin sreg, adhyātmahoma&lt;/em&gt;), and (3) supreme fire oblation (&lt;em&gt;bla na med pa’i sbyin sreg&lt;/em&gt;). He further divides internal fire oblation into: (2)-1 internal fire oblation by use of external matters (&lt;em&gt;phyi rol gyi rdzas kyis nang gi sbyin sreg, bāhyavastunādhyātmahoma&lt;/em&gt;), and (2)-2 internal fire oblation with no dependence on external matter (&lt;em&gt;phyi rol gyi rdzas la ma ltos pa’i nang gi sbyin sreg&lt;/em&gt;).3 This typology is not perfect. There are other Buddhist systems of inner fire oblation that do not fall into either category, or that are mixtures of these types. (However, this typology is useful to a certain extent if we take it as a list of elements of practice that constitute actual types of inner fire oblation rather than as a list of actual types of inner fire oblation.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 The Three Types of Fire Sacrifice According to Kāṇha’s *Śrīcakrasaṃvara-homavidhi*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/03_The_Three_Types_of_Fire_Sacrifice_According_to_Khas_rcakrasavara-homavidhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/03_The_Three_Types_of_Fire_Sacrifice_According_to_Khas_rcakrasavara-homavidhi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;David B. Gray&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;images&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THE TIBETAN EXEGETICAL traditions on the &lt;em&gt;Cakrasaṃvara-tantra&lt;/em&gt; and related literature that developed by the end of the period of the second transmission of Buddhist teachings (&lt;em&gt;phyi dar&lt;/em&gt;), as exemplified by authors such as Tsongkhapa Blo-bzang-grags-pa (1357–1419 C.E.) and Jo-nang Tāranātha (1575–1634 C.E.),1 placed great emphasis on works attributed to three great Indian Mahāsiddhas. These three figures, the &lt;em&gt;lo dril nag gsum&lt;/em&gt;, were Lūi-pa, Ghaṇṭa-pa, and Kāṇha-pa. Lūi-pa is the reputed author of the &lt;em&gt;Cakrasaṃvarābhisamaya&lt;/em&gt;, an extremely influential &lt;em&gt;sādhana&lt;/em&gt; that is the subject of a dozen commentaries preserved in the Tibetan Tanjur.2 Ghaṇṭa-pa, also known as Vajraghaṇṭa-pa, is the reputed author of an influential presentation of advanced “perfection stage” (&lt;em&gt;niṣpannakrama&lt;/em&gt;) yogic practice entitled the &lt;em&gt;Śrīcakrasaṃvarapañcakrama&lt;/em&gt; (To. 1433). A number of influential ritual manuals are also attributed to him.3&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Fire Rituals by the Queen of Siddhas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/04_Fire_Rituals_by_the_Queen_of_Siddhas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/04_Fire_Rituals_by_the_Queen_of_Siddhas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Aparimitāyur-homa-vidhi-nāma&lt;/em&gt; in the Tengyur&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Georgios T. Halkias&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;images&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;FIRE, IN ITS creative and destructive potency and in its luminous immediacy, has inspired a variety of ritual activities across religious settings and mythological contexts. We may briefly recall the lame god Hephaistos (Grk. Ἥφαιστος; Lat. Vulcan), master of weaponry, metallurgy and volcanoes worshipped by the Greeks and Romans, and Hestia (Grk. Ἑστία; Lat. Vesta), the virgin goddess of the hearth bestowing blessings on the altars of the faithful. Across the Black Sea, a national hero with a “flaming beard,” “hair of fire,” and “eyes of sun,” the sun-god and king Vahagn watches after the welfare of Armenians,1 and in the Far East the Shinto Hi-No-Kagu-tsuchi-no-kami (radiant father) or Homusubi-no-kami (fire-growth) is worshipped as a fire-god by the Japanese.2 In one of the most important of all Iranian ceremonies, devotees supplicate the “wise lord” and “world-creator” Ahura Mazdā to descend from the sky as heavenly fire and merge with the ritual hearth.3 Alhough nowadays worshipers of the medium of fire are commonly identified with Zoroastrianism, the official religion of Persia that lasted nearly a millennium, the religious hypostatization of fire may predate the teachings of the prophet Zoroaster.4 Magical customs of firewalking are noted in many parts of the world, while cases of self-immolating &lt;em&gt;śramaṇa&lt;/em&gt;s (Buddhists) have been memorialized by the Greeks.5 In ancient Greek esoteric traditions death by fire was “a standard way of attaining heroic status;” especially by lightning that was seen as the purest form of death.6&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 *Homa* Rituals in the Indian *Kālacakra-tantra* Tradition</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/05_Homa_Rituals_in_the_Indian_Klacakra-tantra_Tradition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/05_Homa_Rituals_in_the_Indian_Klacakra-tantra_Tradition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vesna A. Wallace&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;images&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The diverse &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; rituals attested in the &lt;em&gt;Kālacakra-tantra&lt;/em&gt; and in its commentary, the &lt;em&gt;Vimalaprabhā&lt;/em&gt;, represent an amalgamation of theories and ritual practices unique to the Kālacakra tradition with others that are appropriations and redefinitions of Vedic fire ritual and the Sāṃkhya theory of the material world (&lt;em&gt;prakṛti&lt;/em&gt;) and its properties (&lt;em&gt;guṇa&lt;/em&gt;). The appropriation and adaptation of Vedic &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; ritual by Buddhist and Śaiva tantric traditions are well attested. Although these adaptations of Vedic &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; show certain commonalities in terms of their functions, they mutually differ in their set ritual requirements and broader theoretical contexts. However, since an examination of these differences exceeds the scope of this essay and deserves greater attention, they will not be discussed here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Ritual Subjects</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/06_Ritual_Subjects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/03_Textual_Studies/06_Ritual_Subjects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;HOMA&lt;/em&gt; IN CHINESE TRANSLATIONS AND MANUALS FROM THE SIXTH THROUGH EIGHTH CENTURIES&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Charles D. Orzech&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;images&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THE EARLY NINTH-CENTURY monk Huilin 慧琳1®describes &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; as follows: “In Tang language this Indic term is called ‘fire offering.’ Substances used to make food offerings for the worthies and sages are incinerated in a fire, just as in the four suburban and five marchmount sacrifices, etc.”2&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As a disciple of the esoteric master Amoghavajra (Bukong jin’gang 不空金剛, 704–774), Huilin was well aware of the importance of &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; not only in esoteric ritual but also as a key instrument in esoteric Buddhism’s support of the imperium. From the very beginning of his rise to power, Amoghavajra had promoted &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; as the instrument for supporting the imperial house.3 One of the first pieces of correspondence we have from Amoghavajra’s hand is dated 758, not long after Emperor Suzong retook the capital Chang’an from An Lushan’s forces. Suzong had sent a gift of incense to Amoghavajra to thank him for his efforts on behalf of the imperial cause. In his reply Amoghavajra wrote,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
