<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 Rājadharma on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 Rājadharma on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/01_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/01_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;RĀJADHARMA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;( GOVERNMENT AND STATECRAFT)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER I&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rajadharma has been a subject of discussion in works on dharmasastra from very ancient times. The Āp. Dh. S. II. 9.25.1 says &amp;ldquo;The general and special dharnus of all varṇas have been explained: but now we shall declare the dharmas of a king in particular! Āp. then states that the king should cause to be built a capital and a palace, the gates of which both should face the south; that the palace should be in the heart of the capital; that in front of the capital there was to be a hall called &amp;lsquo;aman trana&amp;rsquo; (hall of invitation); that to the south of the town there was to be an assembly house with doors on the north and south. Āp. requires that in the king&amp;rsquo;s realm no brāhmaṇa should suffer hunger, sickness, cold or heat; Ap. gives regulations about the assembly house and about persons who were to be allowed to engage in gambling; he prescribes that the exercise in) arms, dancing, singing and music should not go on anywhere except in the houses of the king&amp;rsquo;s servants, that the king was to see that there was no danger from thieves in villages and forests, that the king should donate fields and money to brāhmaṇas according to their worth without detriment to his servants, that the king who meets death in recovering the property of brāh mapas and other warlike persons who meet death in fighting for a similar worthy cause reap the merit of a sacrifice (i, e, reach heaven as reward); that the king should appoint in towns and Villages officers and their subordinates, who are pure and truth ful, for the protection of the subjects against thieves and who are to be made to make good what is stolen; that they are to collect lawful taxes for the king from the people except from learned brāhmaṇas, women of all castes, minors, students stay. ing with teachers and ascetics fulfilling the rules of their order, sūdras who do menial work for the higher castes (such as washing their feet), persons that are blind, deaf or dumb. Ap. then lays down punishments for adultery and rape, for slander and defamation, for manslaughter, for theft and appropriation of another&amp;rsquo;s land, for breach of contract to cultivate the field of another, for a herdeman leaving his herd or negligently allowingHistory of Dharmasāstra&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Seven Aṅgas of Rājya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/02_Seven_angas_of_rAjya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/02_Seven_angas_of_rAjya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER II.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SEVEN ANGAS OF RAJYA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;According to almost all of our authorities a state (rūjya) is constituted by seven elements 20 viz. svāmin (ruler or sovereign), amūtya (minister), janapada or rāṣtra (the territory of the State and its people), durga ( fortified city or capital), kośa ( accumula ted wealth in the ruler&amp;rsquo;s treasury), dandu (army), mitra (friends or allies). These seven are called angas or praktis. The word praksti in works on politics is also used for the constituents of a circle of states (of a mandala). Vide Manu VII. 156 and Kau tilya (VI.2). The word also means ministers as in Sukranitisāra II. 70-73 and &amp;lsquo;subjects&amp;rsquo; in Khāravela&amp;rsquo;s Inscription (E. I. vol. 20 p.79 1. 4), Nārada (prakīrṇaka 5), Raghuvamsa VIII. 18. The order in which these are arranged and their names vary a good deal. The quotations given below will indicate how the order differs. The sequence is important for the reason that some of our authorities expressly state that when calamities be fall or deterioration sets in each of the seven elements, those that befall each preceding one are more serious for the State than those of each succeeding one ( Kautilya VIII. 1, Manu IX. 295). For janapada sometimes the word jana or rāṣtra is used, for * danda&amp;rsquo; the word &amp;lsquo;bala&amp;rsquo; and the word &amp;lsquo;pura&amp;rsquo; for &amp;lsquo;durga&amp;rsquo;. The Aśramavāsiparva (5.8) speaks of eight angas of rājya. Accord ing to Sumantu quoted by the Sarasvativilāsa (p. 46 ) danda means “punishment bodily or monetary” and&amp;rsquo; army is included under ‘kośa&amp;rsquo;. Sumantu says that th esvūmin has to be preserved by himself, the ministers by showing them proper respect, the people by keeping them contented, the fortified capital by abun dance of wealth and grain, the kośa by proper expenditure, danda&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Duties of the Ruler</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/03_Duties_of_the_Ruler/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/03_Duties_of_the_Ruler/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER tft&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;DUTIES AND RESPONSIBILITIES OF&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THE RULER.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All works are agreed that the first and foremost duty of the king is the protection of subjects. Sāntiparva (68.1-4) notes that all the seven expounders of polity (rājaśāstraprane tāraḥ) named by it extol protection as the highest dharma of the king. Manu VII. 144 states that the protection of subjects is the highest dharma and Kālidāsa in Raghuvamsa 14.67 alludes to this dictum of Manu. Protection consists in punishing internal aggression (such as by thieves and robbers and by persons who invade a man&amp;rsquo;s rights ) and in meeting external 88 aggression. Vide quotation from Bphaspati below. Gautama (X. 7-8) prescribes that the special responsibility of the king is to protect all beings, to award just punishment and that he has to protect the several varṇas and aśramas according to the rules of śāstra and to bring them round to the path of their proper duties when they swerve from it (XI. 9-10). Vasiṣtha ( 19. 1-2) states that the wise say that protection is a life-long sattra in which he has to give up fear and softness of heart. Vas. 19.7-8 and Viṣṇu Dh. S. III. 2-3 are similar to Gaut. XI. 9-10. The Sāntiparva ( 23.15 ) repeats a gātha of Bphaspati. As a snake gwallows mice lying in holes, so the earth swallows these two viz, a king who does not fight (an invader) and a brāhmana who does not go on a journey (for acquiring knowledge from famous teachers ) 68a Manu IX. 306 states that the king pro tecting his subjects according to the śāstra and meting out punishment to those who deserve it performs every day sacrifices in which the fees are one hundred thousand cows (i.e. he secures the spiritual reward of very solemn sacrifices). Yāj. I. 335 is to the same effect. Kautilya also lays emphasis on the duty to keep the varṇas and aśramas to their duties &amp;lsquo;Therefore the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Ministers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/04_Ministers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/04_Ministers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER IV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;MINISTERS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Amatya -The second of the seven elements of rājya is the amālya, which word may be translated as &amp;lsquo;minister.&amp;rsquo; There are three words that are interchangeable though sometimes dis tinguished, viz. amõtya, saciva and mantrin, the first being the oldest of the three. A Kārikā on Pāṇini (IV. 2. 104) teaches the formation of the word with the affix tyap (tya ) from ama meaning near or with&amp;rsquo;( vide Mahābhāṣya, vol. II. p. 292). In Rg. IV. 4. 1 188 there is the germ of this word &amp;lsquo;O Agnil Go like a king riding an elephant, accompanied by his ministers &amp;lsquo;. Yāska (in Nirukta VI. 12 ) explains&amp;rsquo; amayān &amp;rsquo; as &amp;lsquo;amātya vān,&amp;rsquo; though two more explanations of the word are offered by him. The word amatya itself occurs in Rg. VII. 15. 3, but there it is an adjective and means &amp;lsquo;our own&amp;rsquo; or &amp;rsquo; abiding in our house &amp;lsquo;. In some of the sūtras like the Baudhāyanapitf-medhasūtra (I. A. 13, I. 12. 7 ) the word amātya is used in the sense of &amp;rsquo;near male relations in the house&amp;rsquo;. Vide H. Dh, vol. II. p. 588 n. 1375. The word &amp;rsquo; amātya&amp;rsquo; occurs in the sense of minister in Ap. Dh. 8. II. 10. 25. 10 The king should not live better or more luxuriously than his gurus ( elders) and his ministers (gurūn amātyānsca nātijivet)&amp;rsquo;. The word &amp;lsquo;gaciva&amp;rsquo; occurs in the Ait. Br. ( XII. 9) where it is said that Indra considered the Maruts as his &amp;lsquo;sacivas&amp;rsquo; (helpers or comrades). The necessity of amatyas or sacivas is stated in graphic language by several writers. Kautilya (I. 7 last verse ) says &amp;lsquo;kingship is possible only with ( the aid of) assistants, a single wheel cannot work ( a chariot ); therefore the king should appoint ministers and listen to their opinions&amp;rsquo;. Manu ( VII. 55 = Sukra II. 1) says it is difficult for a person single-handed to accomplish even an easy task ; how can government particularly, which has great good as its aim, be accomplished without helpers&amp;rsquo;? The Matsya-purāṇa ( 215. 2 ) prescribes the king, while his head is still wet with the waters of coronation, if he wants to supervise his State, should choose his helpers, as in the latter the kingdom secures stability. Matsya 215. 3 is the same as Manu VII. 55. Vide&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Rāṣṭra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/05_rAShTra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/05_rAShTra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER V&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;RĀSTRA (THE TERRITORY OF A STATE)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;DDT WI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;rastra&amp;rsquo; occurs even in the Rgveda (IV. 42.1, &amp;lsquo;mania dvitā rāstram kṣatriyasya”)-‘mine is the kingdom on both sides (or in both spheres)&amp;rsquo; says king Trasadasyu. In Rg. VII. 34,11 Varuna is praised as the Lord of rāṣtras ( rājā rāṣtrāṇām &amp;amp;c.). In Rg. VII. 84.2 and X. 109. 3 the word rāstra occurs. In a very famous benedictory 175 passage of the Tai. S. VII. 5. 18. 10 = Vāj. S. 22.22 ) one of the blessings invoked is &amp;lsquo;may the king in this kingdom become brave, a skilled archer, and a great warrior&amp;rsquo;, Vide Tai, Br. III. 8. 13 for explanation of the Tai, S. passage. In the Atharvaveda XII. 1. 8 and 10 the earth is called mother and invoked to impart to the rāṣtra strength and brilliance (or energy ). Kām. VI. 3 says 175 that since all the elements of the State spring from the territory of the State, the king should raise up his territory with all his efforts. The Agnipurāṇa 239, 2 holds that rāṣtra is the most important of all elements of the State. Manu VII. 69 prescribes that a king should make his home in a country that is not water-logged (i. e. is dry and not moist ), 176 is rich in crops, inhabited mostly by Aryas (or well-conducted people), not disturbed ( by epidemics &amp;amp;c.), that is charming (owing to trees, flowers and fruits ), the chiefs in which have submitted to him and in which livelihood can be had easily. Yāj. I. 321 and Viṣṇudharmasūtra III. 4-5 are to the same .effect. Kām. (IV. 50-56 ) remarks the territory of&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Durgā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/06_Durga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/06_Durga/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER VI DURGA ( FORT OR CAPITAL)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Manu IX, 294 places the capital (pura) even before rastra. Medhātithi (on IX. 295 ) and Kullūka explain that the loss of the capital is a more serious danger than even the loss of some territory, because if the capital, which possesses all the stocks of food, in which are centred the principal elements and the army, is saved, then it is possible to retrieve even lost territory and to protect the country. It is as it were the pivot of the whole machinery of government. Other writers (and even Manu in VII. 69-70) place the capital or fort after the rastra. It is probably due to the geographical situation in North India and the nature of the fighting in ancient times that made the capi tal and forts of great importance in the several elements of the State. The capital mirrored the prosperity of the country and if properly walled also provided security. Yāj. I. 321 says that forts are meant for the safety of the king, the people and the treasury (janakośātmaguptaye). The reason for the construction of forts is well put by Manu VII. 74 viz. that a single archer under the shelter of the fort-wall can fight a hundred of the enemy and a hundred can fight ten thousand. The Pañcatantra (I. 229 and II. 14 ) has a similar verse. Bphaspati quoted by the Rājanītiprakāśa 288 p. 202 states that the king should con struct a fort with walls and a gate for the protection of himself, his wives, the people and the ( wealth ) collected by him. Kaut. (II. 3 and 4) deals at length with the construction of durgas and the laying out of the capital in one of them. He says that in the four quarters of the boundaries of the kingdom forts should be built for offering resistance (to the enemy) on ground naturally fitted for the purpose. He speaks of four kinds of forts viz. &amp;lsquo;audaka&amp;rsquo; (water-protected, which is on an island burrounded by water or on a plain surrounded by low ground), pārvata (mountain one, such as a rocky hill or a cave ), dhūnvana (desert fort, on a waterless tract full of thickets or waste land ), a forest fort full of wagtails and water and&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Kośa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/07_kosha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/07_kosha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER VII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;KOSA (TREASURY OR FINANCE)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kaut (II. 1) states that a king whose treasury is depleted preys upon the citizens and the rural population and (II. 8) very 231 rightly remarks that all undertakings depend upon kośa (financial position of the king), therefore the king must pay the first attention to kośa. Gautama (as cited by 8. V. p. 46 ) holds that kośa is the basis or support of the other six elements of the State. The Sāntiparva 119. 16 calls upon the king to guard his finances with great effort, since kings depend upon kośa, which tends to the prosperity ( of the kingdom). Kām. XIII. 33 states that it is on the lips of all that the king is dependent on koga. Sānti 133 contains a eulogy of kośa. The Viṣṇudharmottara II. 61, 17 says that kośa is the root of the tree of State. The two great pillars of the Indian States in ancient India were the revenue and the army. Manu VII. 65 says that kośa and the government of the realm depend on the king i. e. they should be the personal concern of the king. Yāj. (I. 327-328) recommends that the king should personally look into the income and expenditure every day and keep in his treasury buildings whatever is brought by those who are appointed to bring gold and wealth. Kām. V.77 and Sukra I. 276-278 say the same. The Rājataran gini (VII. 507-508) tells us that king Kalasa of Kashmir (1063–1089 A. D.) kept accounts like a merchant, closely watched income and expenditure and had a clerk by his side with chalk and bhūrja ( birch leaf) to write upon. The principal means of filling the treasury is taxation. It is therefore neces sary to consider first the principles of taxation as evolved by our writers. The first principle was that the king could not levy, according to the smrtis, taxes at his pleasure or sweet will, that the rates of taxes which the king was entitled to lovy were fixed by the smrtis and varied only according to the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Bala</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/08_Bala/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/08_Bala/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER VIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;BALA (THE ARMY).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bala is also called danda in Kaut and elsewhere. Accord ing to Sumantu dapda means &amp;lsquo;punishment, corporal or monetary&amp;rsquo; and the army with its four arms is included by Sumantu under kośa ( acc. to $. V. p. 46).260 In the Rgveda we have frequent references to armies, weapons, battles &amp;amp;c. The word senāni occurs in Rg. X. 84. 2 where Manyu ( martial Fury ) is invoked to be the Commander.261 Rg. VI. 75 is full of references to bows, arrows, armour, bow-strings, quiver, charioteer, horses, chariots &amp;amp;c. Kām. (XIII. 34-37 ) states that the king possessed of a sound financial position increases his depleted army, supports his own subjects and is depended upon even by his enemies. All the following result from the possession of a (powerful ) army viz. increase of the wealth of one&amp;rsquo;s friends and enemies and of the ( king&amp;rsquo;s) territories, prompt attainment of objects that seemed distant, protection of what is already secur ed, destruction of the armies of the enemy, the keeping together of one&amp;rsquo;s army. Most authorities agree in saying that troops are of six kinds viz. maula (hereditary ), bhrta or bhṛtaka or bhitya (hired troops ), śreni (guild troops ), mitra ( troops of an ally or friendly power or feudatories ), amitra ( troops that once belonged to the enemy ), atavi or ātavika (wild tribes as troops). Vide Kaut. 242 IX. % (first sentence ), Kām. XVIII. 4, Agnipurāṇa 242. 1-2, Mānasollāsa ( II. 6, verge 556 p. 76). The first three works say that each earlier variety of troops is superior to each later one. Maula troops corresponded to the modern standing army, since Kaut. (IX. 2) prefers them on the ground that they depend on the king for maintenance and are being constantly drilled. They most probably consisted of persons who and whose ancestors got tax-free lands in lieu of military service. The Sabba parva 5, 63 appears to refer to four kinds ( omitting śreni and amitra ) and Yuddhakanda 17. 24 refers to five ( omitting śrepi).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 Mitra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/09_Mitra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/09_Mitra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER IX SUHRT OR MITRA (ALLY OR FRIEND).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Manu inculcates the necessity of making friends in VII. 208 and cites the qualities of a good friend (for. a king) &amp;lsquo;a king does not prosper by the acquisition of gold and land so much as by securing a firm friend who would be powerful in future, though he may be of depleted resources at the time. That friend, though a weak one, is commended, who is righteous, grateful, whose subjects (or ministers) are contented, who is attached and who pursues (to the end) work undertaken&amp;rsquo;. According to Manu VII. 206 land, gold and ally are the three fruits of royal endeavour or policy. Yāj I. 352 is similar to Manu VII. 208. In VII. 9 Kautilya in opposition to the above holds that the acquisition of land is better than that of gold and friend and the acquisition of gold is superior to that of a friend284. The Mahā. bharata (Santi 138.110) states &amp;rsquo;no one is the friend or enemy of any one else; friends or enemies are made by wealth (or objects pursued by a person):285 Kām. VIII. 52 says the same. Sukra. (IV. 1.8-10) opines&amp;rsquo; in the case of a brave, energetic, strong and politic king all others, though outwardly friendly, secretly cherish enmity to bim and only wait for (the proper) time to strike). There is no wonder in this. Are they not themselves greedy of conquering territories? A king has no friend and he is the friend of none&amp;rsquo;. Santi (80. 3) says286 that a friend is of four kinds, one who has the same goal, one who comes for protec tion or security, one who is naturally go and one who is acqui. red. Karnaparva 88. 28 gives the four kinds somewhat diffe rently viz. natural (sahaja), acquired by conciliatory words,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Purpose of the Study of Rājadharma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/10_Purpose_of_the_Study_of_rAjadharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/1_rAjadharma/10_Purpose_of_the_Study_of_rAjadharma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER X&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PURPOSE OF THE STUDY OF RĀJADHARMA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;AND THE ENDS OF THE STATE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the preceding pages an attempt has been made to present a picture of the theory and practice of Government and state craft as delineated by ancient and medieval Indian writers on dharmaśāstra and arthaśāstra. One feature that would strike any reader is the religious colouring with which all theories and ideals are suffused. Another is that the ideal set before rulers and their officers is a highly moral one. Several faults have been found in the theory and practice inculcated by the writers. Except for some centuries before and after the Christian era, monarchy has been the only form of government known in India&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
