<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;घोराङ्गीरसः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/articles/ghorAngIrasa/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;घोराङ्गीरसः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/articles/ghorAngIrasa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A short discussion on</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/articles/ghorAngIrasa/2018-07-22_a-short-discussion-on-pertinent-issues-presented-b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/articles/ghorAngIrasa/2018-07-22_a-short-discussion-on-pertinent-issues-presented-b/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
A short discussion on pertinent issues presented by the sabarimalA matter
It’s often argued that restrictive rules, in terms of temple entry or offering worship at one, impinge upon the “right to participate in religion” of those who are thus restricted. This stems from a fundamental misunderstanding of participation as intrinsically a positive act.
What do I mean by “positive act”? Most of us see would see participation as actually (and thus, positively) doing acts one generally does in a religious setting: such as entering a temple or performing a particular ritual.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Patrilineal ancestry as ritual input</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/articles/ghorAngIrasa/patrilineal-ancestry_as_ritual-input/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/articles/ghorAngIrasa/patrilineal-ancestry_as_ritual-input/</guid>
      <description>The adhikAra for vaidika rites was intimately tied to one’s ArSeyatvam. It is this essential ArSeyatvam (literally: the state of being descended from a RSi) that gives the right to upanayanam, conduct rites, etc.. There are indicators for this ArSeyatvam: gotra/pravara, AprI sUkta (there is a particular sUkta for each of the RSi clans of the brAhmaNas; there are even particular AprI sUktas for kSatriyas &amp;amp; vaishyas).
The rites &amp;amp; mantras were first “seen” by the RSis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ritual participation and ritual reality</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/articles/ghorAngIrasa/ritual-participation_and_ritual-reality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/articles/ghorAngIrasa/ritual-participation_and_ritual-reality/</guid>
      <description>Ritual reality and coherence In our dharma, everything imaginable, whether it be age, gender, various trees, animals, metals, other materials, colours, shapes, times, numbers, etc are all given sacral meaning, a ritual significance. This is a quintessential aspect of Hinduism as it is practiced. Anyone who seeks to stamp on our traditions, either out of ignorance or malice, we must fiercely resist with every effort at our disposal. It is hoped that this thread gives an idea into certain dimensions of Hindu ritual thought &amp;amp; the rationale behind restrictions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temple ritual inputs</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/articles/ghorAngIrasa/temple-ritual-inputs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/meta-ritual/articles/ghorAngIrasa/temple-ritual-inputs/</guid>
      <description>The vast majority of Temples were built in accordance with particular textual traditions &amp;amp; were intended to be sites where rituals are held in perpetuity in accordance with those texts &amp;amp; associated extra-textual traditions. The traditions place a premium on particular patrilines.
Giving tradition as a distinct option &amp;amp; that too in quotation marks betrays the all-too-often bias that traditions not based in a scripture/text are nonsense or just “made up”.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
