<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Dharmasastra Works and Writers on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/Dharmasastra_Works_and_Writers/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Dharmasastra Works and Writers on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/Dharmasastra_Works_and_Writers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>List of Authors</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/Dharmasastra_Works_and_Writers/Appendix_B_List_of_Authors_on_dharmashAstra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/Dharmasastra_Works_and_Writers/Appendix_B_List_of_Authors_on_dharmashAstra/</guid>
      <description>Appendix B List of Authors on Dharmaśāstra
APPENDIX B
LIST OF AUTHORS ON DHARMASÁSTRA
While preparing this list, great difficulties were experienced in stating all the works composed by an author. In the case of such names as Ananta, Krsna, Gangadhara, Nārāyaṇa, Rama kļṣṇa, Śhaṅkara which are extremely common, the only method that could be followed, in the absence of materials to identify the authors bearing these names, was to place the same name several times in the list against the work composed by that author.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>List of Works</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/Dharmasastra_Works_and_Writers/Appendix_A_List_of_Works_on_dharmashAstra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/Dharmasastra_Works_and_Writers/Appendix_A_List_of_Works_on_dharmashAstra/</guid>
      <description>Appendix A List of Works on Dharmaśāstra
APPENDIX A.
List of Works on Dharmaśāstra It is necessary to say a few words about the methods followed in preparing this list of the works on dharmaśāstra. Purely srauta works have generally been excluded, except where they have been profusely quoted or relied upon by dharmaśāstra writers. Works of the Tantra class and the Purāṇas have been passed over, inas-much as they form in themselves independent and extensive branches of Sanskrit literature requiring an exhaustive and detailed treatment, which from considerations of space had to be abandoned here.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
