<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;10 Hindu Culture and Civilization on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/10_Hindu_Culture_and_Civilization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;10 Hindu Culture and Civilization on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/10_Hindu_Culture_and_Civilization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/10_Hindu_Culture_and_Civilization/36_Characteristics_of_Hindu_Culture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/10_Hindu_Culture_and_Civilization/36_Characteristics_of_Hindu_Culture/</guid>
      <description>Ṛg.+++ title = &amp;ldquo;36 Characteristics of Hindu Culture&amp;rdquo;
+++
SECTION X
The fundamental conceptions and characteristics of Hindu (Bharatiya) culture and civilization from the Vedic times to about 1800 A. D. and future trends.
CHAPTER XXXVI
Fundamental and leading characteristics of Hindu culture and civilization
It is necessary to gather together the threads scattered over six thousand pages of the History of Dharmaśāstra and to emphasize the fundamental and leading characteristics and conceptions of Hindu culture and civilization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>37 Future Trends</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/10_Hindu_Culture_and_Civilization/37_Future_Trends/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/10_Hindu_Culture_and_Civilization/37_Future_Trends/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXXVII
Future Trends After the battle of Plassey in 1757 the civil government of the three large provinces of Bengal, Bihar and Orissa came under British rule from 1765. From 1818 when the last Peshwa Bajirao II was defeated and became a pensioner, the British were in control over the whole of India except Punjab, which was subdued in 1845. The British left India in 1947. Therefore, they were rulers over a large part of India for 180 years, over the whole of it except Punjab for about 130 years and over Punjab just about 100 years.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
