<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 Vyavahāra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 Vyavahāra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>11 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/11_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/11_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;VYAVAHARA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(LAW AND ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That to administer justice impartially and to punish the guilty were among the prime functions of the sovereign has been stated above (p. 57). The king was deemed to be the fountain (i. e. the distributor ) of justice. Kautilya 323 (I. 19) prescribes that the king was to look into the disputes of citizens and country people in the 2nd part of the day (divided into eight parts ). Manu (VIII. 1-3) states that the king desirous of looking into the disputes of people should enter the sabhā ( the hall of justice ) accompanied by brāhmaṇas, ministers and should there decide every day the causes of litigants. Sukra IV.5.45 is the same as Manu VII. 1, Vas. 16-2, Saṅkha-Likhita, Yāj. I. 327 and II. 1, Vispu Dh. S. II. 72, Nār. (1.2), Sukra IV. 5.5, Mānasollasa II. 20, verse 1243 state that the administration of justice was the personal concern of the king. The Mit on Yāj. II. 1 says that protecting the subjects is the highest duty of a king and that that duty cannot be discharged without eradicating and punishing the wicked, which latter requires that the king should administer justice ( vyavahāradarśana). Medhātithi on Manu VIII. 1 also says that protection consists in the removal of troubles, secular and spiritual (adrsta ). Manu VIII. 12 and 14 ( = Nār. III. 8-9 p. 42) personifies the administration of justice as Dharma incarnate by representing that when justice is administered the dart of adharma or falsehood by which dharma is pierced is taken out from the body of Dharma. Yāj. (I. 359-360) declares that the impartial administration of justice yields the same rewards as solemn vedic sacrifices do. In this way administra tion of justice was held to be a very sacred duty. Manu VIII. 128 ( = Vļddha-Hārlta VII. 194) declares that a king who punishes those that do not deserve to be punished and who does not punish those that deserve punishment incurs great obloquy and goes to hell. Vas. (19.40-43) prescribes one day&amp;rsquo;s fast for the king and three days&amp;rsquo; fast for the purohita when the king lets off those that deserve punishment and three days&amp;rsquo; fast for the king and the kṣcchra penance for the purohita when the king&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 Bhukti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/12_Bhukti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/12_Bhukti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;BHUKTI or BHOGA (possession ).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;According to Gaut. X. 39 a man becomes an owner by inheritance, purchase, partition, seizure (appropriation of forest trees and other things which have no owner ) and find ing (i. e. appropriation of lost property the owner of which is unknown). Gaut. (X. 40-41) adds that in the case of brāhmaṇas acceptance (of a thing donated) is an additional mode (of becoming an owner), that conquest in the case of a ksatriya and gain ( by trade or labour ) in the case of a vaisya or sūdra are also additional modes. Vag. 16. 16 mentions eight modes. Br. ( quoted in V. P. p. 153, Aparārka p. 635, S. B. E. vol. 33 p. 309 v. 2) mentions seven modes of acquiring immovable property viz. by learning, purchase, mortgage, valour (i. e, conquest ), through the wife ( as dowry ), inheritance (from an ancestor ) and succession to an issueless kinsman, Nārada (q. in Sm. C. II. p. 70) mentions the same except mortgage. None of these expressly says that long possession is by itself a source of ownership. Great divergence 449 has prevailed throughout the centuries among the sages and digests about the relation of title and possession and about the length of possession necessary for making a person secure in his right to property by reason of possession. Possession (bhukti ) may be with title ( sāgamā) or without title ( anagamū). Agama means &amp;rsquo; origin&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;source of title&amp;rsquo; such as purchase or simply &amp;rsquo; title :. 450 Manu VIII. 200, Yaj. II. 27, Nār. IV. 84 employ that word in that sense. Vide Kāt. 317 (q. in Sm. C. II p. 73 and Par. M. III. p. 141). If property is held in one of the modes of acquiring ownership stated above and there is also possession, one&amp;rsquo;s right to that property is indefeasible ( Nār. IV. 85, Bṛ. q. by Sm. C. II. p. 70, S. B. E. 33 pp. 309 and 312 v. 3 and 22 ), but possession without a clear title&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 Witnesses</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/13_Witnesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/13_Witnesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;WITNESSES (saksinah).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word saksin occurs in the Svetasvataropanisad 76 (VI. 11) wliere it is applied tu the une immanent Spirit of the uni. verse as All-seving. Panini 477 V. 2. 91 explains the word sākṣin as meaning one who has directly seen&amp;rsquo;. Gaut. 478 XIII. 1, Kant. III. 11, Nar. IV. 147 state that when two persons litigate and there is a doubt or discrepancy between the two the deter mination of the truth in the dispute is due to witnesses. Manu VIII. 74, Sabhaparva 479 68,84, Nar. IV. 148, Vishu Dh. S. 8. 13, Kat. 346 (q. in V. M. p. 317 and V. P. p. 106) provide that a (proper) witness is one who has himself either seen or heard or experienced the matter in dispute. This means that the evidence of a witness must be direct and should not be what is called hearsay, Medhātithi (on Manu VIII. 74) says 480 that hearsay evidence occurs when a person who hears from another that has himself heard soinething from another coines forward as a witness and that hearsay is no legal evidence. Manu VIII. 76 prescribes that even though a man may not have been expressly asked or appointed by the parties (in the word:4 &amp;rsquo; you are the witness to this transaction&amp;rsquo;), he is a proper witness when asked it to any matter in dispute that lie has himself seen or heard. The only exception to hearsay evidence ullowed by&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 Ordeals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/14_Ordeals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/14_Ordeals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XIV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ORDEALS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A brief history of ordeals may be get out here. Rg. I. 158. 4-5, wherein 561 the sage Dirghatamas, son of Ucatha, prays that the fire of faggots heaped tenfold may not burn him and that the rivers in which he was thrown bound hand and foot may not engulf him, are regarded by some as a reference to the ordeal of fire and water. Yet in those verses there is probably no reference to ordeals, but to the cruel treatment of Dirghatanas by dūsas headed by Traitana. Rg. III. 53. 22 also, where it 562 is said &amp;lsquo;he beats the axe (or acc. to Sāyana &amp;lsquo;just as the tree is injured by contact with the axe &amp;amp;c.&amp;rsquo;)&amp;rsquo;, does not contain a clear or certain reference to the ordeal of holding the heated axe. Atharvaveda 563 II. 12 is held by several Western scholars to contain a reference to the fire ordeal. This also is far from certain, though verse 8 may lend some support to that view $64. The Pancavimśa (or Tāndya ) Brāhmaṇa 14. 6. 6 refers 565 to the story of Vatsa, who was abused by his step-brother that the former was the son of a sūdra woman, against which Vatsa protested, urged that he was a brāhmaṇa, entered fire to prove the truth of his assertion and came out of fire unscathed. This is referred to by Manu VIII, 116. This is probably the earliest&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 Decision</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/15_Decision/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/15_Decision/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;DECISION&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The last (i. e. 4th) stage in a judicial proceeding is siddhi (Yaj. II. 8) or nirṇaya ( decision). If pratyākalita (as defined above on p. 298) is regarded as a pāda of vyavahāra (and since all are agreed that there are only four pādas) then the decision is not a pūda of a lawsuit but is the fruit thereof (V. P. p. 86). When the evidence has been led, the king (or chief justice ) should with the help of the sabhyas decide upon the success or failure of the plaintiff594, Nar. II. 42 says that the sabhyas should ask the parties to leave the court when they are considering their verdict or what decision was to be pronounced 5%. It is stated by Vyāsa and Sukra IV. 5. 271 that the decision of a case is based on eight sourceg 596 ( 6 acc. to Sukra) viz. the three pramāṇas (possession, documents and witnesses ), logical inference, the usages of the country, sapathas (oaths and ordeals), the king&amp;rsquo;s edict and the admission of the litigants. Pitāmaka prescribes that, in disputes where there are no witnesses, no possession nor documents and no recourse can be had to divine proof, there the king is the final deciding factor as he is the lord of all 597&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 Contracts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/16_Contracts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/16_Contracts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XVI.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CONTRACTS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are only three titles of law, viz, recovery of debts, the relation of husband and wife (stripunsayoga) and partition of wealth (dāyabhāga) that are of importance to modern Hindus, since to a very large extent they are oven now governed in these matters by the ancient Hindu Law as interpreted by the commentators. These three topics therefore have to be described in detail while other titles will not and cannot be allowed to occupy much space. In almost all smrtis and digests of Hindu Law rṇādāna (recovery of debts) is treated of first. Therefore here also that subject will be taken up first. A good deal of the matter falling under the title of the relation of husband and wife has already been dealt with in the 2nd volume of the History of Dharmaśāstra pp. 427-636. The topic of dāyubhāga will be dealt with last of all, the other topics being taken up in the same order as in Manu. Many of the vyavahūrapadas are concerned with the law of contracts in various aspects, viz. the contract of debt, of pledge or mortgage, of bailments, of sale, of partnership, of hire and service.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 Asvāmivikraya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/17_asvAmivikraya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/17_asvAmivikraya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XVII ASVĀMIVIKRAYA ( sale by one not the owner ).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The different modes of the sources of ownership have already been referred to ( H. of Dh. vol. II. pp. 130 ff) and will be referred to again under dayabhāga. According to Nār. VII. 1 and Br. (SBE vol. 33 p. 335 verse 2) when 789 a person, who holds an open deposit, a sealed deposit, an article bailed for delivery to another, stolen property, an article borrowed for some festival, a pledge, or property lost by a stranger and found ( by him ), sells it in secret ( or behind the back of the owner ) it is to be considered as a sale by one who is not the rightful owner. Vyasa has a similar verse. The word &amp;lsquo;sells&amp;rsquo; is only illustrative and includes gifts and pledges. Similarly as most sales by one not the owner are clandestinely brought about, Bs. employs the words in secret&amp;rsquo; but even if the sale is effected openly the same consequences may follow. The same rules will apply to an article lost by the owner and found by a stranger. Kat. ( 612 ) provides 790 that a sale, gift, or pledge, made by one who is not the owner, should be rescinded ( by the king or judge), Manu VIII. 199 and Nar. (q. by Sm. C. II. p. 213, V. P. p. 291 ) and others say the same thing. Yāj. II. 168, Nār. VII. 2 provide that the owner is entitled to recover his property from the person that purchases from one who is not the owner. If the buyer purchases an article not in the open market, then he is liable for punishment; if he purchases from one who could have no means of posgessing the thing sold (such as a slave without the master&amp;rsquo;s consent) or for a very inadequate price or at a very unusual hour (at midnight or&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 Sambhūya-samutthāna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/18_sambhUya-samutthAna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/18_sambhUya-samutthAna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XVIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SAMBHŪYA-SAMUTTHĀNA 801 (A joint undertaking, partnership).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Where traders or others (like actors, musicians or artisans) carry on a business jointly it is termed a partnership (Nar. VI. 1 and Kat. 624).802_Bx. (SBE Vol. 33 p. 336 verses 1-2) says that a man should carry on a joint business with other persons of good family, that are clever, active, intelligent (or educated), familiar with coins, skilled in ( controlling ) expenditure and income, honest and valiant ( or enterprising ) and that joint undertakings like trade should not be carried on by prudent men with persons (partners ) who are weak or lazy or afflicted with disease or are unlucky or destitute ( of money ), 803 The meaning is not that all the above qualities must exist in all partners, but that according to the nature of the undertaking some of these qualities will be absolutely necessary. Nar. VI. 2-3, Yaj. II. 259, Br. (SBE vol. 33 pp. 336-337 verses 3 and 4) prescribe that the expenses, loss, profit or work of those who jointly lend gold, grain or liquids shall be according to the capital put in by each. 804 The duty of each is to act honestly towards the others, whether they are present or absent,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 Dattānapākarma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/19_dattAnapAkarma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/19_dattAnapAkarma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;DATTĀNAPAKARMA (resumption of gift).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This title is also called dattāpradūnika 815 (lit. that which is concerned with the non-delivery or resumption of a gift ). Nār. VII. 1 defines it as that title where a man desires to resume what has been given by him because it has been improperly (in a manner opposed to law ) given by him. Nār. (VII. 2 ) divides this title into four topics viz, what may not be given, what may be given, what are valid gifts and what are invalid gifts, Nār. VII. 3-5 and Br. (SBE vol. 33 p. 342 verse 2) state that there are eight things that cannot be given (adeyu ) viz, an anvāhita, a deposit, yācitaka, a pledge, property jointly owned with others, a deposit, son and wife, the entire property in the case of one who has offspring, and what has been already promised to another. Vide Kauṭ. III. 16, Yāj. II. 175 816 for a similar but more com pendious statement, and Kāt. 638. These cannot be given either because they are not one&amp;rsquo;s absolute property or because the gift of them is forbidden by the sages. In the case of even those who hold that one has ownership over one&amp;rsquo;s son or wife, the gift of them is not possible because it is forbidden, just as though one owns rice, yavas and māṣı beans, one cannot make offerings of maṣa because the veda prohibits their use in the words&amp;rsquo; ayajñiyā vai māṣāḥ&amp;rsquo;(q. by Sabara on Jai. VI. 3. 20). So son and wife cannot be given on account of the prohibition in the smrtis. The general rule of what may be given is stated&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 Vetanasyānapākarma and related topics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/20_vetanasyAnapAkarma_and_related_topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/20_vetanasyAnapAkarma_and_related_topics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;VETANASYANAPĀKARMA, ABHYUPETYASUŚRŪSĀ&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;AND SVĀMIPĀLAVIVADA (Non-payment of wages, non-rendition of service, dispute&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;between master and herdsman ).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;TH&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The question about the payment or non-payment of wagen to those whose services are hired for work is dealt with under this title ( Nār. IX. 1). According to Bp. there 826 are three titles of law in which the question of hiring enters, viz. abhyupetya $usrūṣā, vetanasyānapākarma and svūnipūlavivāda. Manu and Kauṭ. do not treat of the first of these three. Here vetanasya napākurma will be first dealt with, then abhyupetyāśutrūṣā and suāmipālavivāda will be separately treated of. All these three topics are concerned with masters and servants or employers and employees. The rules are different according as the contract of service is for a fixed term or for an indefinite period or is for executing a definite piece of work and according as the rate of wages or the hire is fixed beforehand or is not fixed. We have further to remember that the rules are spread over a large period i. e. from about 6th century B. C. to about 500 A. D. (from Gaut. and Āp. to Bṛ. and Kat. ). The rules deal with the liabilities of both masters and servants. Nar.IX.2 states that the wages agreed upon may be paid at the beginning, in the middle or at the end of the work undertakon, But when no wages are settled beforehand Nār. IX. 3, Yāj. II. 194, Kaut. III. 327 13 provide that the ( agent of a ) trader, the cowherd, the husbandman should receive a tenth part respectively of the profit, of the milk and of the crops. This latter according to the Sm. C. II&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 Saṁvid-vyatikrama and other titles</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/21_Savid-vyatikrama_and_other_titles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/21_Savid-vyatikrama_and_other_titles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;TT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SAMVID-VYATIKRAMA AND OTHER TITLES&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;( Violation of compacts or conventions)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nār. ( XIII. 1 ) employs the expression samayasyānapākarma. Manu VIII. 5 employs the first expression. Manu (VIII. 218-219) has both names in view, when he says &amp;lsquo;I shall now declare the rules applicable to those who violate samayas (conventions ). He who having entered into a compact (samvid) under (the sanction of) an oath with the inhabitants of a village or a district or with a group of traders or other persons breaks it through greed should be banished from the kingdom by the king.&amp;rsquo; In Ap. Dh. S. I. 1. 1.2 and II. 4, 8. 13 the word&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 Sīmavivāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/22_sImavivAda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/22_sImavivAda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SĪMAVIVĀDA ( boundary disputes ).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is called kṣetra javivāda 897 (disputes relating to fields ) by Nārada XIV. 1, who defines it as &amp;rsquo; dispute with regard to land in which questions about dikes or embankments, the boundaries of fields, ploughed land and fallow land have to be decided.&amp;rsquo; Nārada&amp;rsquo;s idea appears to be that the word &amp;lsquo;simavivāda&amp;rsquo; in Manu is only illustrative and is a compendious way of mentioning disputes about land in general. According to Kāt. (732) there are six causes 89 of land disputes viz. claiming more land, claim that a person is entitled to less than he possesses, claim to a share, denial of a share, seizing possession when previously there was none, boundary. In all these cases boundaries have directly or indirectly to be settled and there fore all these are included under the topic of simāvivāda. A boundary dispute may relate to the boundaries of a distriot (janapada ), a village, a field and a house. Boundaries, acc. to Nār., may be of five kinds.899 They are described as follows: dvhanni is what is indicated by trees which are like a flag staff. Manu (VII. 246-247) prescribes that trees such as asvattha, the silk cotton, śāla, tāla (palmyra palm ), that have milky juice (like udumbara ) should be planted to indicate boundaries and also bamboo clumps, bushes, reeds &amp;amp;c. A matsyini (lit. having fish) boundary is provided by rivers flowing naturally and full of fish and tortoises or by tanks and reservoirs of water (Manu VIII. 248). A naidhāni boundary is one indicated by concealed signs (just as nidhāna i. e. treasure is concealed in the earth), such as pots filled with chaff, coal, bricks, bones and similar things that the earth does not corrode&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 Vākpāruṣya and Daṇḍapāruṣya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/23_vAkpAruShya_and_daNDapAruShya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/23_vAkpAruShya_and_daNDapAruShya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;VAKPĀRUSYA AND DANDAPARUSYA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;( Abuse and defamation; assault)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vakpāruṣya, dandapārusya, steya, strisangrahana, sāhasa are five titles out of 18 that are concerned with what may be called criminal matters or crimes in modern nomenclature. Vide under sāhasa below.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nār, XVIII. 1 defines vākpārusya as &amp;lsquo;abusive words that loudly proclaim censure of another&amp;rsquo;s country, caste, family and the like and that cause mental pain or offence to that man. Kat. (768) defines it as 92 consisting in making the sound &amp;lsquo;hum&amp;rsquo; (of defiance) before another or coughing before him, of imitating or uttering before another whatever is censurable according to popular notions. Nār. (XVIII. 2-3) says that abuse is of three kinds, niṣthura ( reproachful such as calling a man a fool or a rogue), atlila (obscene or insulting), tiura (mercilessly severe such as charging a man with such grave sins as brāhmana-murder or drinking liquor ) and that the punishment for each later one is more severe than for each preceding one. Examples of the abuse of country, caste and family are respectively &amp;rsquo;the Gaudas are quarrelsome&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;brāhmaṇas are extremely greedy&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;persons of the Viśyāmitra gotra commit cruel deeds&amp;rsquo;. Br. (S. B. E, vol, 33 p. 355 verses 2-4) divided vākpārusya into three kinds viz. lowest ( when the country, caste or family of a person is abused or sinfulness is ascribed without specifying any definite act), middling (speaking that the abuser will have sexual inter course with the mother or sister of the abused or ascribing the commission of upapātakas 923 or minor sins to the abused ), highest (charging him with taking forbidden food or drink or mercilessly exposing or ascribing the grave sins to a person ). Various fines are prescribed in the smrtis that depend upon the above distinctions and also on the castes of the abuser and the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 Steya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/24_Steya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/24_Steya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXIV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;STEYA (theft).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Rg. there is frequent mention of taskara, stena and tāyu. In Rg. VI. 28. 3 the sage 948 says &amp;lsquo;may the cows not disappear from us, may a thief not injure them! In Rg. VIII. 29. 6 it is said &amp;ldquo;Pūṣan guards the ways and knows of concealed treasures as a thief does! From Rg. X. 4.6 it appears that thieves were desperate and bound people with ropes and (from Rg. I. 191. 5 ) that thieves (taskaras ) appeared at night. Tāyu (thief) occurs in Rg. I. 50.2, IV. 38. 5, VI. 12. 5 and is an Indo-Iranian word. The word &amp;lsquo;stena&amp;rsquo;occurs in Rg. VI. 28.7 and means &amp;lsquo;one who is a cattle-lifter&amp;rsquo;. Rg. VIII. 67. 14 indicates that a stena was bound with ropes (when caught). In Rg. VII. 55. 3 the dog is asked to run after a stena and a taskara, the first being probably a thief (who secretly carries away pro perty) and the second a thief who openly carries it away. In the Vāj. 9484 S. XI. 79 (=Tai. S. IV. 1.10.2) we have the malimlu in addition to stena and laskaru. Atharvaveda IV, 3 contains charms against wolves, tigers and thieves (taskaras ).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 Strīsaṅgrahaṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/25_strIsangrahaNa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/25_strIsangrahaNa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;STRĪSANGRAHAŅA (Adultery or unlawful intercourse&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;with a woman ).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Mit. ( on Yāj. 11.976 283 ) states that sangrahana means the unlawful coming together of a man and a woman for sexual enjoyment. Bp. (S. B. E. 33 p. 365 verses 1-2) says that sinful 977 sangrahaṇa is of three kinds, viz. brought about by force, deceit or sensual passion. The first (which is rape ) occurs when intercourse is had in a secluded place against the will of a woman, or with a woman who is intoxicated or is disordered in mind or is under a mistake or when she raises a cry; the second occurs when a woman is brought to one&amp;rsquo;s house by some trick or pretence, an intoxicant (such as Dhatura) is administered to her or her mind is brought under control ( by chants or otherwise ) and sexual intercourse takes place; the third occurs when intercourse takes place by conveying (passion ) to each other by means of the eyes ( glances) or by employing a go-between and when the parties are drawn to each other by the temptation of beauty or of wealth. This last is again of three kinds acc. to Vyāsa and Br. ( S. B. E. 33 p. 365-66 verses 6-8 q. by Sm. C. II. p. 8) viz. trifling, middling and grave. The first is characterised by winking at a woman, smiling at her, sending a go-between, touch ing her ornaments or clothes; the second by the sending of flowers, unguents, fruits, incense, food, clothes, and indulging in private talks ; the third is characterised by lying on the same bed, dalliance, kissing and embraces. Stri sangrahaṇa by force (that is rape ) is really included under&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 Dyūtasamāhvaya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/26_dyUtasamAhvaya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/26_dyUtasamAhvaya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER xxvi&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;DYŪTASAMĀHVAYA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Gambling and prize-fighting ) Manu IX. 223, Nār. XIX. 1 and Bṛ. (8. B. E. 33 p. 385 verse 3) define dyūta (gambling ) as that sport which is carried on with inanimate objects such as dice, pieces of leather, ivory and the like and in which there is a stake, while sport carried on with animate objects such as cocks, pigeons, rams, buffaloes and wrestlers is called samāhvaya. The attitude of Manu towards gambling was uncompromising. Manu (IX, 221-222, 224-226) calls upon the king to suppress gambling and prize-fighting in his country as they cause the destruction of the State; he states that gambling is open theft and therefore the king should endeavour to put it down and that the king should punish with corporal punishment all those who engage in gambling or who induce or help others to gamble, and that he should banish gamblers from the city because gamblers residing in the country harags wellconducted subjects by their deceitful tricks. Manu IX. 227 ( = Udyogaparva 37. 19) states that in ancient times gambling engendered great enmities and therefore a wise man should not resort to it even for amusement or in jest. Kāt. (934) is to the same effect. Yāj. II. 203 and Kaut. III. 20 994 allowed gambling in a central place under State supervision as it led to the detection of thieves. Br. 995 ( S. B. E. 33 p. 385 verse 1) refers to this divergence of viows: * Gam bling that causes loss of truth, purity and wealth was forbid den by Manu, but others allowed it because it led to the detec tion of thieves, provided it was carried on in the presence of a master of the gambling hall and provided it yielded revenue to the king&amp;rsquo;. The person who was in charge of the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 Dāyabhāga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/27_dAyabhAga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/27_dAyabhAga/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXVII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;DAYABHAGA ( Partition of wealth )&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word dāya has been used even in the oldest period of the Vedic Literature. Rg. II. 32. 4 ( dadātu viram satadāyam ukthyam ) has already been quoted above (on p. 388). In Rg. X. 114, 10 ( śramasya dayam vibhajantyebhyah) the meaning of the word seems to be &amp;lsquo;a share&amp;rsquo; or &amp;rsquo; reward&amp;rsquo;. In the Tai. S. and the Brāhmanas the word dāya appears to be employed in the sense of paternal wealth&amp;rsquo; or simply &amp;lsquo;wealth&amp;rsquo;. In the story of Nābhā nediṣtha 1010 it is stated that Manu divided his daya among (for) his sons&amp;rsquo; (Tai. S. III 1. 9.4). That&amp;rsquo; dāya&amp;rsquo; here stands for &amp;rsquo; dhana&amp;rsquo; follows from another passage of the Tai. S. (II. 5.2.7) Therefore they distinguish (or establish) the eldest son by wealth&amp;rsquo;. In the Tāndya Brāhmaṇa 1011 16. 4. 3-5 also it is said Therefore whoever among ( a man&amp;rsquo;s ) sons secures the best or major portion of wealth as dāya, him they regard as the son who would be the lord of all&amp;rsquo;. Another word viz. riktha occurring in the sūtra and smrti literature is also employed in the Rgveda 1912 III. 31.2 &amp;rsquo;the son of the body does not give to his sister the ancestral wealth, but makes her the receptacle for the son of her husband&amp;rsquo;. The word dayāda (meaning a con sharer, one who takes a share ) occurs frequently in the Vedic Literature. In the Tai. S. VI. 5. 8. 2 1013 it is said &amp;ldquo;Therefore women being destitute of strength take no portion (of Soma )&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 Dattaka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/28_Dattaka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/28_Dattaka/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXVIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;DATTAKA ( adopted son)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;No branch of Hindu Law in modern times has been as fruitful in litigation as adoption. There are instances, where, fifty years after a point in the law of adoption was deemed to have been settled by a Full Bench decision, the Privy Council intervened and overruled the Full Bench decision in spite of its usual practice to follow the rule of stare decisis. The medieval digests are full of varying interpretations of the same smrti texts and the law of adoption differs from province to province according to the authoritative medieval works and modern case law. Voluminous works like those of Shastri Golapchandra Sarkar and of Mr. Kapur have been written on the subject of adoption in all its details. There is so much bewildering confusion and so much case law on the several aspects of adoption that it is only legislation that can resolve the tangled skein of the modern law of adoption. In this section an attempt will be made to present the law of adoption as evolved by the smrtis and medieval works and only some im portant cases bearing in various ways on the ancient law will be cited.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 Order of Succession After the Son</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/29_Order_of_Succession_After_the_Son/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/29_Order_of_Succession_After_the_Son/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ORDER OF SUCCESSION AFTER THE SON&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been stated above that daya is either apratibandha or sapratibandha and that sons, grandsons and great-grandsons take the first kind of daya. If a man has no son either aurasa or secondary (viz. the dattaka, the other kinds of sons being now forbidden or obsolete), then his property devolvos in a certain order. When a man dies sonless and is a member of a joint Hindu family then on the surviving coparceners the whole estate devolves except that after 1937 (by Act XVIII of 1937) his widow takes his place as to the joint family property. But if he dies separated and has male issue (from whom also he is separate ) then his male issue will succeed to him in a body viz. his son, grandson (son of a predeceased son) and great grandson (son of a predeceased son&amp;rsquo;s predeceased son) will together take his separate property per stirpes. From Manu IX. 137 ( which is the same as Vas. 17.5 and Viṣṇu Dh. 8. 15. 46 ) and 186 and Yaj. I 78 it follows that the son, grandson and great grandson equally confer great spiritual benefit and so are the principal group of heirs. According to the strict theory of the Mitakṣarā as stated above, son, grandson and great-grandson take by birth an interest even in property acquired by a man him self, but they have no power to prevent him from alienating it. If one or more out of a man&amp;rsquo;s sons, grand-sons or great-grandsons are separate from him then on his death his self-acquired property will first be taken by those sons, grandsons and great grandsons that are joint with him and if none of these is joint. with him, the separated son, grandson and great-grandson will Bucceed per stirpes to his estate, 1339&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 Strīdhana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/30_strIdhana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/30_strIdhana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;STRĪDHANA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Stridhana ( woman&amp;rsquo;s property ). This subject abounds with differing views on several topics that fall under it, as will be Been below.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The germs of the topic of stridhana can be traced to the Vedic Literature. As Sir Gooroodas Bannerjee remarks (in : Marriage and Stridhana&amp;rsquo; p. 370 ), &amp;rsquo; nowhere were proprietary rights of women recognized so early as in India; and in very few ancient systems of law have these rights been so largely conceded as in our own&amp;rsquo;. The wedding hymn in the Rgveda ( X 85 ) contains two verses 1483 ( 13 and 38) which indicate that gifts were sent to the bridegroom&amp;rsquo;s house with the bride, They are : &amp;rsquo;the bridal gifts of Sūryā that Savits sent off have gone forth; in the Agbās (Māgha constellation) are struck the kine and in the Arjunis ( Phalguni constellation) is carried ( the bridal gift ); for thee in the beginning they carried about Sūrya together with the bridal gifts &amp;amp;o.&amp;rsquo;. Sāyaṇa explains &amp;lsquo;vahatu&amp;rsquo; as &amp;lsquo;cows and other objects given for pleasing the girl to be married&amp;rsquo;, while Lanman ( Harvard O. series vol. VIII p. 753) renders it as &amp;lsquo;bridal car&amp;rsquo;. Sāyaṇa&amp;rsquo;s interpretation suits the context much better. In the Tai. S. VI. 2. 1. 1 we read, 1484 &amp;rsquo;the wife ( of the sacrificer) holds on ( to the cart), for the wife is the mistress of the household gear&amp;rsquo;. Manu IX. 11 uses the word &amp;lsquo;pāriṇahya&amp;rsquo; (household gear) and states that the wife should be entrusted among other matters with the supervision over it. Jaimini 1485, according to Sabara, refers to&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 Maintenance and other topics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/31_Maintenance_and_other_topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/2_vyavahAra/31_Maintenance_and_other_topics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXXI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;MAINTENANCE AND OTHER TOPICS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The subject of maintenance occupies an important place in modern Hindu Law. A brief statement of the law of the smrtis and the digests on this subject must be made here.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The liability to provide maintenance for certain persons arises under the ancient Hindu Law in either of two ways viz. (1) on account of bare relationship between the parties or (2) on the ground of the possession of property. A verse 1559 quoted by Medhātithi on Manu III. 7% and IV, 251, by the Mit. on Yāj. 1. 224 and II. 175 and occurring in some mss. of the Manusmrti after XI. 10 provides, &amp;lsquo;Manu declares that one must maintain one&amp;rsquo;s aged parents, a virtuous wife and a minor son by doing even a hundred bad acts.&amp;rsquo; From this verse it follows that irrespective of the possession of property there is a personal legal obligation on the father to maintain his minor son, on the husband to maintain his wife and on the son to maintain his aged parents. Baud. Dh. 8. (II. 2. 48) goes further and provides 1560 that a son is bound to maintain a mother even if she be patita. To the same effect are Āp. Dh. S. I. 10. 28. 9 and Vas. 13. 47.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
