<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मारीचकाश्यपः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/AyurvedaH/prakIrNam/mArIchakAshyapaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मारीचकाश्यपः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/AyurvedaH/prakIrNam/mArIchakAshyapaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>काश्यपसंहिता</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/AyurvedaH/prakIrNam/mArIchakAshyapaH/kAshyapasaMhitA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/AyurvedaH/prakIrNam/mArIchakAshyapaH/kAshyapasaMhitA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[काश्यपसंहिता&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=NDU4MjUwMDEwOTU4MTMz&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FOREWORD.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kāsyapa is one of the most ancient sages of India from whom the numerous body of Brahmans belonging to Kāsyapa Gotra trace their origin. His exact period, as that of most other Vedic men and institutions, is yet an unsolved mystery.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This valuable work, &amp;ldquo;Kāsyapa Samhita&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; was one of the manuscripts which came to the possession of H. H. Sri Yatiraja Swamy of Melkote years ago through the priest of the sacred temple there. Glancing through its contents, he was struck by its tantric and medical usefulness, and decided to make it available for the public. As the manuscript was worn with age and not in perfect condition, he looked about for other manuscript copies of the work, and after considerable search, found one in the Government Oriental Library, Madras, and one in the Theosophical Library at Adyar. By collating the three manuscripts a fairly satisfactory text was prepared, and through the kind offices of the then Muzroi Commissioner, Mr. Rajakarya-pravina P. G. D&amp;rsquo;Souza, the Government of Mysore were pleased to advance the cost of its publication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
