<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Ritual on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/ritual/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Ritual on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/ritual/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>saMskAra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/ritual/saMskAra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/ritual/saMskAra/</guid>
      <description>Only non-vedic rites of passage (saṃskāra-s) were permitted by most sūtrakāra-s. As a consequence of not studying the veda-s, there were śūdra-s acquired only one formal āśrama - gṛhastha. So, no upanayana according to most thinkers. However, the Baudhayana gṛhyasūtra (2.5.8 and 2.5.9) states the teacher to &amp;ldquo;[l]et him initiate [to school through Upanayana] a Brahmin in spring, a Kshatriya in summer, a Vaishya in autumn, a Sudra in the rainy season; or all of them in the spring.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>smRti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/ritual/smRti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/ritual/smRti/</guid>
      <description>A śūdra could hear the smṛti-s, itihāsa-s and the purāṇa-s through a brAhmaṇa reader. Some dharmaśāstra-s (eg. śūdrakamalākara) prohibit him from reading it himself. There was no prohibition whatsoever on studying and enjoying derivative poetic works in any language including saṃskṛta. There was no -explicit- prohibition of a śūdra reading the smṛti-s, itihāsa-s and the purāṇa-s himself, if he were capable of doing so. Several sources point to śūdra-s reading the smṛti-s, itihāsa-s and the purāṇa-s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vedic sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/ritual/vedic-sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/ritual/vedic-sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>Intro Śūdra-s could not consecrate vaidika fires and major perform vaidika sacrifices. Vedic (śrauta) fire sacrifice vs non-vedic fire sacrifice This distinction is crucial to this restriction, and many people are terribly confused about it. Some think that a regular “homa” fire sacrifice conducted in a home or in a temple is a “vedic” sacrifice. In fact, keeping the seasonal household sacrifices apart, major vedic yāga-s are conducted in a special temporary shelter which is burnt down at the end of the sacrifice.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
