<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;07 Mīmāṃsā and Dharmaśāstra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;07 Mīmāṃsā and Dharmaśāstra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>28 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/28_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/28_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECTION VII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXVIII MĪMĀŃSA AND DHARMASĀSTRA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;VI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Yājñavalkya-smrti provides that there are fourteen sources of vidyās (knowledge ) and of Dharma, 1863 viz. Purāṇa, Nyāya, Mimāṁsā, Dharmaśāstra, Angas (six) and the Vedas (four). A similar verse is quoted by some as Manu&amp;rsquo;s, but it is not found in the extant Manusmrti. It is therefore necessary to consider the origin and meaning of the word Mimāmsā, to set out the principal doctrines of that Sāstra, to mention the important rules of interpretation and the maxims of the Mimāṁsā in their application to topics of Dharmaśāstra and to refer to some of the important works of that Śāstra together with their approximate dates.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 Doctrines of Mīmāṃsā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/29_Doctrines_of_mImAMsA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/29_Doctrines_of_mImAMsA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some Fundamental Doctrines of Purvamimāmsā&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some of the characteristic fundamental doctrines of the Pūrvamimāṁsā will now be set out with some references and a few renarks as to some of them, the views of Prabhakara and his followers being also rarely referred to&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(1) Veda is eternal, self-existent, not composed by any author, human or divine, and is infallible. This is the core of the P, M, system. Vide P. M. S. 1. 1. 27-32 and Sabara on 1, 1. 5 (p. 53) and ślokavārtika (Vākyādhikarana, verges 1953 366 368). The argument briefly is; Veda is learnt at present and . was studied in tbe past also by students from teachers, that there is no evidence about the person who first composed it or who first studied it. If it be argued that such a reasoning may be put forward as regards the Mahabharata, the reply is that people know that Vyāsa is the author of it. Similarly, the passages in Smrtis and Purāṇas that Prajapati created the Veda are merely artharadas (laudatory ) not based on any evidence or perception and are meant only to convey the absolute autho ritativeness of the Veda. If the connection between word and . songe is eternal and not brought about by any person, the same reasoning holds good as to the Veda. This view is opposed to the view of the Naiyāyikas who hold that God is the author of the Voda or the interpretation of V. S. I. 1. 3 (Sastrayonitvāt) by Saṅkarācārya based on Br. Up. II, 4. 10. Manu I, 21 ( stating that Brahmā created from the words of the Voda the names and appropriate duties of all) seems to suggest that (according to&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 Mīmāṃsā Priniciples and Dharmaśāstra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/30_mImAMsA_Priniciples_and_dharmashAstra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/30_mImAMsA_Priniciples_and_dharmashAstra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXX On Mināmsā principles and rules of interpretation&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;in relation to Dharmasastra&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Pārvamimamas ayolyed a method of its own and a set of principles for the interpretation of Vedic texts. It is now time to get down and explain some of these principles and rulea and point out how they have been employed by Dharmasastra writers for solving their own difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Mimārsā principles and rules of interpretation fall into several groups. There are rules that are concerned only with the details of Vedic saorifices and their inter-relations. The most important rule in this field is this that only Vidhis proper ly so called have absolute authority and binding force, while what are called arthavādas have authority in so far only as they form one syntactical whole with the vidhis and as they are meant to praise the vidhis. (P. M. 8. I. 2.7). Vidhis and Arthavādas are not discussed consecutively, but they are scattered over the several chapters of the P. M. S. For example, arthavādas are first dealt with in I. %. 1-18 (the arthavadādhi karaña), but in many other places there is a discussion about arthavādas as in III. 4. 1-9, II, 4, 10, III, 4. 11, IV. 3. 1-3, VI. 7. 26–30, X. 8. 5, X. 8. 7 and 8.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
