<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1.1 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1.1 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Meaning of Dharma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/01_meaning_of_dharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/01_meaning_of_dharma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dharma&lt;/em&gt; is one of those Sanskrit words that defy all attempts at an exact rendering in English or any other tongue. That word has passed through several vicissitudes. The dictionaries set out various meanings of Dharma such as “ordinance, usage, duty, right, justice, morality, virtue, religion, good works, function or characteristic.&amp;quot; Dharma is also personified as a deity, as in the well-known verse. &amp;lsquo;Ādityacandrāvanilo’nalaśca&amp;hellip; dharmaśca jānāti narasya vṛttam&amp;rsquo;(Mahābhārata, Ādi., chap. 74.16) or as in Manusmṛti VIII. 16 &amp;lsquo;vṛṣo hi bhagavān Dharmaḥ&amp;rsquo; ( which also occurs in Śāntiparva 90.75 ). Vide H. of Dh. Vol. V (part 1) pp. 19-21 for the three words &amp;lsquo;vrata&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;dharman&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;ṛta&amp;rsquo; and JBBRAS. Vol. 29 (1954) pp. 1-28. In the hymns of the Ṛgveda the word appears to be used either as an adjective or a noun (in the form &lt;em&gt;dharman&lt;/em&gt;, generally neuter) and occurs at least about sixty times by itself (i.e. not preceded by a particle like &lt;em&gt;vi&lt;/em&gt; or some words like &lt;em&gt;satya&lt;/em&gt;), and about eighteen times in combination with a particle &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;vi&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo; and with the words &amp;lsquo;sva&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;satya&amp;rsquo; fifty-six times therein. It is very difficult to say what the exact meaning of the word &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; was in the most ancient period of the Vedic language. The word is clearly derived from root &lt;em&gt;dhṛ&lt;/em&gt; (to uphold, to support, to nourish). In a few passages, the word appears to be used in the sense of &amp;lsquo;upholder or supporter or sustainer&amp;rsquo; as in Ṛg. I. 187 .1&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and X. 92. 2&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In these two passages and in Ṛg. X. 21. 3&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the word &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; is clearly masculine. In all other cases, the word is either obviously in the neuter or presents a form which may be either masculine or neuter. In most cases the meaning of &lt;em&gt;dharman&lt;/em&gt; is &amp;lsquo;religious ordinances or rites&amp;rsquo; as in Ṛg. I. 22. 18, V. 26. 6, VIII. 43. 24, IX. 64. 1 &amp;amp;c. The refrain &amp;rsquo;tāni dharmāṇi prathamānyāsan&amp;rsquo; occurs in Ṛg. I. 164. 43 and 50, X. 90. 16. Similarly, we have the words &amp;lsquo;prathamā dharmā&amp;rsquo; (the primeval or first ordinances) in Ṛg. III. 17. 1, and X. 56. 3 and the words &amp;lsquo;sanatā dharmāṇi (ancient ordinances) occur in Ṛg. III. 3. 1. In some passages this sense of &amp;lsquo;religious rites&amp;rsquo; would not suit the context, e.g. in IV. 53. 3&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, V. 63. 7&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, VI. 70. 1&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, VII. 89. 5&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In these passages the meaning seems to be &amp;lsquo;fixed principles or rules of conduct&amp;rsquo;. In the Vājasaneyasaṃhitā the above senses of the word &lt;em&gt;dharman&lt;/em&gt; are found, and in II. 3 and V. 27 we have the words &amp;lsquo;dhruveṇa dharmaṇā.&amp;rsquo; In the same Saṃhitā the form &amp;lsquo;dharmaḥ&amp;rsquo; (from dharma) becomes frequent, e.g. X. 29, XX. 9. The word &amp;lsquo;Vidharman&amp;rsquo; is frequently employed in the Ṛgveda viz. in the instrumental (in X. 46. 6), in the dative (in VIII. 7.5), in the locative in eight passages (I. 164. 36, III. 2. 3, VI. 71. 1, IX. 4. 9, IX. 64. 9, and IX. 86. 29-30, IX. 100. 7) probably meaning &amp;lsquo;Vidhāraṇe&amp;rsquo; and in the vocative (in V. 17. 2). It is difficult to assign a definite meaning to this word in all these passages. But from several passages where the word &amp;lsquo;vidhartṛ&amp;rsquo; is employed (which is derived from the same root &lt;em&gt;dhṛ&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;em&gt;vi&lt;/em&gt;) it follows that vidharman probably means the same thing as vidhartṛ (in Ṛg. II. 28. 4, VII.7.5, VII. 41. 2, VII. 56. 24) applied to different gods. &amp;lsquo;Svadharman&amp;rsquo; as an epithet of Agni occurs in Ṛg. III. 21.2 and the word Satyadharman is applied to different gods alone viz. to Savitṛ, Viśvedevāh, Agni and to Mitra and Varuna in I. 12. 7, V. 51. 2, V. 63. 1, X. 34. 8, X. 121. 9, X. 139. 3. In the case of this word the meaning appears to be &amp;lsquo;whose regulations do not fail&amp;rsquo;. The Atharvaveda contains many of those verses of the Ṛgveda in which the word &lt;em&gt;dharman&lt;/em&gt; occurs, e.g. VI. 51. 3 (acittyā сet tava dharmā yuyopima), VII. 5. 1 (Yajñena yajñamayajanta), VII. 27. 5 (trīni padā vicakrame). In XI. 7. 17 the word &amp;lsquo;dharmaḥ&amp;rsquo; seems to be used in the sense of &amp;lsquo;merit acquired by the performance of religious rites&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&amp;rsquo; In the Aitareya-brāhmaṇa, the word &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; seems to be used in an abstract sense&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, viz. &amp;rsquo;the whole body of religious duties&amp;rsquo;. The Bṛhadāranyaka Up. (I. 14. 14) treats Dharma and Satya as equivalent. In the Chāndogya-upaniṣad&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (2.23) there is an important passage bearing on the meaning of the word &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;rsquo;there are three branches of &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt;, one is (constituted by) sacrifice, study and charity (i.e. tho stage of house-holder), the second (is constituted) by  austerities (i.e. the stage of being a hermit); the third is the &lt;em&gt;brahmacārin&lt;/em&gt; dwelling in the house of his teacher and making himself stay with the family of his teacher till the last; all these attain to the worlds of meritorious men; one who abides firmly in &lt;em&gt;brahman&lt;/em&gt; attains immortality.&amp;rsquo; It will be seen that in this passage the word &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo; stands for the peculiar duties of the &lt;em&gt;āśramas&lt;/em&gt;. As the word &lt;em&gt;brahmacāri&lt;/em&gt; itself occurs in this passage of the Chāndogya, it is clearly indicated that this brief passage means to refer only to the āśramas and their special duties. Prof. Hazra (in &amp;lsquo;Our Heritage&amp;rsquo; Vol. VII part I pp. 15-36, &amp;lsquo;on the early meaning and scope of the word dharma&amp;rsquo;) remarks (on p. 20) that the word Dharma as used in Vedic literature did not mean any act of vyavahāra is shown definitely by this Chāndogya passage (II. 23. 1). This is a strange (to put it mildly) argument as one passage from an Upaniṣad (relating to only one small aspect of dharma) cannot control the meaning of the word &amp;lsquo;Dharma&amp;rsquo; occurring hundreds of times in Saṃhitās, Brāhmaṇas and other Upaniṣads. Vide Bṛ. Up. I. 4. 14, II. 5. 11 for the wide conception of Dharma (to cite only a few Upaniṣad passages). The foregoing brief discussion establishes how the word &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; passed through several transitions of meaning and how ultimately its most prominent significance came to be &amp;rsquo;the privileges, duties and obligations of a man, his standard of conduct as a member of the Āryan community, as a member of one of the castes, as a person in a particular stage of life.&amp;rsquo; It is in this sense that the word seems to be used in the well-known exhortation to the pupil contained in the Taittirīya-upaniṣad (I. 11) &amp;lsquo;speak the truth, practise (your own) &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp;c.&amp;rsquo; It is in the same sense that the Bhagavadgītā uses the word &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; in the oft-quoted verse &amp;lsquo;svadharme nidhanaṁ śreyaḥ&amp;rsquo; The word is employed in this sense in the &lt;em&gt;dharmaśāstra&lt;/em&gt; literature. The Manusmṛti (1.2) tells us that the sages requested Manu to impart instruction in the &lt;em&gt;dharmas&lt;/em&gt; of all the &lt;em&gt;varṇas&lt;/em&gt;. The Yājñavalkya-smṛti (I. 1) employs it in the same sense. In the Tantra-vārtika&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; also we are told that all the dharmasūtras are concerned with imparting instruction in the &lt;em&gt;dharmas&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;varṇas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;āśramas&lt;/em&gt;. Medhātithi commenting on Manu says that the expounders of &lt;em&gt;smṛtis&lt;/em&gt; dilate upon &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; as five-fold, e.g. &lt;em&gt;varṇadharma&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;āśrama-dharma&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;varṇāśrama-dharma&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;naimittikadharma&lt;/em&gt; (such as prāyaścitta) and &lt;em&gt;guṇadharma&lt;/em&gt; (the duty of a crowned king, whether Kṣatriya or not, to protect).&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It may be noted that the Mitākṣarā on Yāj. I. 1 after mentioning the fivefold dharmas and illustrating them adds a sixth category viz. &amp;lsquo;Sādhāraṇa-dharma&amp;rsquo;— duties common to all men (including even cāṇḍālas) such as ahiṁsā and quotes a vedic passage in support &amp;rsquo;na hiṃsyāt sarvā bhūtāni&amp;rsquo;. Slightly differing enumerations of virtues to be cultivated by all men are found in Gaut. Dh. S. VIII. 23-25, Matsyapurāṇa 52. 8-10 (8 in all), Manu X. 63 (five), Yāj. I. 1. 22 (nine). Vide H. D. Vol. II pp. 10-11 and vol. V pp. 1023–24, 1637 and 1648. It may be noted that the Arthaśāstra of Kauṭilya (I. 3. 13) prescribes for all men ahiṁsā, satya, śauca, anasūyā, ānṛśaṃsya and kṣamā. It is in this sense that the word &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; will be taken in this work. Numerous topics are comprehended under the title dharmaśāstra, but in this work prominence will be given to works on &lt;em&gt;ācāra&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;vyavahāra&lt;/em&gt; (law and administration of justice).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Sources of Dharma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/02_sources_of_dharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/02_sources_of_dharma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sources of Dharma&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Gautamadharmasūtra&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; says &amp;rsquo;the Veda is the source of &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; and the tradition and practice of those that know it (the Veda).&amp;rsquo; So Āpastamba&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; says &amp;rsquo;the authority (for the &lt;em&gt;dharmas&lt;/em&gt;) is the consensus of those that know &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; and the Vedas.&amp;rsquo; Vide also the Vasiṣṭhadharmasūtra&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (I. 4-6). The Manusmṛti&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; lays down five different sources of &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; &amp;rsquo;the whole Veda is (the foremost) source of dharma and (next) the tradition and the practice of those that know it (the Veda); and further the usages of virtuous men and self-satisfaction.&amp;rsquo; Yājñavalkya&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; declares the sources in a similar strain &amp;rsquo;the Veda, traditional lore, the usages of good men, what is agreeable to one&amp;rsquo;s self and desire born of due deliberation&amp;ndash;this is traditionally recognised as the source of dharma.&amp;rsquo; These passages make it clear that the principal sources of &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; were conceived to be the Vedas, the Smṛtis, and customs. The Vedas do not contain positive precepts (&lt;em&gt;vidhis&lt;/em&gt;) on matters of &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; in a connected form; but they contain incidental references to various topics that fall under the domain of dharmaśāstra as conceived in later times. Such information to be gathered from the Vedic Literature is not quite as meagre as is commonly supposed. In another place&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I have brought together about fifty Vedic passages that shed a flood of light on marriage, the forms of marriage, the different kinds of sons, adoption of a son, partition, inheritance, &lt;em&gt;śrāddha&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;strīdhana&lt;/em&gt;. To take only a few examples. That brotherless maidens found it difficult to secure husbands is made clear by several Vedic passages. &amp;lsquo;Like (a woman) growing old in her parents&amp;rsquo; house, I pray to thee as Bhaga from the seat common to all&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;rsquo;. Vide also Ṛgveda I. 124. 7, IV. 5. 5 and Atharvaveda I. 17. 1 and Nirukta III. 4-5. These passages constitute the basis of the rules of the Dharmasūtras and the Yājñavalkyasmṛti against marrying a brotherless maiden&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This bar against marrying a brotherless maiden seems to have been due to the fear that such a girl might be an appointed daughter (&lt;em&gt;putrikā&lt;/em&gt;) and that a son born of such a girl would be affiliated to his mother&amp;rsquo;s father. This custom of &lt;em&gt;putrikā&lt;/em&gt; is an ancient one and is alluded to in the Ṛgveda, according to Yāska&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Ṛgveda X. 85 is a very interesting hymn as regards marriage ; verses from it are used even to this day in the marriage ritual&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It shows that in the remote Vedic age the marriage rite resembled in essence the Brāhma form as described in the Dharmasūtras and Manu.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But the purchase of a bride (i.e. what is called Āsura marriage in later literature) was not unknown in the Vedic age. A passage of the Maitrāyaṇīyasaṁhitā ((I. 10. 11) is referred to in the Vasiṣṭhadharmasūtra&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in this connection, viz. &amp;lsquo;she who being purchased by the husband&amp;rsquo;. The Gāndharva form is hinted at in the words&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;lsquo;when a bride is finelooking and well adorned, she seeks by herself her friend among men&amp;rsquo;. The importance of the &lt;em&gt;aurasa&lt;/em&gt; son was felt even in the remote Vedic ages. &amp;lsquo;Another (person) born of another&amp;rsquo;s loins, though very pleasing, should not be taken, should not be even thought of (as to be taken in adoption&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;)&amp;rsquo;. The Taittirīya-saṁhitā (VI. 3.10.5) propounds the well-known theory of the three debts&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The story of Śunaḥśepa in the Aitareya-brāhmaṇa (VII. 3) suggests that a son could be adopted even when there was an &lt;em&gt;aurasa&lt;/em&gt; son. The Taittirīya-saṁhitā (VII. 1. 8. 1) tells the story of Atri who gave an only son in adoption to Aurva. The Kṣetraja son of the Dharmasūtras is often referred to in the earliest Vedic literature. &amp;lsquo;What (sacrificer) invites you (Aśvins) in his house to a bed as a widow does a brother-in-law or a young damsel her lover&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The Taittirīya-saṁhitā makes it clear that a father could distribute his wealth among his sons during his own life-time, &amp;lsquo;Manu divided his property among his sons&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Another passage of the same &lt;em&gt;Saṁhitā&lt;/em&gt; seems to suggest that the eldest son took the whole of the father&amp;rsquo;s wealth &amp;rsquo;therefore people establish their eldest son with wealth&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Even in the Vedic ages the son excluded the daughter from inheritance &amp;lsquo;a son born of the body does not give the paternal wealth to (his) sister&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. A passage of the Taittirīya-saṁhitā is relied upon by ancient and modern writers on &lt;em&gt;dharmaśāstra&lt;/em&gt; for the exclusion of women in general from inheritance: &amp;rsquo;therefore women being destitute of strength take no portion and speak more weakly than even a low person&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The Ṛgveda eulogises the stage of studenthood and the Śatapathabrāhmaṇa speaks of the duties of the Brahmacārin such as not partaking of wine and offering every evening a &lt;em&gt;samidh&lt;/em&gt; to fire&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The Taittirīya-saṁhitā (VI. 2. 8.5) relates&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; how Indra consigned &lt;em&gt;Yatis&lt;/em&gt; to wolves (or dogs) and how Prajāpati prescribed a Prāyaścitta for him. The Śatapathabrāhmaṇa speaks of the king and the learned brāhmaṇa as the upholders of the sacred ordinances.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Taittirīyasaṁhitā says &amp;rsquo;therefore the Sūdra is not fit for sacrifice&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&amp;rsquo; The Aitareya Brāhmaṇa tells us that when a king or other worthy guest comes, people offer a bull or a cow&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:25&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The Śatapatha-brāhmaṇa speaks of Vedic study as &lt;em&gt;yajña&lt;/em&gt; and the Taittirīya-āraṇyaka&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; enumerates the five &lt;em&gt;yajñas&lt;/em&gt;, which are a prominent feature of the Manusmṛti. The Ṛgveda eulogises the gifts of a cow, horses, gold and clothes&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:27&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Another passage of the Ṛgveda&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (thou art like a &lt;em&gt;prapā&lt;/em&gt; in a desert) is relied upon by Śabara on Jaimini (I. 3. 2) and by Viśvarūpa on Yājñavalkya as ordaining the maintenance of &lt;em&gt;prapās&lt;/em&gt; (places where water is distributed to travellers). The Ṛgveda condemns the selfish man who only caters for himself&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Date of Dharmaśāstra works</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/03_date_of_dharmashAstra_works/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/03_date_of_dharmashAstra_works/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The important question is to find out when formal treatises on &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; began to be composed. It is not possible to give a definite answer to this question. The Nirukta (III. 4-5) shows that long before Yāska heated controversies had raged on various questions of inheritance, such as the exclusion of daughters by sons and the rights of the appointed daughter (putrikā). It is very likely that these discussions had found their way in formal works and were not merely confined to the meetings of the learned. The manner in which Yāska writes suggests that he is referring to works in which certain Vedic verses had been cited in support of particular doctrines about inheritance&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It is further a remarkable thing that in connection with the topic of inheritance Yāska quotes a verse, calls it a Śloka and distinguishes it from a ṛk.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This makes it probable that works dealing with topics of &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; existed either composed in the śloka metre or containing ślokas. Scholars like Būhler would say that the verses were part of the floating mass of mnemonic verses, the existence of which he postulates without very convincing or cogent arguments in his Introduction to the Manusmṛti (S. B. E. vol. 25 Intro.xc). If works dealing with topics of &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; existed before Yāska, a high antiquity will have to be predicated for them. The high antiquity of works on &lt;em&gt;dharmaśāstra&lt;/em&gt; follows from other weighty considerations. It will be seen later on that the extant &lt;em&gt;dharmasūtras&lt;/em&gt; of Gautama, Baudhāyana and Āpastamba certainly belong to the period between 600 to 300 B. C. Gautama&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; speaks of &lt;em&gt;dharmaśāstras&lt;/em&gt; and the word &lt;em&gt;dharmaśāstra&lt;/em&gt; occurs in Baudhāyana also (IV. 5.9). Baudhāyana speaks of a &lt;em&gt;dharmapāṭhaka&lt;/em&gt; (I. i. 9.). Besides, Gautama quotes in numerous places the views of others in the words &amp;lsquo;ityeke&amp;rsquo; (e.g. II. 15, II. 58, III. 1, IV. 21, VII. 23). He refers to Manu&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in one place and to &amp;lsquo;Ācāryas&amp;rsquo; in several places (III. 35, IV.18). Baudhāyana mentions by name several writers on dharma, viz. Aupajaṇghani, Kātya, Kāśyapa, Gautama, Maudgalya and Hārīta. Āpastamba also cites the views of numerous sages such as those of Eka, Kaṇva, Kautsa, Hārīta and others. There is a Vārtika which speaks of Dharmaśātra&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Jaimini speaks of the duties of a Śūdra as laid down in the dharmaśātra&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Patañjali shows that in his days &lt;em&gt;dharmasūtras&lt;/em&gt; existed and that their authority was very high, being next to the commandments of God&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. He quotes verses and dogmas that have their counterparts in the dharmasūtras&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The foregoing discussion establishes that works on the &lt;em&gt;dharmaśāstra&lt;/em&gt; existed prior to Yāska or at least prior to the period 600-300 B.C. and in the 2nd century B.C. they had attained a position of supreme authority in regulating the conduct of men.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 The Dharmasūtras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/04_the_dharmasUtras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/04_the_dharmasUtras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It seems that originally many, though not all, of the &lt;em&gt;dharmasūtras&lt;/em&gt; formed part of the Kalpasūtras and were studied in distinct &lt;em&gt;sūtrucaraṇas&lt;/em&gt;. Some of the extant dharmasūtras here and there show in unmistakable terms that they presuppose the Gṛhyasūtra of the &lt;em&gt;caraṇa&lt;/em&gt; to which they belong. Compare Āp. Dh. S. I. 1. 4. 16 with Āp. Gṛ. S. I. 12 and II. 5; and Baud. Dh. S. II. 8. 20 with Baud. Gṛ. S. II. 11. 42 (and other sūtras).&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Dharmasūtras belonging to all sūtracaraṇas have not come down to us. There is no dharmasūtra completing the Āśvalāyana Śrauta and Gṛhyasūtras; no Mānavadharmasūtra has yet come to light, though the Mānava Śrauta and Gṛhya sūtras are extant; in the same way we have the Śāṅkhāyana Śrauta and Gṛhya sūtras, but no Śāṅkhāyanadharmasūtra. It is only in the case of the Āpastamba, Hiraṇyakeśin and Baudhāyana Sūtracaraṇas that we have a complete &lt;em&gt;kalpa&lt;/em&gt; tradition with its three components of Śrauta, Gṛhya and Dharma sūtras. The Tantravārtika of Kumārila contains very interesting observations on this point. It tells us that Gautama (dharmasūtra) and Gobhila (gṛhyasūtra) were studied by the &lt;em&gt;Chandogas&lt;/em&gt; (Sāmavedins), Vasiṣṭha (dharmasūtra) by the Ṛgvedins, the dharmasūtra of Śaṅkha-Likhita by the followers of Vājasaneya-saṃhitā and the sūtras of Āpastamba and Baudhāyana by the followers of the Taittirīya Śākhā&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, The Tantravārtika (p. 179) establishes it as a &lt;em&gt;siddhānta&lt;/em&gt; (on Jaimini I. 3. 11) that all the &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;gṛhyra&lt;/em&gt; sūtras are authoritative for all Āryan people. From this it appears that, although originally all sūtracaraṇas might not have possessed dharmasūtras composed by the founder of the &lt;em&gt;caraṇa&lt;/em&gt; or ascribed to him, yet gradually certain dharmasūtras were specially taken over or appropriated by certain caraṇas. As the dharmasūlras were mostly concerned with rules about the conduct of men as members of the Āryan community and did not deal with ritual of any kind, all &lt;em&gt;dharmasūtras&lt;/em&gt; gradually became authoritative in all schools.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 The Dharmasūtra of Gautama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/05_the_dharmasUtra_of_gautama/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/05_the_dharmasUtra_of_gautama/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This has been printed several times (there is Dr. Stenzler&amp;rsquo;s edition of 1876, the Calcutta edition of 1876, the Ānanadāśrama edition with the commentary of Haradatta, and the Mysore Government edition with the bhāṣya of Maskarin; it was translated by Būhler in S. B. E., Vol. II. with an introduction). The Anandāśrama edition of 1910 which is incorrect in a few places (e. g. 21.7) has been used in this work. This dharmasūtra is, as we shall see, the oldest of those we have. The Gautama dharmasūtra was specially studied by followers of the Sāmaveda (see note 55 above). The commentary on the Caraṇavyūha tells us that Gautama was one of the nine sub-divisions of the Rāṇāyanīya school of the Sāmaveda. A teacher Gautama is mentioned frequently in the Lāṭyāyanaśrautasūtra (e.g. I. 3. 3 and I. 4. 17) and in the Drāhyāyanaśrauta (e.g. I. 4. 17, IX. 3. 15) of the Sāmaveda. The Gobhilagṛhya (III. 10. 6) which belongs to the Sāmaveda cites Gautama as an authority. Therefore it is not improbable that a complete Gautamasūtra embodying Śrauta, Gṛhya and Dharma doctrines once existed. There are other indications pointing to the close connection of the Gautamadharmasūtra with the Sāmaveda. Chapter 26 of the dharmasūtra about &lt;em&gt;Kṛcchra&lt;/em&gt; penance is the same, almost word for word, as the Sāmavidhāna&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Brāhmaṇa (I. 2, Burnell&amp;rsquo;s ed.).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 The Baudhāyana Dharmasūtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/06_the_baudhAyana_dharmasUtra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/06_the_baudhAyana_dharmasUtra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;06 The Baudhāyana Dharmasūtra&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This has been edited several times (text by Dr. Hultzsch at Leipzig in 1884, text in the Ānandāśrama collection of smṛtis and in the Mysore Government Oriental Series in 1907 with the commentary of Govindasvāmin; translated in S. B. E., Vol. 14, with an Introduction). The Mysore edition has been used in this work. Baudhāyana is a teacher of the Kṛṣṇayajurveda. A complete set of the Baudhāyanasūtras has not yet been recovered and has not been as carefully preserved as the sūtras of Āpastamba and Hiraṇyakeśin. Dr. Burnell arranges Baudhāyana&amp;rsquo;s sūtras into six sūtras, the Śrautasūtra in 19 praśnas (probably); Karmāntasūtra in 20 adhyāyas; Dvaidhasūtra in four praśnas; Gṛhyasūtra in four praśnas; Dharmasūtra in four praśnas; Śulvasūtra in three adhyāyas. The commentators offer no indication as to the place originally assigned to the &lt;em&gt;gṛhya&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;śulva&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;sūtras&lt;/em&gt; in the whole collection. Dr. Caland in his mono graph (A.D. 1903) &amp;lsquo;Uber das Rituelle sūtra des Baudhāyana&amp;rsquo; gives on p. 12 the contents of the Baudhāyanasūtra as follow: Praśnas I-XXI Śrauta, XXII-XXV Dvaidha, XXVI XVIII Karmānta; XXIX-XXXI Prāyaścitta; XXXII Śulvasūtra; XXXIII-XXXV Gṛhyasūtra, XXXVI Gṛhyaprāyaścitta; XXXVII Gṛhyaparibhāsā; XXXVIII-XLI Gṛhyapariśiṣṭa; XLII-XLIV Pitṛmedha; XLV Pravara; XLVI-XLIX Dharma. Dr. Caland edited nine &lt;em&gt;praśnas&lt;/em&gt; of the Śrautasūtra for the B. I. Series (A. D. 1904). Dr. R. Shamsastri published for the Mysore University (in 1920) the Baudhāyanagṛhyasūtra with &lt;em&gt;paribhāṣā&lt;/em&gt;, gṛhyaśesa, Pitṛmedhasūtra. The Gṛhyasūtra cites the view of Baudhāyana himself (1.7). The Baudhāyana-dharma refers to the Gṛhya and presuppose it in several places (vide note 54). In the Baudhāyanagṛhya (III. 9. 6) we have a reference to &lt;em&gt;padakāra&lt;/em&gt; Ātreya, Vṛttikāra Kauṇḍinya, Pravacanakāra Kāṇva Bodhāyana, and Sūtrakāra Āpastamba.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A similar passsage occurs in the Bhāradvāja Gṛhyasūtra. In the Baudhāyana-dharma-sūtra (II. 5.27 Ṛṣitarpaṇa) we have Kāṇva Bodhāyana, Āpastamba sūtrakāra and Satyāṣāḍha Hiraṇyakeśin one after another. These references show that Kāṇva Bodhāyana was an ancient sage when the Baudhāyana-dharmasūtra was written and that he could not have been the author of the gṛhya or the dharmasūtras of Baudhāyana. Baudhāyana may have been a descendant of this Kāṇva Bodhāyana. This surmise is supported by Govindasvāmin who explains Baudhāyana occurring in Baudhāyanadharinasūtra 1. 3. 13 as Kāṇvāyana. In the dharmasūtra Baudhāyana is himself cited as an authority several times (e.g. I. 4. 15 and 24, III. 5. 8, III. 6. 20). In all these places the Mysore edition reads Bodhāyana, while the Ānandāśrama reads Baudhāyana. In one or two places he is styled &amp;lsquo;bhagavān (III. 6. 20). Several explanations are offered by the commentator Govindasvāmin (on I. 3. 13). He says that it is the practice of the Ācāryas to refer to themselves in the third person (as Medhātithi says on Manu. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) or that the author of the dharmasūtra is a pupil of Baudhāyana as the Manusmṛti is promulgated by Bhṛgu, the pupil of Manu, or there was some other Baudhāyana whose works have not come down to us.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Dharmasūtra of Āpastamba</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/07_dharmasUtra_of_Apastamba/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/07_dharmasUtra_of_Apastamba/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;07 Dharmasūtra of Āpastamba&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dharmasutra of Āpastamba. This has been edited several times (viz. by Būhler in the Boinbay Sanskrit Series with large extracts from Haradatta&amp;rsquo;s commentary called Ujjvalā and also at Kumbhakonam with the complete commentary of Haradatta and translated by Būhler with an introduction in S. B. E. vol. II). The Apastan bakalpasūtra of the Taittiriya Sākhā of the black Yajurveda is divided into 30 pruśnas. According to Būhler, the first 24 praśnas contain the treatment of Srauta sacrifices; the 25th contains paribhūṣās, pravarakhanda, and Hautraka prayers to be recited by Hotr priests ; 26th and 27th praśnas constitute the Gșhyasūtra, the 28th and 29th Dharmasūtra and the 30th praśna is Sulvasūtra. Būhler seems to be slightly inaccurate here. According to Caundappa, who commented on the Āpastambiya sūtras in the 14th century, the Āpastambiyaman trapātha forms the 25th and 26th praśnas of the Kalpasūtra and the Gșhyasūtra forms 27th prasna.80 The Srauta-sūtra of 80 पंचविशेष षइविंशे गृहमन्त्राः प्रपञ्चिताः । प्रश्नेथ सप्तर्विशे स्याब्रह्मतन्त्रविधिक्रमाती&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Dr. Winternitz&amp;rsquo;s edition of Āp. Maptrapātha p. IX ). The editor farthek states (p. IX n. 2) that Paribhāṣās form part of the 24th praśn a nu not of the 25th, as Būhler says.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Hiraṇyakeśi-Dharmasūtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/08_hiraNyakeshi-dharmasUtra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/08_hiraNyakeshi-dharmasUtra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;08 Hiraṇyakeśi-Dharmasūtra&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Hiraṇyakeśi-dharmasūtra forms the 26th and 27th &lt;em&gt;praśnas&lt;/em&gt; of the Hiraṇyakeśi-kalpa. The Śrauta-sūtra has been published by the Ānandāśrama Press (Poona). The Hiraṇyakeśi-gṛhya-sūtra was edited with extracts from the commentary of Mātṛdatta by Dr. Kirsto (Vienna, 1889). The Gṛhya forms the 19th and 20th &lt;em&gt;praśnas&lt;/em&gt; of the Kalpa, each &lt;em&gt;praśna&lt;/em&gt; being divided into eight paṭalas. The Śrauta-sūtra is largely based on the Śrauta-sūtra of Āpastamba Tho Gṛhya-sūtra is indebted to the Gṛhya-sūtra of Bhāradvāja. The Dharmasūtra of Hiraṇyakeśin can hardly be called an independent work. Hundreds of sūtras are borrowed word for word from the Āpastamba Dharmasūtra. The Dharmasūtra of Hiraṇyakeśin is therefore the oldest voucher for the authenticity of Āpastamba&amp;rsquo;s text and is very valuable for checking the latter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 Vasiṣṭha-dharmasūtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/09_vasiShTha-dharmasUtra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/09_vasiShTha-dharmasUtra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;09 Vasiṣṭha-dharmasūtra&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vasistha-dharmasutra. This dlurmusutra has been printed several times. The collec tion of Jivanada (part II, pp. 456-496 ) contains only 20 chapters and a portion of the 21st and so does the collection of Mr. M. N. Dutt (Calcutta 1908). The Anandāśrama collection of sinītis ( 1905, pp. 187-231 ) and the edition of Dr. Fūhrer in the B. S. series (1916) contain thirty chapters. According to Dr. Jolly (R. u 8, p. 6 ) some mss. give only six or ten chapters, The Vasisthadharmasūtra with the commentary called Vidvan modini was printed at Benares. In the following Dr. Fūhrer&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;edition has been used.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Viṣṇudharmasūtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/10_viShNudharmasUtra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/10_viShNudharmasUtra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Viṣṇudharmasutra. The Viṣṇudharmasūtra has been printed several times in India, viz. by Jivananda in his Dharmasastrasangraha (1876 part I pp. 70-176 ) by the Bengal Asiatic Society (1881, ed. by Dr. Jolly with extracts from the commentary Vaijayanti ), by M. N. Dutt (Dharmaśāstra texts, vol. II pp. 541-666, Calcutta, 1909) and translated by Dr. Jolly (in the S. B. E. vol. VII with an Introduction). In the present work Dr. Jolly&amp;rsquo;s edition has been used. The sūtra contāins one hundred chapters. Though the number of chapters is so large, the sūtra is not very extensive. There are several chapters such as 40, 42 and 76 that contain only one sūtra and one verse. The first chapter and the last two are entirely in verse; the remaining chapters are in mixed prose and verse, the versified portion being generally at the end of each chapter. As pointed out by the Vaijayanti the sūtra is in close relation to one of the oldest schools of the Yajurveda, viz. Katha. It also stands in a peculiar relation to the extant Manusmṛti. According to the Caranavyūha, Kathmand&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1917&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 The Dharmasūtra of Hārīta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/11_the_dharmasUtra_of_hArIta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/11_the_dharmasUtra_of_hArIta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;11 The Dharmasūtra of Hārīta&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Dharmasutra of Harita That Hārīta was an ancient sūtrakāra on dharma is quite patent from the fact that the dhurmasitras of Baudhā. yana, Apastamba and Vasiṣtha quote him as an authority.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;118 6.g. para 637 : JUTE potrafavaraanageTAAT aftage: fouse&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;वाचीति । ( Viṣṇu&amp;rsquo;s sutra seems to have been बीजग्रहणानुविधायमर्श&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;TERITE); para 719 375 HTEN: ( on fai&amp;rsquo;s FLE &amp;lsquo;foraya T na garnit pe ) que sentiafafa; pura 736 347 prae: भिनोदराणामिति निर्धारणे षष्ठी ( on विष्णु&amp;rsquo;सूत्र ‘भिन्नोदराणां संसृष्टिनी&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 The Dharmasūtra of Saṅkha-Likhita</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/12_the_dharmasUtra_of_sankha-likhita/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/12_the_dharmasUtra_of_sankha-likhita/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;12 The Dharmasūtra of Saṅkha-Likhita&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the Tantravārtika we learn (note 55 above) that the Dharmasūtra of Śaṅkha-Likhita was specially studied by the Vājasaneyins (the followers of the white Yajurveda ). The Tantravārtika also quotes a few words from that Dharmaśūtra which constitute an Anuṣṭubh pāda&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The Mahābhārata (in Śāntiparvan, chap. 23. 18-43 ) narrates the story of the two brothers, Śaṅkha and Likhita, who resided in separate dwellings surrounded by trees. Once Likhita came to the āśrama (hermitage ) of Śaṅkha in his absence. He took some ripe fruits from some of the trees of Śaṅkha’s āśrama and ate them. While he was eating, Śaṅkha came and asked him where he got the fruits. Likhita smiled and told his brother that he took them from his trees. Then Śaṅkha got angry and told his brother that he was guilty of theft and asked him to go to the king Sudyumna for punishment. Likhita went to the king who would not punish him as he was a man of pure character and learned ; when he persisted the king ordered his hands to be cut off. His arms were restored when he plunged into the river Bāhudā. In Santi ( 130.29 ) &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; it is said &amp;lsquo;It is not possible to live if one adopts Saṅkhalikhita mode of life, particularly when one intends to secure the protection of the subjects.&amp;rsquo; In another place (Santiparvan 132. 15-16 ) it is said &amp;lsquo;Some hold that conduct or practice is the best characteristic of dharma, others to whom Saṅkha-Likhita are dear do not like them.&amp;rsquo; Vide Sabhāparva 7. 11 where among the holy sages who graced Iudra&amp;rsquo;s sabhii are included Saijkha and Likhita.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 Mānavadharmasūtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/13_mAnavadharmasUtra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/13_mAnavadharmasUtra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Mānavadharmasutra-Did it exist?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;143&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Mānavadharmasutra-Did it exist ? Following the orthodox view of Western Sanskrit scho lars that most of the dharinasūtras are older than almost all, if not all, the metrical smrtis, I gave the first place of honour to the dharmasutras of Gautama and others. But my own views differ to a great exteut from those of the orthodox school of Sanskritists represented by Max Mūller and Būhler. It is high time to state here my views about the existence of a Mānava-dharma-sūtra supposed to be the original of our extant Manu.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some western scholars, particularly Max Mūller and Weber, started the ingenious theory that the extant Manu. smrti was a recast or remodelling of an ancient Mānavadhar masūtra. Max Mūller went so far as to enunciate the bold generalisation “There can be no doubt, however, that all the genuine dharma-sāstras which we possess now, are without any exception, nothing but more modern texts of earlier sūtra works on kuladharmas belonging originally to certain Vedic caranas&amp;quot; (H. A. S. L. pp. 134-135). For this sweeping gene ralisation there were very few data when it was made, as is admitted by Bihler. This theory of Max Mūller was as hasty, as unfounded and as uncritical as several other theo. ries of his such as that about the renaissance of Sanskrit Lite rature in the early centuries of the Christian era, about the absence of the art of writing in India before Pānini and about the uniform employment of the sloka for literary purposes in his so-called sūtra period and earlier. Western Scholars had to give up such theories before the stern logic of facts, but they have tenaciously clung to the theory about the Manu smrti being a recast of the Mānavadharmasūtra. One of the main planks of Max Mūller&amp;rsquo;s edifice was the now exploded theory about the non-employment of the anustubh during the sūtra period ( which he tentatively placed between 600 B. C.-200 B. C. ) for continuous composition. In spite of the fact that one of the main planks has totally collapsed Būhler makes strenuous efforts to rehabilitate Max Mūller&amp;rsquo;s theory by additional a priori arguments (S. B. E. vol. 25, PPA XVIII-XXIII and xxxI-XXXIX). The main points brought forward by Būhler are:-(I) The Vasistha Dh. S. (IV. 5 contains four sūtras, the first of which is The Mānava sayan that one may kill an animal only in honouring the Mones, gode&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 The Arthaśāstra of Kauṭilya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/14_the_arthashAstra_of_kauTilya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/14_the_arthashAstra_of_kauTilya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;14 The Arthaśāstra of Kauṭilya&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Arthasastra of Kautilya&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are three words in ancient Sanskrit Literature that are used very often in the same sepse viz. Arthasastra, Dandaniti and Rajasāstra or Rājaniti or Rājanitisāstra or simply Nitisāstra. The Mahābhārata descants on Rāja dharma in several parvans, as in Sabhā 5 ( the chapter called kaccit-praśna), Vanaparva 150, Uddyoga (chap. 33-34). In Sabbā 5 one hundred verses occur on Rājaniti; for example, ( verse 41 refers to 18 tirthas (state dignitaries) tested by spies (as in Kaut. I. 12. 20), verse 47 refers to amātyas beyond the reach of upadhās (cf. Kauṭ. I. 10. 1ff). The Santiparva devotes more than 100 chapters to Rāja dharma from chap. 56. Sānti, chap. 58 (1-4) names160s the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 Vaikhānasa-dharma-praśna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/15_vaikhAnasa-dharma-prashna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/15_vaikhAnasa-dharma-prashna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;15 Vaikhānasa-dharma-praśna&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vaikhānasa-dharn-prasna&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;257&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vaikhānasa-dharma-prasna The work has been published in the Trivandrum Sanskrit Series by Pandit T. Gunapati Sastri (1913) and also edited by Dr. Caland in B. I. Series (1927) and translated into English ( 1929 ) with a learned Introiluction.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Mahadeva in his commentary called Vaijayanti ( Anandā srama ed.) on the Satyasādha Franta sūtra speaks of six Srauta Sutras of the Black Yajurveda viz. Baudhāyana, Bharadvāja , Āpastamba, Hiranyakeśin, Vādhūla and Vaikhā nasa, and frequently cites passages from the Vaikhānasa srautasūtra. In the Carana vyūlia of Saunaka, Vādhūla and Vaikhanasa are not mentioned. But that Vaikhānasa was a very ancient writer follows from the references contained in the ancient dharma works. In Gautaina the word Vaikha nasa&amp;rsquo; occurs (Dh. S. III. 2) as the name for the order of forest hermits ( Vivaprastha ) and in another Sūtra (III. 26 ) he lays down that fire was to be consecrated according to the Srāmaṇaka,227 which latter is explained by Haradatta as Vaiklānasa Sāstra. Baudhayana (Dh. S. II. 6. 17 ) has the same Sūtra228 and defines a Vaikhanaga as one who follows the rules of conduct laid down in Viikhānasa sastra (Dh. S. II. 6. 16 ). The Vasistha Dh. S. (9. 10 ) also has the same sūtra as Gautama (Dh. S. III. 26). The Manusmrti (VI. 21) speaks of the Vānajrastha as one who abiiles by the views of Vaikhānasa ( Vaikhānasamate sthital ). Gau. III. 25-34 and Vas. IX. 1-11 deal with Vaikhannsa. Printed Gaut. III. 26 reads &amp;lsquo;śravanakenāgnimñdhāya&amp;rsquo; while Vas. IX. 10 hus&amp;rsquo; sra manakenāgnimūdhāyāhitāgnili syāt&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 Atri</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/16_atri/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/16_atri/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Atri That Atri was an ancient writer on hurma follows from &amp;amp; reference to him in Manu (III. 16 ) as holding the view that a crijati taking as wife a sūdra woman became fallen (patita). In the Deccan College collection there are several mss. ( Nos. 185-187 of A 1881-82 ) of the Atreyadharmaśāstra in nine adhyayas. They trent of gifts, prayers (japya ) and tupus by which men are free from all sins. Some of the chapters are in mixed prose and verse. The first three chapters are entirely in verse and some of the verses (such as ekāksaram param brabma) occur in the Manusmști. The fourth opens with a long sūtra, which, in style, resembles later bbāsyas and com mentaries, 320 The 5th also is in verse and contains several verses found in Viisistha ( Dh. S. 28. 1, 4, 6). The sixth speaks of the specially boly hymns and verses of the Veda. Some of the verses here are the same as Vasistha ( 28. 10–11). &amp;ldquo;The seventh refers to secret prayascittas and the very first sūtra after the opening words sj.eaks of several non-Aryan tribes 230 such as the Sakas, Yavanas, kambhojus, Balbikas, Khusus, Vangus aud Pārasu ( Persians ? ) &amp;amp;c. It is to be noted that the saine sutra ( with slight variations ) is quoted as Atri&amp;rsquo;s by Apariirka (on Ynj. III. 266 p. 1123). The 7th aud 8th chapters are in inixed prose and verse. The 9th is in verse and speaks of Yoya and its unyus. It refers to the fact that Sisupūlu, son of Damaghosa, because in his hatred of Govinda he always thought of the latter, went to heaven. The same sutra work is noticed in I. O. Cat., pp. 380-81, Nos. 1305 and 1306.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;229 34zitof 1791 art thê145CP21Tarand (?) waarat ane 427&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 Uśanas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/17_ushanas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/17_ushanas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Usanas Kāvya Uśanas is an ancient sage in the Rgveda ; vide æg. I. 83. 5, where Kavya Uśanas is said to have been an helper of Indra and brought out the cows (carried away and concealed by the Panis). In Rg. VIII. 23. 17 that sage is said to have established Agni for Manu and in Rg IX. 87. 3 Uśanas is called a ṛsi and vipra and one who knew the hidden place where cows were concealed.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That Uśanas wrote a work on politics follows from seve ral circumstances. The Kauṭiliya quotes the Auśanasāļı seven times. It is almost certainly referring to a work. That work contained directions on the administration of justice also, as Kautilya speaks of Auśanasa method of partition (in allowing a tenth additional share to the eldest son, III. 6 ), as Auśana sāḥ prescribed fines in cases where witnesses proved stupid &amp;amp;c. (III. 11,44 ). The Mahābhārata, Santiparva 236 (chap. 56,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 Kaṇva and Kāṇva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/18_kaNva_and_kANva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/18_kaNva_and_kANva/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Karva and Kānva&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;273&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Kanya and Kānva From the Ap. Dh. S. it appears that Kanva and Kāụva were two distinct writers on dharma. In I. 6. 19. 2 Āpastamba starts the question as to the persons, food at whose house was permitted. He states various views on that point and says that Kanya was of opinion that food may be taken at anybody&amp;rsquo;s house provided the latter offered it with a request (I. 6. 19. 3) and that the opinion of Eka, Kuṇika, Kānva, Kutsa and Puskarasāili (1. 6. 19. 7) was that only that food that was offered by a pure and religious man should be partaken. In another place ( L. 10. 28. 1) Apastambé gives it as the opinion of Kautsa, Hārīta, Kajıva and Puskara sādi that a man became a thief if in any case whatever he appropriates another&amp;rsquo;s belongings. The Kumbhakonam edition of Pandit Halasyanatha reads Kāṇva for Kanva.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kanva is quoted a few times in the Smyticandrika on Ahnika ( daily duties ) and śrāddha. One of these quotations is in prose ( I. p. 97 ).252 Haradatta in his commentary on Gautama cites verses of Kanva in several places (e. g. Guu tama Dh. S, 21. 3, 23. 3 and 11 ).253 The first verse bears &amp;amp; close resemblance to Manu XI. 180 and Baud. Dh. S. II. 1. 62. Kanva is quoted in the Acaramayukha and the Srāddha mayūkha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 Kaśyapa and Kāśyapa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/19_kashyapa_and_kAshyapa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/19_kashyapa_and_kAshyapa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Kasyapa and Kasyapa Baudhayana ( Dh. S. I. 11. 20) cites a verse which con tains the view of Kaśyapa that a woman who is bought can. not be a patnī and that she is not authorised to take part in religious ( daiva ) rites or rites for the Manes.254 This verse is ascribed to Katyayana in the Smrticandrika ( I. p. 87 ). The Vanaparva quotes gāthcs of Kāśyapa on forbearance ( 29. 35-40). Whether Kaśyapa and Kāśyapa are two different writers of dharmasūtras it is rather difficult to say. Probably they are identical. It appears that the dharmasūtra of Kāśyapa comprised all the usual topics of dharmasūtras, such as daily duties, sraddha, asauca, prayascitta. This sutra has been quoted by all eminent writers from Viśvarūpa down wards. Viśvarāpa quotes Kasyapa (in prose ) on the priya scitta for contact with candila 8866 and for killing a cow when the sinner is a brāhmana or a member of another caste. 288 The Mit. (on Yaj. III. 23) quotes a prose passage from Kāsyapa on freedom from impurity on death of infants.257 The quotations in the Smṛticandrikā on āhnika and traddha are all in verse. Haradatta on Gautama (22. 18 ) quotes a sūtra on the prāyaścitta for govadhu, 258 which is also quoted by Viśvarūpa. Haradatta (on Gaut. 23. 26 ) quotes a very long sūtra on the prāyascittu for eating several things and doing&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;254 क्रीता द्रव्येण या नारी सा न पत्नी विधीयते ।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 Gārgya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/20_gArgya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/20_gArgya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Gārgya Viśvarūpa (on Yaj. I. 4-5) quotes a verse of Vṛddha Yājñavalkya in which Gārgya is enumerated among the expo unders of Dharma ( dharmavaktūraḥ). He quotes two sūtras, one from Gārgya ( on Yāj. I. 72260 ) and the other from Vṭddha Gārgya361 (on Yāj. I. 195). Therefore it seems that a sutra work of Gārgya on dharma did exist. The Mit. (e. g. on Yāj. III. 326 ), Aparārka and the Sinșticandrika quote several verses of Gārgya on õhnika, śrāddha and prāyascitta. Parā sara (I. 13) mentious Gārgya among writers on dharma. Apa rārka contains (pp. 124, 190, 368, 544 ) verses from Gārgya on topics of dharina. It seeins that the two writers are identical. Aparārka also quotes several verses from Gārgya of astrono mical import (e. g. p. 5:17 on the nomenclature of the months as Caitiu in connection with the signs of the zodiac). This was probably an independent work. Fragments of a Gārgi samhiti on astronomy and astrology have been recovered and it contains valuable historical information ( vide Kern&amp;rsquo;s pre face. to Br̥hat-samhitā pp. 33-40 and Mr. Jayasval in JBORS. vol. 14, p. 397 (F). A Jyotir-Gārgya and a Brhad-Gārgya are quoted in the Smṛticandrikā. The Nityācārapradipa (p. 20, B.I.S.) mentions Garga and Gārgya separately as smștikāras.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;280 gfaar: fra FUIFFT Wararaarent al zer अनेकोद्धार्ये काष्टशिले भूमिसमे। .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 Cyavana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/21_chyavana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/21_chyavana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cyavana&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;277&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Anuśnsanaparva ( 18.38 ) states that Garga acquired on the banks of the Sarasvati astronomy with its 64 angas. In the same parure it is said that vrddha-Gārgya inquired about vrgotsarga ( 125. 77 ff). Salya parva ( 37. 14-15 ) narra tes that oli Garya by his tapis acquired on the sacred Sara svatī knowledge of Kāla, movements of the planets, of evil and good ut pātas and that the place is therefore called Gargasrotas. This astronomer Garva is probably different from the Dharma sāstra writer Garga. Vide H. of Dh. Vol. V. pp. 591-92, 741 42, 765 for Garga, the astronomer. Viśvarūpa on Yāj: 1. 25 quotes a verse of Gārgya on the proper times for morning Sundhyā and evening Sandhya and a prose passage of Vrddha Gārgya on Yij. I. 195 (p. 136 ).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 Jātūkarṇya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/22_jAtUkarNya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/22_jAtUkarNya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Jatukarnya&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Viśvarūpa (on Yāj. I. 4-5) quotes a verse of Vrudha Yājñavalkya in which Jātukarya is mentioned as an expounder of dharma.389 The name is variouly written as Jātūkarni or Jātākarnya or as Jatukarna. The Smyticandrikā quotes a passage from Angiras in which Jātūkarnya is enumerated among writers of Upasmrtis. Viśvarūpa quotes prose passages from Jātūkarnya a number of times.363 On Yāj. I. 1, he gives a sūtra about “pratilomas&amp;quot;; on Yāj. I. 2 there is &amp;amp; sūtra saying that a pupil should not all of a sudden put a question to his teacher in an assembly of people, on Yūj. I. 29 about a Ksatriya and Vaisya wearing an Upavita of hemp and wool when initiated for sacrifice, on Yāj. I. 37 as to the age when a Brāhmana became a vrūtya, about the prohibition of marrying another wife of a diferent caste when one has already married a savarṇa wife (on Yaj. I. 79 ), about the time for sraddhas (on Yaj. I. 215 ). These quota tions show that Jātukarṇya composed id sutra work on ācāra and srāddha, which was comparatively uncient. The quotations of Jātūkurnya in Mitāksari, Haradatta, A parārka,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 Devala</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/23_devala/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/23_devala/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Devala The name Devala as that of a sage frequently occurs in the Mahābhārata and is closely connected with Asita. Vide Sabhāparva 59. 9-11, Salya 50 and Sāntiparva 230. In Subhā ( 72. 5) it is stated that Devala declared that a man has three lights viz. son, actions and correct knowledge. In the Gita also (in X. 13 ) Arjuna says all the sages, the Devasși Nārada, Asita, Devala and Vyāsu speak of you as done in X. 12&amp;rsquo;. Sarkaricñrya in his bhāsya on Vedānti sutra 1. 4. 28 states that the Sārkhya system is nearer to Vedanta than other systems like the atomic theory, since it espouses the doctrine of the non-difference between cause&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ROOR&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 Paiṭhīnasi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/24_paiThInasi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/24_paiThInasi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;24&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Paithinasi Though not enumerated in Yājsavalkya, Paithinasi seems to have been a comparatively ancient sūtrakāra on Dharma. On Yāj. III. 262 Viśvarūpa quotes a sutra of Paithinasi on the prāyaścitta for kiling a cow. Dr. Jolly (R. und $. p. 12 ) following Dr. Caland (&amp;ldquo;Ahnencult &amp;amp;c.&amp;rsquo; pp. 99, 109) thinks that Paithinasi belenys to the Atharvaveda as the prose quotations on frāddha agree with the ritual of the Atharvans. The Mit. (on Yāj. I. 53 ) quotes a sutra of Paithinasi to the effect that di person should marry a girl who is beyond the third degree on the mother&amp;rsquo;s side and beyond the fifth on the father&amp;rsquo;s side. 271 On Yāj. III. 17 the Mit. quotes two sūtras relating to impurity on death.272 The Smṛticandrikā, A parārka, Hara datta and other writers quote numerous sūtras of Paithinasi. The Smyticandrika has a prose quotation on the duties of women.273 In another place the Smṛticandrikā (II. p. 263 ) cites a sūtra on partition.274 Aparūrka (p. 112 ) quotes two verses of Paithinasi recommending the practice of sati to women of all castes except Brūhmana women. Aparārka (p. 239 ) quotes a sūtra saying that the food of astrologers;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;270 त्रीणि ज्योतींषि पुरुषे इति वै देवलोब्रवीत् । अपत्यं कर्म विद्या च यतः सृष्टाः&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 Budha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/25_budha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/25_budha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;25&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Budha This sūtrakāra is not mentioned by Yāj. nor by Parāśara. He is very rarely cited. Aparārka on Yāj. I. 4-5, Kalpataru on Brahmacāri pp. 24, 78, 160, on Gr. Kanda p. 262, Naiyata K. p. 211 (quoted in Vira-mitrodaya, Paribhāsa p. 16), Hemādri.378 Jimūta-vābana&amp;rsquo;s Kāla viveka are probably the&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;478 खियो गृहदेवताः । तासां न शौचं न व्रतं नोपवासः । पतिशुश्रूषया गच्छान्त&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;परमां गतिम् ॥पैठी in व्यव० कल्प. p. 827 ; compare अनुशासनपर्व 48. 15 (Ch. ed.) श्रिय एताः स्त्रियो नाम सत्कायो भूतिमिच्छता । लालिता निगृहीता च स्त्री श्रीर्भवति भारत ॥ (g. by कल्पतरु on व्यवहार p. 610 ): यत्र कचन जातेन पिता पुत्रेण नन्दति । तेन चानृणां याति पितृणां पिण्डदेन वै॥ शङ्ख-लिखित-पैठीनसि in व्यव० कल्प. p. 742 and स्मृतिच, व्यव०&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 Bṛhaspati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/26_bRhaspati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/26_bRhaspati/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;26&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Brhaspati&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That Bphaspati was an ancient teacher of Arthaśāstra follows from the Kauṭiliya, wherein the Bārhasratyas are cited six times. In the Mahabharata (Sinti. chap. 59. 80-85) Brhaspati is said to have compressed into 3000 chapters the work on dharma, artha and kāma composed by Brahma. The Vanaparva ( 32. 61) speaks of Brhaspati-niti. The Maha bhārata several times cites verses (yrithas or slokas ) said to have been sung by Brhaspatia80 ( vide Sinti. 23. 15, 56. 38-39,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 Bharadvāja and Bhāradvāja</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/27_bharadvAja_and_bhAradvAja/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/27_bharadvAja_and_bhAradvAja/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;27 Bharadvāja and Bhāradvāja&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;29&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bharadvāja and Bharadvaja&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;291&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;observance of Sandhyā and the kindling of fire ;38? on Yāj. 1. 32 Bharadvāja is quoted as prescribing a penance for even thinking of causing harm to beings ; 388 on Yāj. I. 185 a lengthy sutra of Bharadvaja on the purification of certain things is quoted, wherein is cited the view of soine that boys are purified by a mere bath when touched by antyajas ; 289 on Yaj I. 236 &amp;amp; prose passage of Bharadvāja forbids in śrāddhas the use of certain cereals as food. 200 Aparārka quotes a long prose passage (p. 1155 ) from Bharadvāja in connection with the prāyaścitta for cessiou of gļhya fires for various periods. .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 Śātātapa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/28_shAtAtapa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/28_shAtAtapa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;28&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Satatapa Śatātapa is enumerated among the expounders of dharma by Yāj. (I. 4-5) and by Parasura. Viśvarūpa, Haradatta and Aparārka quote several proge passages of Śatātapa on prāyascitta. Viśvarūpa (on Yāj. III. 236 ) tells us that Śatātapa -spoke of only eight, upapatakas and that without dealing with śrāddha as a principal topic he spoke of some of the subsidiary details of srāddha.294 The latter passage quoted from Sātātāpa is a half verse. So Viśvarūpa had a prose work of Sātītapa before him, mixed with verses, Haradatta on Gaut. ( Dh. S. 22. 18 ) quotes a prose passage of Sātāta pa about the penance for killing a cow. Viśvarūpa on Yaj. III. 236 (part II. p. 93 ) states that Sātata pa mentioned in a prose passage only eight. Upapatakas .Sātātape tu. astum. vevopapātakāpyuktāni, athopa pātakānyagnyutsūdītyādini&amp;rsquo; eko. Viśvarūpa on Yaj. III. 262 (part.2, p. 148) mentions a gutre of Śatātapa on prāyuścittu. Maskarī on Gaut. 23. 35 quotes a prose passage from S. on prāyaścıttas unudaka-mutrapu. risayrabane svakakasparśane Sacelasuinam mahā vyābrti. homuśca rajasvulnyamane cartildevann&amp;rsquo;. The Layhu-Satūta pa smrti (Anan. collection) contains several verses of Manu (e.g. verses 103, 105, 107 of it are respectively the girme as Mapu Ill, 237, III. 174, III. 233 and verses 45 and 58 refer to Śatātapa. Vfudba-Sātutupa is quoted several times in Kalpana taru e. g. ou pp. 98-99 of Brahma&amp;rsquo;, on pp. 286, 405 of Grbus tha, 6 times on Sraddha. It is interesting to note that a verse of Satata pa quoted by the Mit. on Yāj. 1. 192 provides that a prāyasetta is not prescribed for men who bathe iri exidvink tbe water from a well or a dam dug or constructed by antyajus. The Mit. on Yāj. quotes several prose passages of&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;208 सन्धिश्व परिवृत्तिश्च विभागश्च समा यदि। आदशाहं निवर्तेत विषमे नववत्सरात् ।। till ensairait pp. 314. 320. 294 74 ÇAT: 16497&amp;amp;a ad JUFTTE - Porat gal taiata ang hasta hacer? Tufan 20 a. I. 46 .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 Sumantu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/29_sumantu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/29_sumantu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;29&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sumantu For a Dharmasūtra of Sumantu vide Madras Tri. Cat. of Sanskrit M88. (1919-22 ) pp. 5160-62.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From Viśvarūpa, Haradatta and Aparārka it follows that Sumantu composed a sūtra work on dharma, particularly on ācāra and prāyaścitta. Viśvarūpa quotes prose passages from Sumantu on upapātakas, 390 on prāyaścitta for Brāh mana-murder ( on Yāj. III. 237), for drinking wine ( on Yāj. III. 250 ), for theft of gold (on Yaj. III. 252 ), for incest (on Yāj. III. 253-54 ), for killing a cow and about atatayin (on Yāj. III. 261 ). In one quotation from Sumantu cited by Viśvarūpa the views of ācāryas and of Angirasa are men tioned. 187 The prīyaścittas for Brāhmana-murder and for killing a cow contained in Viśvarūpa occur in Haradatta (on Gaut. 22. 13 and 18). Most of the qnotations cited by Viśva rūpa occur in Aparārka also. The Hāralatā (p. 68 ) quotes sūtras of Sumantu on āśauca. One well-known sutra of Suma ntu is &amp;rsquo;no prāyaścitta (or blame ) is incurred by killing an&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 The Smṛtis</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/30_the_smRtis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/30_the_smRtis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;30&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Smrtis&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;299&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;fine for selling and purchasing land without the consent of the neighbouriny members of the family and says that in case of pre-emption the neighbours on the east are preferred to all and those on the south come last. :02 Sunintu defines a mort gage by conditional sale (callel uktilihhakraya&amp;rsquo;) and a sale for arrears of revenue by the king&amp;rsquo;s orders (called ajna kraya ).303&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vide reconstruction of Sumanta by Prof. T. R. Chintamani in JOR ( Madras ) vol. VIII. pp. 75 ff.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 The Manusmṛti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/31_the_manusmRti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/31_the_manusmRti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;31-the-manusmṛti&#34;&gt;31. The Manusmṛti&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So many editions of this work have been published in India since 1813 ( when the Manusmṛti was first published at Calcutta ), that it is not possible to name them. In this work the Nirṇayasāgara edition with the commentary of Kullūka has been used throughout. Another edition of Manu well known on this side of India is that of the late V. N. Mandlik, who published several commentaries such as those of Medhātithi, Govindaraja and others. The Manusmṛti has been translated into English several times. The best known translation is that of Dr. Būhler in the S. B. E. series (vol. 25). Dr. Būhler also added an exhaustive and very scholarly introduction to his translation and dealt with numerous problems connected with the Manusmṛti.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32 The Two Epics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/32_the_two_epics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/32_the_two_epics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;32&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Two Epics The two great Epics of India, the Mahābhārata and the Rāmāyaṇa, contain ( particularly the first) numerous passa ges bearing on meny topics of Dharmaśāstra and are relied upon as authorities in medieval and later works. The Mabu bhārata itself claims (in Adiparva, 2. 83) that VyDS composed the work as a great Dharmaśāstra, as Arthasastra ( treatise on politics and Government), Moksaśāstra and also&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;POONA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1917&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33 The Purāṇas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/33_the_purANas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/33_the_purANas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;33&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Puranas The Yājṅavalkyasmști provides that Purāṇa, NMAYA (Tarkaśāstra ), Mimāṁsā, Dharmaśāstra, the ( six, subsidiary lores of the Veda (angas ) and the Vedas (four )-these fourteen&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;FOUNDET&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;AL..datno&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;33&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Purāṇas&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;409&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;are the sources ( means) of Vidyo and of Dharma. It would be noticed that the 14 sources are arranged by Yājñavalkya in a rising scale of importance and authoritativene88.460 The word Purāṇa ( a class of works ) occurs in the Atharvaveda (XI. 7. 24, XV. 6. 10-11). The Sat. Br. (XI. 5.6-8 ) includes&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>34 The Yājñavalkyasmṛti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/34_the_yAjnavalkyasmRti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/34_the_yAjnavalkyasmRti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;34&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Yājnavalkyasmrti This smrti has been published dozens of times. In the following the Nirnayasāgara edition edited by Sāstri Moghe ( 1892 A. D. ) has been used and the Trivandrum edition when speaking of Viśvarūpa.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The name of Yājña valkya is one of the most illustrious among Vedic sayes. He is credited with having promulgated the White Yajurveda. In the Suntiparva (chap. 312 ) we are told that there was a rupture between Vaiśampāyana and his pupil Yājṅavalkya and that by worshipping the Sun the latter received the revelation of the White Yajurveda, the Satapatha etc. The accounts in the Visuu (3. 5 ), the Bhagen vata ( XII. 6. 61-74 ) and other purāṇas differ somewhat from the one in the Mahabharata, but all agree on the fact of them strained relations between Yājña valkya and bis teacher. There&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>35 The Parāśara Smṛti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/35_the_parAshara_smRti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/35_the_parAshara_smRti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;35&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Parāsara Smrti&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This work has been published several times, but the edi. tion of Jivananda (part II. pp. 1-52 ) and that in the Bombay Sanskrit Series with the voluminous gloss of the great Mādhava are the best known. In the following pages Jika nanda&amp;rsquo;s edition has been used.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The smști of Parāśara must have been an ancient one as Yāj. (1.4 ) mentions him among the ancient writers on dha wim&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>36 The Nāradasmṛti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/36_the_nAradasmRti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/36_the_nAradasmRti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;36&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Nāradasmrti&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;467&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;36&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Naradasmrti&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are two versions of Nārada on Vyavahāra, a smaller and a larger one. The smaller version was translated by Dr. Jolly in 1876 (Trūbner &amp;amp; Co., London ). The text of the longer version was published by the same scholar in the Bib liotheca Indica series (1885 ) and was translated by him in the Sacred Books of the East Series ( vol. 33). The edition of the text is accompanied up to verse 21 of the 5th title abhyu petyāśusrūsā&amp;rsquo; by extracts from the commentary of Asabāya as revised by Kalyāṇabhattu, who was encouraged in the task of revision by Kesavabhatta.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>37 Bṛhaspati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/37_bRhaspati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/37_bRhaspati/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;484&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;37&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Brhaspati Brbaspati as a sūtra writer on politics has been dealt with above ( section 26 ). In this section Brhaspati the jurist will be spoken of. The complete smrti of Bșhaspati on law has not yet been discovered. It will be, when discovered, a very precious monument of ancient India, exhibiting the high water mark of Indian acumen in strictly legal principles and definitions. Dr. Fūbrer collected together 84 verses ascribed to Brhaspati in the legal treatises of Aparārka and others with German translation and notes ( Leipzig, 1879 ) and Dr. Jolly collected about 711 verses of Brhaspati on law and translated them in the Sacred Books of the East (vol. 33 ).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Yāj. (I. 4-5 ) enumerates Brhaspati among the writers on dharma, but he is probably referring to Brlaspati&amp;rsquo;s work on politics. The com. on the Nitivākyrimpta (p. 7) quotes the first verse of Brhaspati&amp;rsquo;s Nitiśastra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>38 Kātyāyana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/38_kAtyAyana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/38_kAtyAyana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;496&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;38&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Katyayana Nārada, Bșhaspati and Kātyāyana form a triumvirate in the realm of the ancient Hindu Law and procedure. The work of Kātyāyana on Vyavahāra, like that of Bphaspati, has yet to be recovered. After the first volume of H. of Dh. was published in 1930, I contributed to a Law Journal in Bombay &amp;amp; collec tion of Kātyāyana&amp;rsquo;s verses gathered from quotations in 21 works and later (in 1933 ) published in a book form 973 verses of Kātyāyana with English translation, two Appendices and a General Index (in all 372 pages). Later on Prof. K. V. Rangaswami Aiyangar contributed a paper to the Kane Fest schrift (pp 7-17) embodying 121 additional verses of Kātyāyana from the work called Vyavahāranirṇaya of Vara darāja ( which he published in 1942 48 No. 29 of the Adyar Library series ).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kātyāyana is enumerated as one of the expounders of dhurma by Sarkha-Likhita, Yājṅavalkya ( I. 4-5 ) and Parā Sara. A Kātya is quoted as an authority in the Baudhāyana dharmasūtra (I. 2. 37). A Srautasūtra and Sraddhakalpa of the white Yajurveda are ascribed to Kātyāyana.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>39 Aṅgiras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/39_angiras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/39_angiras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;39&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Angiras Angiras is one of the ten primordial sages mentioned in Manusmrti 1.34-35). It is &amp;amp; very ancient oame even in the Rgverle. On Yāj. I. 50 Viśvarūpa quotes a verge of Angiras that what is done according to one&amp;rsquo;s owo will without follow ing the dictates of Sāstra is fruitless.578 On Yaj. III. 248 Viśvarūpa says that the vrutie called Vajra wu8 prescribed by Angiras for Brāhmunas guilty of deadly sins. Viśvarūpa (on Yāj. III. 255 ) quotes two verses of Argiras on the prayaścitta for killine the wife of a brāhinana who has kindled the sacred fires for killing wives of other brahmanas and ksatriyas and vaisyas. On Yāj. III. 266 he quotes two verses of&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Y&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>40 Ṛṣyaśṛṅga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/40_ShyashRnga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/40_ShyashRnga/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;510&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ilistory of Dharmaśāstra&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;40&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Rsyasrnga This is a writer who is frequently quoted on ācāra, āśauca, srāddha, and prāyaścittu by the Mit., Aparārka, Smṛticand rikā and other works. A parārka (p. 724 ) quotes as Rsyas roga&amp;rsquo;s a verse ascribed to Sarkha in the Mitāksarā ( on Yāj. II. 119 ) and other works, which states that when one copar cener recovers with his own efforts family property that was lost to the family, he gets a fourth share of it and the others become sharers in the rest.684 The Smrticandrikā (I. p. 32 ) quotes &amp;lsquo;api vāsasi yajñopavitārthān kuryāt tadabhāve trivstā sūtrena&amp;rsquo;, which is in prose,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rsyaśṛnga is frequently quoted by Aparārka on the Prāyaścitta section of Yāj. (about 13 verses ) on Prāyaścitta. The Vy. N. of Varadaraja ( p. 26 ) ascribes the verse of Yāj. II. 32 ( Mattonmattārta &amp;amp;c) to Rsyaśṣnga also. Aparārka (p. 724 ) quotes one verse of Rsya&amp;rsquo;, on Vyavahāra viz. &amp;lsquo;If one coparcener in a joint family recovers by his efforts pro perty lost to the fumily, he should be awarded one-fourth of it and the remaining portion should be distributed among the remaining coparceners according to their proper shares. This verse is ascribed to Saikha by the Smrticandrikā ( on p. 276 ). Kalpataru (on Vy. 622 ) quotes two verses on a wife&amp;rsquo;s duties.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>41 Kārṣṇājini</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/41_kArShNAjini/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/41_kArShNAjini/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;41&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Karsnajini This writer is quoted by the Mit. (YĀj. III. 265 three verses ), Aparārka, Smṛticandrikī and other works mostly op srāddha. A parārka (p. 138 ) quotes a verse from him which enumerates the seven sons of Bralmā, viz. Sanaka, Sanandana, Sanātana, Kapila, Asuri, Vodha (?) and Panca sikha. A parūrka (p. 424 ) quotes a verse of Kārsnājini which refers to the two signs of the Zodiac, Kanyā, and Vrścikā.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>42 Caturviṁśatimata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/42_chaturvishatimata/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/42_chaturvishatimata/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;42&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Caturvimsatimata There are two Mgs. of this work in the Bhandarkar Institute, Poona (No. 244 of A. 1881-1882 and 111 of 1895-1902). It contains 525 verses. The work is so called because it embodies the essence of the teachings of 24 sages, Manu, Yājña valkya, Atri, Viṣṇu, Vasistha, Vyāsa, Usanas, Apaskambe, 584 पूर्वनष्टा तु यो भूमिमेकश्येदुद्धरेत् क्रमात् । यथाशं तुं लभन्तेन्ये वाचशित&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;a81494 11&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;FOUNDED&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1917&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;42&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Caturviñsatimata&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;511&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vatsa, Harita, Guru ( Brhaspati), Narada, Parāsara, Gautama, Yama, Baudhāyana, Daksa, Saikha, Aigiras, Śatātapa, Sārkhya (Sārkhyāyana? ), Saṁvarta. The subjects treated of are :&amp;ndash; The usages of the varmas and iframas, sauca, acamana, cleansing the teeth, bath, pranayama, repeating the Gāyatri, study of the Vedas, marriage, agnihotra, five great daily yajñas, means of livelihood, forest hermits, sam nyāsins, duties of Ksatriyas and the other two varṇas, prāyaścittas for the deadly sins and other lesser misdeeds, means of livelihood, srāddha, āśauca (on birth and death ).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>43 Dakṣa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/43_daxa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/43_daxa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;43&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Daksa&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dakṣa is one of the writers on dharma enumerated by Yāj. Vigvarūpa quotes verses of Daksa several times, viz. on Yāj. 1. 17 (on clods of earth for purifying the body ), on Yāj. III. 30 (two verses on āśauca ), on Yāj. III. 66 ( about &amp;amp; parivrājaka ), on Yāj. III. 191 (about padmāsada ). The Mit. (on Yāj. I. 89) quotes a half verse of Daksa to the effect that a dvija should not remain unattached to an asrama (i. e. without a wife in the context ) even for a moment; on Yāj. III. 58 two verses about bhikṣus; on Yāj. III. 243 (one verse ). Aparārka cites numerous verses of Dakṣa on ācāra, āśauca, srāddha and similar topics. In one case (p. 368 ) be attributes a prose passage to Dakṣa about the gift of gold.500 Two of Daksa&amp;rsquo;s verses most frequently quoted by writers on vyavahāra are those that lay down wbat nine things cannot be the subjects of gift.601&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>44 Pitāmaha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/44_pitAmaha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/44_pitAmaha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;44&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Pitāmaha&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pitāmaba is enumerated among writers on dharma in a verse of Vṛddha-Yājsavalkya quoted by Viśvarūpa. The Smrti of Pitāmaha (part I p. 10) is drawn upon mostly on Vyavabāra. Viśvarūpa cites (on Yaj. I. 17 ) &amp;amp; verse from him on sauca.603 The Mitākṣarā and Aparārka respective ly quote about 45 and 75 verses from Pitāmaba only on Vyavabāra and specially on ordeals and the Kalpataru on Vyavahāra quotes about 90 verses on the same topics from Pitāmaha. Some verses are ascribed to both Pitāmaha and Nārada (as in Kalpataru Vy. pp. 238, 239) and in a few cases to Bșhaspati and Pitāmaba (as in Kalpataru, Vy. p. 251 ). The Smṛticandrikā quotes about ten verses (of Pito ) on āhnika, 130 on Vyavahāra and only a few on srāddha. Pitāmaha regards the Vedas with the angas, Mimāṁsā, the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>45 Pulastya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/45_pulastya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/45_pulastya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;45&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Pulastya Pulastya&amp;rsquo;s name is among the ten primordial sages men tioned in the Manusmrti I. 34&amp;ndash;35.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pulastya is one of the expounders of dharma enumerated by Vrddha-Yājñavalkya. Viśvarūpa quotes a verse from him on sārīraśauca.604 The Mit. (on Yāj. I. 261 ) cites &amp;amp; verse from Pulastya that a Brāhmaṇa should principally use asce tic&amp;rsquo;s food (i. e. vegetable food ) in srāddha, that ksatriyas and vaisyas should use meat and būdras madhu.606 The Mit. (Yāj. III. 253 ) quotes two verses of Pulastya who enumerates eleven intoxicating drinks together with surā as the twelfth.806 Aparārka quotes several verses from Pulastya on saṁdhyā, Sraddha, asauca, duties of yatis, prayascitta. Aparārka quotes two verses from Pulastya propounding the view that a&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>46 Paiṭhīnasi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/46_paiThInasi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/46_paiThInasi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;46&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Paithīnasi&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Paithīnasi, though not named among the Smṛtikāras enu merated in Yāj. I. 4-5, is mentioned among the 36 Smṛtis quoted by Aparārka (p. 7) from the Bhaviṣyapurāua and also in the quotation from Paithinasi about the thirty-six names of the expounders of Dharmaśāstra in the Smiṣti-Candrikā (p. 1). Another reason is that he appears to have dealt in his work with all three branches of Dharmaśāstra, viz. ācāra, vyavahāra and prayascitta. Another important matter is that quotations in prose from him far outnumber quotations in verse in the comparatively early digests like the Mit., Aparārka, Kalpataru. Viśvarūpa on Yāj. III. 262 cites a prose&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>47 Pracetas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/47_prachetas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/47_prachetas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;47&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Pracetas&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pracetas fiuds a place among the sages enumerated by Perāsara (though not in Yājñavalkya), in the list of 36 Smrti kāras by Paithināsi in Smṛticandrikā p. 1). In both Mit. and Aparārka there are passages in prose and verse ascribed to Pracetas on daily duties, srāddha, āśauca, prāyascitta. The Mit. (on Yāj. III. 27 ) quotes &amp;amp; verse from Pracetas saying that workmen, artisans, physicians, male and female slaves, kings, royal officers have not to observe periods of impurity 811 (on death). This verse is cited as a smrti by Medhātithi on Manu V. 60 without ascribing it to Pracetas. So Medhātithi looked upon Pracetas as equally authoritative with Manu, Viśṇu and others.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>48 Prajāpati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/48_prajApati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/48_prajApati/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;48&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Prajapati Prajāpati is cited as an authority by the Baudhāyana dharinasūtra (II. 4. 15 and II. 10. 71 ). Vasistha several times quotes Prājāpatya blokas (viz. III. 47, XIV. 16-19, 24-27, 30-32). It has been shown above that most of these Verses are found in the Manusmrti or have close correspon dence with verses of Manu. So it is not unlikely that both the writers of dharmasūtras mean Manu by Prajāpati.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Anandāśrama collection (p. 90-98 ) there is a smrti of Prajāpati in 198 verses on the various details of frāddha, such as the time, place, the persons authorised to perform, proper food, Brāhmanas to be invited etc. The pre vailing metre is Auustubh, but there are nine verses in the Indravajrā, Upajāti, Vasantatilakā (verse 137 ) and Sragdharā (verse 96 ). It speaks of Kalpaśāstra, smrtis, dharmaśāstra, purāṇas. It contains a verse referring to the Kanya and Vrścika ( scorpion ) signs of the Zodiac, which is almost the same as a verse of Kārśṇājini.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>49 Marīci</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/49_marIchi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/49_marIchi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;49&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Marici&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The name Marici is very ancient. In Manusmṛti II. 34-35 Marici is mentioned first among the ten Prajāpatis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This sage is relied upon as an authority by the Mit., Aparārka, Smrticandrika on Ahnika, Asauca, Sraddha, Prāyascitta and Vyavahāra. Aparārka quotes several verses on&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;है आपके&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;813 मातामहस्य गोत्रेण मातुः पिण्डोदकक्रियाम् । कुर्वीत पुत्रिकापुत्र एवमाह&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;प्रजापतिः ॥ अपरार्क. 814 साक्षी विभेदो विज्ञेयः कृत एकोऽपरोऽकृतः । लेख्यारूढः कृतो ज्ञेयः मुक्तकोऽ.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;कृत उच्यते । अपरार्क p. 666, स्मृतिच० (व्य. p. 80 reads उत्तरोऽकृत०). 815 स्मृतिच० (व्य. p. 42-43 ), परा. मा. vol. III, p. 69-73. 618 पूर्व प्रमीताग्निहोत्रं मृते भर्तरि तद्धनम् । लभेत् पतिव्रता नारी धर्म एष&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>50 Yama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/50_yama/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/50_yama/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;50&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Yama&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Vasistha-dharmasutra (18. 13-15 and 19. 48 ) cites four slokas of Yama and quotes (11. 20 ) one verse in which Yama is spoken of as an authority. All the slokas except one&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;818 सप्तम्यां रविवारे च गृही जन्मदिने तथा । भृत्यपुत्रकलत्रार्थी न कुर्यात्तिल&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;atunt il 34727* p, 132 ; ffaao ( 341 p. 123 ). 619 TDAH perfish tat hal peat: larg Fri 7 gata sararaan&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ATUTA 11 3742T* p. 235. 820 स्थावरे विक्रयाधाने विभागे दान एव च । प्रतिग्रहे च क्रीते च नालेख्या&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>51 Laugākṣi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/51_laugAxi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/51_laugAxi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;51&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Laugaksi&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Laugākṣi is mentioned among the 36 expounders of Dharmaśāstra set out by Paithīnasi (on p. 1 of Smṛ. Ch.) and Angiras quoted on the same page includes Laugākṣi among Upasmṛtis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Mit. (on Yāj. III, 1-2, 260, 289 ) quotes verses of Laugāksi on āśauca and prāyascitta. Aparārka quotes nine proge passages (pp. 28–29, 33, 122, 145, 166, 176 and 530) on Ācāra including Srāddha and ten verses on ten pages on Acāra, Āśauca and the order of forest hermits and one very long prose passage on p. 1227 (covering half a page ). On p. 542 Aparārka quotes a verse of Laugāksi in which Prajāpati is mentioned as an authority. The Mit. on Yāj. II. 118-119 quotes the definitions of Yoga&amp;rsquo;and Ksema given by Laugākṣi and which are declared to be not liable to partition by coparceners ( acc. to Mapu IX. 219 ), even if they be acqui red by detriment to the parental estate. Those definitions of Yoga and Kṣema are quoted by many works and writers on Vyavahāra such as the Smṛticandrikā (on Vy. p. 277 ), Par. M. Vol. III. p. 563. Vide H. of Dh. Vol. III. pp. 588-589 for different meanings of the two words.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>52 Viśvāmitra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/52_vishvAmitra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/52_vishvAmitra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;52&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Viśvamitra Vievāmitra is one of the writers on dharma enumerated by Vrddha-Yājījavalkya as quoted by Viśvarūpa. Aparārka, the Smṛticandrikā, the Kālaviveka of Jimūtavāhana and other works quote verses of Viśvāmitra on almost all topics of dharma except vyavahāra, such as on the five deadly sins, on srāddhas, prāyaścitta etc. Viśvāmitra defines dharma as that which is esteemed by Aryas ( respectable people who know the Vedas. 640 Aparārka quotes 18 verses from Visvā. mitra on Prayascitta and the Sinrticandrikā also quotes several verses of his Kalpataru ( on Brahmacario), cites Yāj. I. 14 (Garbhāstame &amp;amp;c.) as occurring in Viśvāmitra also. Similarly Kalpataru (on Naiyatakāla p. 314 ) states that Yāj. I. 179 (prānātyaye &amp;amp;c. ) also occurs in Visvāmitra&amp;rsquo;s Smṛti. His verses on the mahāpātakas are frequently quoted.641 The Madras (Govt. ) Mss. cat. (p. 1985 No. 2717 ; notices a Smṛti of Visvāmitra in verse in nine chapters.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;RA&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>53 Vyāsa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/53_vyAsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/53_vyAsa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;53&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vyāsa In Jivananda (part II, pp. 321-342 ) and in the Anandā srama collection of smṛtis there is a smrti ascribed to Vyasa (pp. 357-371 ). The two texts are the same with a few variations. It is in four chapters and contains about 250 verses. Vyāsa is said to have declared the Smrti in Benares.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;640 यमार्याः क्रियमाणं तु शंसन्त्यागमवेदिनः । स धर्मों यं विगर्हन्ति तमधर्म&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Tad il pictato ( 1T1 p. ). 841 ब्राह्मणो न च हन्तव्यः सुरा पेया न च द्विजैः । ब्राह्मणस्वर्णहरणं न कर्तव्य&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>54 Ṣaṭ-triṁśan-mata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/54_aT-trishan-mata/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/54_aT-trishan-mata/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;54 Ṣaṭ-triṁśan-mata&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;54&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sat-trimsan-mata The title literally means &amp;rsquo;the doctrines of thirty-six (Smṛtis )&amp;rsquo;. This appears to have been a work like the Catur vimśatimata. It has been stated above that Paithinasi enumerated thirtysix propounders of Dharma (vide Smrtican drikā p. 1). Quotations from Șat-trimsan-mata cited in the&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;653 पलान्यष्टौ सुवर्णस्य सुवर्णाश्च चतुर्दश । एतनिष्कप्रमाणं तु व्यासेन परिकीर्तितम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;quoted by plago (jo ) p. 99, 97. AT. ( 200 ) p. 158. 864 चतस्रस्तु परित्याज्याः शिष्यगा गुरुगा च या। पतिध्नी च विशेषेण जुङ्गितो.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>55 Saṁgraha or Smṛtisaṁgraha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/55_saMgraha_or_smRtisagraha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/55_saMgraha_or_smRtisagraha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;55 Saṁgraha or Smṛtisaṁgraha&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;55&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Samgraha or Smrtisamgraha This work is frequently cited by the Mitākṣarā, Aparārka, the Smṛticandrikā and other works on all topics of dharma, The quotations on vyavahāra are copious and are very im&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;659&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;657 तिलहोमायुतं चैव पराकद्वयमेव च । गायत्र्या लक्षमेकं च समान्याह बृहस्पतिः॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अपरार्क p. 1249. 658 समुच्छिष्टस्तु यो भुङ्क्ते मुद्दे वा मुक्त भोजनः । एवं वैवस्वतः प्राह भुक्त्वा&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सान्तपनं चरेत् ॥ अपराके p. 1174. प्रामाण्यमेव ये वेदे न वदन्ति कुदृष्टयः । तेषां बौद्धार्हतादीनां पाषण्डाख्या प्रकीर्त्यते ॥ प्रव्रज्य वसिता (प्रवज्यावसिता) ये तु पाषण्डास्ते प्रकीर्तिताः। पौरुषेयतया वेदं (वेदे?) प्रामाण्यं प्रवदन्ति ये। तेषां वैशेषिकादीनां नैगमाख्या&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>56 Saṁvarta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/56_savarta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/56_savarta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;56&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Samvarta Saṁvarta occurs as a Smrtikāra in the list of Yājña valkya. He is cited on all topics of dharma by Viśvarūpa, Medhātithi, the Mit., Haradatta, Aparirka, the Smṛticandrikā and a host of other writers. Viśvarūpa quotes either wholly or in part about twenty verses of Samvarta on evening sandhyā vandana, on the duties of a yuti and on the prāyaścittas for theft, adultery of various kinds, deadly sius. Medhātithi quotes verses of Surivarta on Manu V. 88 and XI. 116. The Mit. quotes him on prayascitta and aśauca ( Yāj. III. 6. 17 19 etc. ). Apararka had a large work before him and quotes about 200 verses almost all on īcīra and priyuscitta.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A few of the views of Samvartu on topics of vyavahāra may be noted here. According to him oral testimony when in opposition to writing was to be discarded. 674 This is in striking agreement with section 92 of the Indian Evidence Act. He says that if houses and fields are being enjoyed ( by one person us against another ) when the king is there (i. e. when the central government is strong and there is no&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>57 Hārīta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/57_hArIta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/57_hArIta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;57&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Harīta The verse quotations from Hārīta on topics of vyavahāra deserve some treatment. He defines vyavahāra as that where by the recovery of one&amp;rsquo;s own wealth and the avoidance of (doing ) the duties peculiar to another (caste or class ) are effected in due course of law.878 He further says that that judicial proceeding is proper which is based on the dictates of dharmaśāstra and arthasāstra, which is in conformity with the usages of respectable people and which is free from fraud.978 Hārita calls upon the king to know the sāstras, the&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NST&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>58 Commentaries and Nibandhas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/58_commentaries_and_nibandhas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/58_commentaries_and_nibandhas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;58 Commentaries and Nibandhas&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;58&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Commentaries and Nibandhas ( digests )&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The literature on Dharmaśāstra falls into three well marked but somewhat over-lapping periods. The first period is that of the ancient dharmasūtras and of the Manusmrti. It is a period dating from at least the 6th century B. C. to the beginnings of the Christian era. Next comes the period when most of the versified smrtis were composed and it ranges from the first centuries of the Christian era to about 800 A. D. The third period is that of the commentators and the writers of digests. This covers over a thousand years from about the 7th century to 1800 A. D. The first part of this last period was the golden era of famous commentators. Commentaries on smrti works continued to be written almost to the end of this period, e. g. Nandapandita wrote the commentary called Vaijayanti on the Viṣṇudharmasūtra in the 17th century. But the general tendency from the 12th century onwards was&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>59 Asahāya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/59_asahAya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/59_asahAya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;59&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Asahāya&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jolly in his edition of the Nāradasmrti (B. I. series ) bas incorporated a portion of the bhāsya of Asahāya as re vised by Kalyānabhatta. Even this revised version comes up to only verse 21 of the fifth title abhyupetya-asuśrūṣā. The exact relation of Kalyānabhatta&amp;rsquo;s labours to the original bhāsya cannot be accurately gauged from the opening888 words &amp;rsquo; finding that the Nāradathāsya composed by Asahāya was spoilt (bhrasta ) by bad scribes, Kalyāṇa composes this after revising the ancient one&amp;rsquo;. The colophon at the end of the first chapter of the Vyavahāramātýkā says that Kalyānabhatta&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>60 Bhartṛyajña</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/60_bhartRyajna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/60_bhartRyajna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;| āo. Bharteyajĩa This seems to have been a very ancient commentator. Medhātithiros in his bhāsya on Manu 8. 3 says &amp;lsquo;other explana tions have been well brought out by Bhartļyajña and they should be understood from his work&amp;rsquo;. Trikānda-mandana (who flourished before 1100 A. D.) in his Āpastambasūtra dhvanitārtha-kāriki708 (I. 41) refers to the views of Bhartr yajña that one who had committed to memory the text of the Veda had the privilege ( the adhikāra ) of consecrating the sacred fires, though he may be innocent of the meaning of the Vedic texts. From Ananta&amp;rsquo;s bhāsya it appears that Bhartryajña composed a bhāsya on the KĀtyāyanaśrautasūtra which had been lost (autsanna) in the former&amp;rsquo;s day. From Gadūdhara&amp;rsquo;s comments on the Paraskaragrhyasūtra it appears that Bhartryajña commented on Pāraskara,707 The Grhastha ratnākara of Candeśvara quotes Bhartsyajña’s explanation of&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>61 Viśvarūpa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/61_vishvarUpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/61_vishvarUpa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;61&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Viśvarupa The commentary of Viśvarūpia called Bālakrīdā on the Yājsavalkya-smrti has been recently published in two parts by M. M. T. Ganapati Sāstri in the Trivandrum Sanskrit Series. The Mit. states in the introductory verses that the dicta of Yij. were expanded by the voluminous or ample (vikata ) explanations of Viśvarūsra. In commenting on Yāj. 1. 81 the Mit. tells us that Viśvarūjia looked upon the words of Yāj. I. 79 ( tasmin yugmāsu saṁviset ) as a niyama. In Viśvarūpa&amp;rsquo;s commentary on Yāj. I. 80 (evam gacchan &amp;amp;c. ) we do find that the verse of Yāj. and similar passages of Manu (3. 45 ), Vasistha and Gautama ( 5. 1 ) are understood to contain a niyam and not a prescinkhyu.?!! On Yāj. III. 24 the Mit, inforins us that Viśvarūpa, Medhātithi and Dhāre svara looked upon certain texts of Rsyasriiga on āściucu as in conflict with well-known sinitis and discarded them. Mr. S. Sitaram Sūstri published (in 1900 at Madras ) the text and translation of Viśvarūpia&amp;rsquo;s comment ou inheritance and Mr. Setlur also published the wavahūrco section. In the following pages the Trivandrum edition is relied on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The printed com. of Viśvarūpa on the vyavaharu section is extreinely meagre and scarcely merits the epithet vikata applied to it by the Mit. But the commentary of Viśvarūpa on the ācāra and grīyascitta sections is truly voluminous and coinpares favourably with the Mit. The style of Viśvarūpa is simple and forcible and resembles that of the great Saṅkarā. cārya. He quotes profusely from Vedic works, mentions the Carakas and Vājasaneyins (on Yaj 1. 32 ), the Kathaka (on Yaj. III. 237 and 243 ) and very often supports his position by quotatious from the Rgveda (e.g. on Yāj. 11. 121 and 206 ), the Brāhmanas (e. g. the Sata patha on Yāj. 1. 53 and III. 257 ) and from the Upanisads (e. g. on Yāj. 11. 117, the well-known&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>62 Bhāruci</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/62_bhAruchi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/62_bhAruchi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;62&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bhāruci The Mit. on Yij. (I. 81) says that Bhiruci like Viśvaripa held the view that the rulertau bhūryam gacchet&amp;rsquo; was a niyanma and not a paristkrinkhayti. On Yij. II 124 the Mit. says that the explanation of&amp;rsquo; the fourth share&amp;rsquo; to be given to un married sisters oflered by Asahiya and Medhitithi was the&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;732 अत एवोक्तं श्राद्धकलिकायां-मासिकानि सपिण्डं च अमावास्या तथाब्दिकम् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अन्नेनैव तु कर्तव्यं यस्य भाया रजस्वला ॥ इति । अनेनैव कर्तव्यं न त्वामान्नादिनेति च कलिकाविवरणेपि श्रीमद्विश्वरूपाचार्यव्याख्यानम् । Ms. in&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>63 Śrīkara</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/63_shrIkara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/63_shrIkara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;63&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Srikara The Mit. on Yāj. II. 135 alludes to the view of Srikara and others that the widow succeeded is heir to her deceased husband&amp;rsquo;s estate if it was small.743 The Smytisāra744 of Harinātha attributes the same view to Srikara and disappro ves of it. On Yāj. II. 169 the Mit.746 cites the view of Srikara about that topic and disapproves of it. Viśvarūpa also gives two explanations of that verse of Yāj., the first of which agrees with that of the Mit, and the second is akin to Srikara&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The works of Jimūtavāhana (viz. the Dayabhāga and the Vyavahāramātṛkā ), the Smrticandrikā and the Sarasvati vilāsa contain very interesting notices of Srikara&amp;rsquo;s views. Many of them were brought together by ne in JBBRAS for 1925, pp. 213-215. Srikara like Viśvarūpa held the view that &amp;lsquo;duhitarah in Yūj. refers to the putriku, he allowed the parents of a chililless person to succeed together at the same time. The Diyabhāga very severely criticizes the views of Srikara on the succession to re-united members, on vidyā dhana and on Yaj. II. 24 ( about enjoyment for 20 years ). 148 Most of the views attributed to Srikara were also entertained by Viśvarūpa ur are more antiquated than Viśvarūpa&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>64 Medhātithi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/64_medhAtithi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p1/64_medhAtithi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;64&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Medhātithi Medhātithi is the author of an extensive and erudite commentary ( bhusyu ) on the Manusmrti. It is the oldest extant commentary on that smrti. The bhāsya of Medhātithi was first published about forty years ago by Rao Saheb V. N. Mandlik in Bombay and recently Mr. J. R. Gharpure of Bombay brought out an edition of Medhātithi which closely follows Mandlik&amp;rsquo;s edition. A critical edition of the bhāsya based upon all the available Msg. is a great clesideratum. A new edition in two volumes based on several mss. edited by M. M. Dr. Ganganath Jha was published in the G. O. I. Series in 1932 and 1939. In this edition also ten verses in the 3rd adhyāya are wanting and in adhyāya nine there&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;750 &amp;lsquo;राजधने दीनानाथादिसकलप्राणिनामंशित्वं बहुनायकत्वाद्राज्यविनाशश्चेति&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
