<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;04 Purāṇas and Dharmaśāstra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/04_purANas_and_dharmashAstra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;04 Purāṇas and Dharmaśāstra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/04_purANas_and_dharmashAstra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>22 History of Purāṇa Literature</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/04_purANas_and_dharmashAstra/22_History_of_purANa_Literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/04_purANas_and_dharmashAstra/22_History_of_purANa_Literature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECTION IV THE PURĀNAS AND DHARMAŚĀSTRA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXII Origin and development of Purāṇa literature&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The History of Dharmaśāstra (vol I pp. 160-167 ) has a hrief chapter on the Puranas. It has been shown tharsin how the Taittiriya Arapyaka, the Chandogya and Bṛbadaranyaka Upanisads mention Itihasa and Purana (sometimes callectively as &amp;lsquo;Itihasapuradam&amp;rsquo; and sometimes separately as &amp;lsquo;Itibasah Purāpam&amp;rsquo;) and how some of the extant Parāṇas are minch varlier than the 6th century A.D. It is further pointed out there that the number of the principal Puranag has been traditionally handed down as eighteen, 324 that some para as much as the Matsya, the Vispu, the Vayu and Bhaviṣya contain mich Dharms śāstra material, that the Garuḍa-purana and the Aguipurna contain several bundred verses each that are identical with verste of the Yājñavalkya amrti, that there is great divergence as to the extent of almost all Purapas, that some of the Paranas that selves enumerate minor works called Upaparabas, that the Puranas are divided into three groups, vis sātlaku, rajasa and tāmasa (as done by Garuḍa L 223. 17-20, and Padma VL. 263. 81-84). Details were also farnished as to the chapters of the Puranas in which the several topics of Dharmasastra (ch as ācāra, āhnika, dana, röjadharma, fuddha, tirtha ) were dealt with&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 Notes on Purāṇas and Upapurāṇas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/04_purANas_and_dharmashAstra/23_Notes_on_purANas_and_upapurANas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/04_purANas_and_dharmashAstra/23_Notes_on_purANas_and_upapurANas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Brief Notes on individual Purāṇas and Upapurāṇas&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Agnipurāṇa- Present Agni&amp;rsquo; (by H.) in L. H. Q. vol Xi pp. 683-691: &amp;lsquo;Studies in genuine Agneya alias Vahnipurāṇa&amp;rsquo; by H. in Our Heritage&amp;rsquo; vol. I part 2 pp. 209–245 and vol. II part 1 pp. 76-109; &amp;lsquo;Discovery of genuine Āgneyapurāṇa &amp;rsquo; by E. in J. O. L (Baroda ) vol. V (1956) pp. 411-416 ( shows that present Agni published by Anan. Press is not the original Purana, that this was compiled late, while the original Agneya or Vahni is not yet printed ); the Dānasāgara p. 7. verse 63 speaks of an Āgneya which it has discarded apart from one which it has utilized (p. % Vorso 11 ). As usual with most Purāṇas, the printed Agneya glorifies itself by saying (in chap. 272. 13 and 17 ) that in that Mahāpurāṇa Hari resides in the form of diffe rent lores and the Agneya is a great purāṇa full of Veda and all vidyās.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
