<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;MT on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/MT/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;MT on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/MT/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Red lines</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/MT/red_lines/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/articles/MT/red_lines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/1941532934512456009&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Again and again, the question of who is a Hindu comes up. Another form of it is “Red Lines,” one must draw to exclude someone from being an H. We see this in large part as reactionary – something responding to the Abrahamistic assault on the practitioners of dharma. Few days ago, we had posted a statement from an early scripture of the shaivAgama canon that had implicitly defined what could be taken as the boundaries of the H tradition. However, that boundary was not a sharp one; other comparable definitions over a millennium placed it at slightly different radii. Sometimes the boundary was not sharp – something seen in bhaTTa jayanta’s AgamaDambara. Different expansive boundaries (“big-tent”) were implicitly given in medieval times by authors like vij~nAnabhikShu and vidyAraNya. While we ought to be guided by the long tradition in this regard, the boundary and or the definition need to be a static one – there is definitely no harm in it to change with time, depending on the benefits it offers to those inside the boundary, likewise, with its porosity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
