<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2.1 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2.1 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Topics of Dharmaśāstra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/01_Topics_of_dharmashAstra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/01_Topics_of_dharmashAstra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Manifold are the topics that have been included under {{Dharmaśāstra|Dharmaśāstra}} from very ancient times. The {{Dharma-sūtras|Dharma-sūtras}} of Gautama, Baudhāyana, Āpastamba and Vasiṣṭha deal in greater or less detail principally with the following subjects: the several &lt;em&gt;varṇas&lt;/em&gt; (classes), &lt;em&gt;āśramas&lt;/em&gt; (stages of life), their privileges, obligations and responsibilities; the &lt;em&gt;saṁskāras&lt;/em&gt; performed on an individual (from &lt;em&gt;garbhādhāna&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;antyeṣṭi&lt;/em&gt;); the duties of the &lt;em&gt;brahmacārin&lt;/em&gt; (the first āśrama); &lt;em&gt;anadhyāyas&lt;/em&gt; (holidays on which Vedic study was stopped); the duties of a &lt;em&gt;snātaka&lt;/em&gt; (one who has finished the first stage of life); &lt;em&gt;vivāha&lt;/em&gt; (marriage) and all matters connected therewith; the duties of the &lt;em&gt;gṛhastha&lt;/em&gt; (house-holder&amp;rsquo;s stage); &lt;em&gt;śauca&lt;/em&gt; (daily purification of body); the five daily &lt;em&gt;yajñas&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;dāna&lt;/em&gt; (gifts); &lt;em&gt;bhakṣyābhakṣya&lt;/em&gt; (what food should one partake of and what not); &lt;em&gt;śuddhi&lt;/em&gt; (purification of persons, vessels, clothes &amp;amp;c.); &lt;em&gt;āśauca&lt;/em&gt; (impurity on birth and death); &lt;em&gt;antyeṣṭi&lt;/em&gt; (rites on death); &lt;em&gt;śrāddha&lt;/em&gt; (rites performed for the deceased ancestors and relatives); &lt;em&gt;strīdharma&lt;/em&gt; (special duties of women) and &lt;em&gt;strīpuṁdharma&lt;/em&gt; (duties of husband and wife); &lt;em&gt;dharmas&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;kṣatriyas&lt;/em&gt; and of kings; &lt;em&gt;vyavahāra&lt;/em&gt; (judicial procedure, and the sphere of substantive law such as crimes and punishments, contracts, partition and inheritance, adoption, gambling &amp;amp;c.); the four principal classes, mixed castes and their proper avocations; &lt;em&gt;āpaddharma&lt;/em&gt; (actions and avocations permitted to the several castes in extreme difficulties); &lt;em&gt;prāyaścitta&lt;/em&gt; (sins and how to expiate them); &lt;em&gt;karmavipāka&lt;/em&gt; (results of evil deeds done in past lives); &lt;em&gt;śānti&lt;/em&gt; (rites on the happening of portents or for propitiating the planets &amp;amp;c.); duties of &lt;em&gt;vānaprastha&lt;/em&gt; (forest hermit) and &lt;em&gt;saṁnyāsin&lt;/em&gt; (ascetic). All these subjects are not treated in any fixed or settled order in the {{sūtra|sūtra}} works. To take only one example, the subject of partition and inheritance occurs at the end of the {{dharmasūtra|dharmasūtra}} of Gautama, while Vasiṣṭha places the same subject in the middle of his work (17th chapter) and Āpastamba deals with those topics after finishing three-fourths of his work (in II. 6.14). Further, some works on {{dharmaśāstra|dharmaśāstra}} give very elaborate treatment of certain topics of which only faint traces are found in the ancient {{dharmasūtras|dharmasūtras}} and metrical {{smṛtis|smṛtis}}. Such topics are &lt;em&gt;vratas&lt;/em&gt; (which may be looked upon as extensions of the subject of gifts), &lt;em&gt;utsarga&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;pratiṣṭhā&lt;/em&gt; (dedication of works of public utility and of temples and shrines), &lt;em&gt;tīrtha&lt;/em&gt; (sacred places and pilgrimages to them), &lt;em&gt;kāla&lt;/em&gt; (auspicious times, festivals &amp;amp;c.).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Varṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/02_varNa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/02_varNa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER II&#xA;VARṆA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The number of works dealing with the origin and characteristics of the caste system in India is legion. Most of them, however, concern themselves with the detailed {{des cription|description}} of the bewildering variety of castes and subdivisions of castes in modern times and their present religious and social customs and usages. The origin of caste has given rise to great speculation and several schools of thought have arisen. Generally individual authors lay undue emphasis on one element or attach far too much importance to one point in tracing the origin of the caste system and its ramifications, such as race (Risley), tribe (Ibbetson), occupation (Nesfield). The study of the origin and development of caste in India is one of deep and absorbing interest to all students of sociology. A complete and critical examination of the several theories of caste advanced by distinguished authors and a detailed description of the hundreds of castes and {{suboastes|subcastes}} now found in India is far beyond the scope of the present work. For those who want to make a thorough study of the most important works on caste a modest list is given in the footnote below.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Duties and Privileges of Varṇas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/03_Duties_and_Privileges_of_varNas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/03_Duties_and_Privileges_of_varNas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER III&#xA;THE DUTIES, DISABILITIES AND PRIVILEGES OF THE VARṆAS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The duties and privileges of {{varṇas|varṇas}} occupy a very prominent place in all works on Dharmaśāstra. The study (of the Vedas), offering sacrifices and giving gifts are said to be the duties absolutely enjoined on the brāhmaṇa, kṣatriya and vaiśya,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; while each of these three varṇas has certain peculiar privileges, which are its principal means of livelihood. {{Teach iog|Teaching}} Vedas, officiating at sacrifices and receiving gifts—these are the privileges of brāhmaṇas; the profession of arms and protection of the people are the {{peouliar|peculiar}} privileges of kṣatriyas; agriculture, rearing cattle, trade and {{inoney-lending|money-lending}} are the peculiar privileges of vaiśyas. The first three viz. study, sacrifices and liberality are said to be the dharmas of all dvijas and the other actions such as teaching the Veda are said to be the vṛtti or {{jivikū|jīvikā}} (means of livelihood) of the dvijas. The consequence of this bifurcation is that if the first three are not performed or are {{negleoted|neglected}}, the person concerned was deemed to incur {{sia|sin}}, while a brāhmaṇa is not bound necessarily to earn his livelihood by all or any one of the three viz. teaching, officiating at a sacrifice or receiving gifts.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A few words on each of these duties and privileges must be said at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Untouchability</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/04_Untouchability/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/04_Untouchability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;chapter-iv&#34;&gt;CHAPTER IV&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;untouchability&#34;&gt;UNTOUCHABILITY&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Those who have written on the Indian caste system have always been struck by the fact of the existence of certain castes that are treated as untouchables. But it should not be supposed that this is something confined only to India. Even nations that have no caste system at all have often carried out complete segregation of certain people dwelling in their midst, which in essentials is the same as the system of untouchability in India. The Encyclopaedia of Social Sciences vol. XI. p. 339 says that in the southern States of {{U. S. A.|U.S.A.}} discrimination against Negroes took the form of residential segregation, separation of the races in public conveyances and places of amusement, exclusion of Negroes from public institutions and educational discrimination. Disenfranchisement and social discrimination had their {{economio|economic}} counterpart in all branches of industry except agriculture and domestic and personal service, occupations to which Negroes had been habituated under the slave regime.&amp;rsquo; It is also within living memory that Mahatma Gandhi had to lead a movement of satyāgraha in South Africa against the discriminating treatment of Indians and even now in Natal and other parts of British Africa there is legislation restricting Indians in the matter of residence and {{purchagos|purchases}} of land. [[166]]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Slavery</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/05_Slavery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/05_Slavery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Slavery has existed as a constant element in the social and economic life of all nations of antiquity such as Babylon, Egypt, Greece, Rome and also of many nations of Europe.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It was however left to such Christian nations of the West as England and the United States of America to carry on the institution of slavery in the most horrible manner possible never dreamt of by any nation of antiquity, viz. by sending out kidnapping expeditions to Africa to collect slaves, to huddle them in ships in such unspeakably filthy conditions that half of them died on the voyage, to sell them to plantation owners and others like chattel.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Samskāras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/06_samskAras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/06_samskAras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Gautama (II. 1) says that before {{upanayapa|upanayana}}, a boy may act, speak and eat as and what he likes (i. e. may follow his inclinations). Hāradatta explains that this does not mean that he can kill a {{brāhmana|brāhmaṇa}} or drink liquor, but that there is no restriction, although he be a {{brāhmana&amp;rsquo;s|brāhmaṇa&amp;rsquo;s}} son, to his selling what is forbidden to a {{brābmana|brāhmaṇa}} to sell, or he may eat onions and garlic or stale food or may eat four or five times a day. {{Ap. Dh. S.|Āp. Dh. S.}} (II. {{1. 6. 15. 17-20|6.15.17-20}}) states several views on this point. &amp;lsquo;Up to the time when they begin to take cooked food infants do not become impure (by the touch of a {{rajasvala &amp;amp;o.|rajasvalā, etc.}}); according to some (teachers) up till they are one year old; or till they are not able to distinguish the cardinal points; another view is that till {{upanayang|upanayana}} (they do not become impure)&amp;rsquo;. Aparārka (p. 28) also explains that a boy may (before {{upa nayana|upanayana}}) eat the leavings of the food of his parents, but he cannot eat or drink what would cause loss of caste as in that case he may become unfit to have the {{samskāra|saṃskāra}} of upanayana performed on him. The {{Sinrtyarthasāra|Smṛtyarthasāra}} gives the view of some that in case an infant touches a cāṇḍāla before it reaches the age of taking cooked food, only water need be sprinkled on it, before caula ācamana need be done by it and after caula (and before upanayana) a bath would be necessary. {{Vas. Dh. 8.|Vas. Dh. S.}} (II. 6) quotes a {{verge|verse}} of {{Harita|Hārīta}} to the effect &amp;lsquo;up till {{investi ture|investiture}} with the girdle of {{muõja|muñja}} grass (i. e. till upanayana) there is no action that is obligatory on him, as long as he is not born again for Vedic study he may be in his {{conduot|conduct}} like a {{sūdra|śūdra}}&amp;rsquo;.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This verse occurs also in {{Baud. Dh. S.|Baudh. Dh. S.}} I. 2. 6 and Manu II. 171 and 172. {{Daksa|Dakṣa}} I. 3-4 {{gays|says}} &amp;lsquo;Till a boy is eight years old he is like one newly born and only indicates the caste in which he is born. As long as his upanayana is not performed the [[189]] boy {{inours|incurs}} no blame as to what is allowed or forbidden to be eaten, as to what should (or should not) be drunk, as to what he should or should not speak, as to telling a falsehood&amp;rsquo;.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But this does not hold good as to {{mahāpatakas|mahāpātakas}}. As to {{prāya soitta|prāyaścitta}} when a child is guilty of the commission of a {{mah.. pātaka|mahāpātaka}}, {{sea|see}} under prāyaścitta later on and the Mit. on {{Yāj.|Yājñavalkya}} III. 253.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Upanayana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/07_Upanayana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/07_Upanayana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER VII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;UPANAYANA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This word literally means &amp;rsquo;leading or taking near&amp;rsquo;. But the important question is &amp;rsquo;near what&amp;rsquo;? It appears that it originally meant &amp;rsquo;taking near the {{ācārya|ācārya}}&amp;rsquo; (for instruction); it may have also meant &amp;lsquo;introducing the novice to the stage of student-hood&amp;rsquo;. Some of the {{gṛhyasūtras|gṛhyasūtras}} bring out this sense clearly e. g. the {{Hir. gṛ.|Hiraṇyakeśi-gṛ.}} I. 5. 2 &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; says &amp;ldquo;The teacher then makes the boy utter &amp;lsquo;I have come unto {{brahmacarya|brahmacarya}}. Lead me near (initiate me into it). Let me be a student,- impelled by the god {{Savitr|Savitṛ}}&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;. The {{Mānava|Mānava}} and {{Kāṭhaka gṛ.|Kāṭhaka-gṛ.}} (41.1) also use the word {{upāyana|upāyana}} for {{upanayana|upanayana}} and {{Ādityadarśana|Ādityadarśana}} on {{Kāṭhaka gṛ.|Kāṭhaka-gṛ.}} (41. 1) says that {{upānaya|upānaya}}, {{upanayana|upanayana}}, {{mauñjībandhana|mauñjībandhana}}, {{baṭukaraṇa|baṭukaraṇa}}, {{vratabandha|vratabandha}} are synonyms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Āśramas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/08_Ashramas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/08_Ashramas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the preceding pages several questions connected with brahmacarya have been dealt with. Brahmacarya is, according to the theory of the dharmasūtras and {{smśtis|smṛtis}}, the first of the four āśramas. Therefore, before proceeding to the next saṁskāra, viz. vivāha (marriage) which is the starting point of the second āśrama, it is necessary to discuss the origin and development of the idea of asramas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the times of the most ancient dharmasūtras the number of āśramas has been four, though there are slight differences in the nomenclature and in their sequence.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; {{Ap. Dh, 8. II. 9.21. 1|Āp. Dh. S. II. 9. 21. 1}} says &amp;rsquo;there are four āśramas, viz. the stage of householder, (staying in) the teacher&amp;rsquo;s house, stage of being a muni, the stage of being a forest dweller.&amp;rsquo; That here mauna stands for the āśrama of sannyāsa is clear from Āpastamba&amp;rsquo;s own words in II. 9. 21. 7 (atha parivrājaḥ) where he employs the word &amp;lsquo;parivrāj&amp;rsquo; to indicate&amp;rsquo; mauna, Āp. places the householder first among the {{āāramas|āśramas}}, probably on account of the importance of that stage to all other Āśramas. Why he should mention the stage of forest hermit last is not clear. Gaut. also (III, 2) enumerates the four āśramas as brahmacārī, gṛhastha, bhikṣu and vaikhānasa. Here also Gaut. speaks of bhikṣu before vaikhānasa and Haradatta&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; explains this departure from the usual sequence of āśramas as due to the words in Gaut. 28. 47 where we read &amp;lsquo;prāg-uttamāt traya {{āśramiñaḥ|āśramiṇaḥ}}&amp;rsquo; (persons belonging to the three āśramas except the last may constitute a pariṣad), i. e. to exclude vaikhānasa from the pariṣad he is mentioned last. Why the vānaprastha is called vaikhānasa will be discussed later on under the former word. {{Vas. Dh. 8.|Vas. Dh. S.}} (VII. 1-2) names the four āśramas as {{brahmaoāri|brahmacārī}}, gṛhastha, vānaprastha and parivrājaka.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 Marriage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/09_Marriage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/09_Marriage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER IX MARRIAGE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is the most {{inportant|important}} of all {{samskāres|samskāras}}. Throughout the ages for which literary tradition is available in India marriage has been highly thought of. The several words that are employed to denote the idea of marriage indicate one or more of the elements of the {{samskāra|samskāra}} of marriage. Such words are udvāha ( taking the girl out of her parental home ), vivāha ( taking the girl away in a special way or for a special purpose i. e. for making her one&amp;rsquo;s wife ), pariṇaya or pariṇayana (going round i. e. making a pradakṣiṇā to fire), upayama (to bring near and make one&amp;rsquo;s own), and {{panigrahana|pāṇigrahaṇa}} ( taking the hand of the girl). Though these words express only one component element of the rite of marriage they are all used in the {{sāstras|śāstras}}&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to indicate the totality of the several acts that go to make up the ceremony of marriage. The word &amp;lsquo;vivāha&amp;rsquo; occurs in the Tai. S. VII. 2. 87 and Ait. Br. (27.5). In the {{Tāṇdya|Tāṇḍya}}&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; {{Mahābrābmaṇa|Mahābrāhmaṇa}} VII. 10.1 it is said that &amp;ldquo;heaven and earth were once together but they became separate &amp;lsquo;; then they said let us bring about a marriage, let there be a {{co-ope ration|co-operation}} between us&amp;rsquo;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Madhuparka and Other Usages</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/10_Madhuparka_and_Other_Usages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/10_Madhuparka_and_Other_Usages/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[CHAPTER X MADHUPARKA AND OTHER USAGES|]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;madhuparka&#34;&gt;Madhuparka&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Madhuparka: ([[ offering|offering ]] of honey by way of honour to [[a|a]] distinguished guest). The word literally means &amp;lsquo;a ceremony in which honey is shed or poured&amp;rsquo; (on the hand of a person). The word occurs in the &lt;em&gt;Jaiminiya Upaniṣad-Brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I. 4. The &lt;em&gt;Nirukta&lt;/em&gt; ( I. 16 ) also refers to the usage of offering madhuparka with the word madhuparka repeated thrice. It appears that the &lt;em&gt;Ait. Br.&lt;/em&gt; III. 4 when it says that if the ruler of men comes as a guest or any one else deserving of honour comes, people kill a bull or a cow (that has contracted a habit of abortion)&amp;rsquo; refers to Madhuparka, &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; though that word is not actually used. In all [[gṛhyasūtras|gṛhyasūtras]] it is described at length. Most of the details are the same, the principal difference being that often different &lt;em&gt;mantras&lt;/em&gt; are prescribed, though [[some|some]] ( like the verse &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;mātā rudrāṇām&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo; ) are the same. The madhuparka &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is offered to [[ṛtviks|ṛtviks]] (priests officiating at sacrifices ) when they are chosen for a sacrifice, to a &lt;em&gt;snātaka&lt;/em&gt; who has come to one&amp;rsquo;s house, to the king ( who rules one&amp;rsquo;s country, when he comes to one&amp;rsquo;s house ), to one&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;ācārya&lt;/em&gt;, father-in-law, paternal and maternal uncles. The &lt;em&gt;Mānava [[gṛ.|gṛ.]]&lt;/em&gt; (I. 9. 1), &lt;em&gt;Khādira [[gṛ.|gṛ.]]&lt;/em&gt; IV. 4. 21, &lt;em&gt;Vāj.&lt;/em&gt; I. 110 say that six persons deserve &lt;em&gt;arghya&lt;/em&gt; (madhuparka ) viz. [[ṛtvik|ṛtvik]], &lt;em&gt;ācārya&lt;/em&gt;, the bride-groom, the king, the [[Snātaka|Snātaka]] and a person who is dear to one. Some like &lt;em&gt;Baud.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I. 2. 65 add &amp;lsquo;atithi&amp;rsquo; (guest ). Vide &lt;em&gt;Gaut.&lt;/em&gt; V. 25, &lt;em&gt;Ap. [[gṛ.|gṛ.]]&lt;/em&gt; 13. 19-20, &lt;em&gt;Ap. Dh. S.&lt;/em&gt; II. 3. 8. 5-6, &lt;em&gt;Baud. Dh. S.&lt;/em&gt; II. 8. 63-64,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 Rights and Duties on Marriage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/11_Rights_and_Duties_on_Marriage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/11_Rights_and_Duties_on_Marriage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[CHAPTER XI POLYGAMY, POLYANDRY AND RIGHTS &amp;amp; AND DUTIES ON MARRIAGE|]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;polygamy&#34;&gt;Polygamy&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Polygamy: Though monogamy [[127seems|seems]] to have been the ideal and was probably the rule, the Vedic literature is full of references to polygamy. &lt;em&gt;Ṛg.&lt;/em&gt; X. 145 (same as &lt;em&gt;Atharvaveda&lt;/em&gt; III. 18) is a hymn meant as a charm for [[weaning|weaning]] the husband&amp;rsquo;s affections from a co-wife. It occurs in the &lt;em&gt;Ap. M. P.&lt;/em&gt; (I. 15 ) and &lt;em&gt;Āp. Gṛ.&lt;/em&gt; IX. 6-8 prescribes it for winning over the husband to oneself and for causing estrangement between him and one&amp;rsquo;s co-wife. &lt;em&gt;Ṛg.&lt;/em&gt; X. [[1878 159|159]] is a hymn attributed to &lt;em&gt;Śacī&lt;/em&gt;, wife of &lt;em&gt;Indra&lt;/em&gt;, who claims to have vanquished and killed her co-wives and to rule supreme over &lt;em&gt;Indra&lt;/em&gt; and all men. This hymn also occurs in &lt;em&gt;Āp. M. P.&lt;/em&gt; (I. 16 ) and is prescribed by the &lt;em&gt;Ap. Gṛ.&lt;/em&gt; (IX. 9) as a charm always to be repeated by a wife for suppressing [[her|her]] co-wives. In [[a|a]] verse (&lt;em&gt;Ṛg.&lt;/em&gt; I. 105. 8) &lt;em&gt;Trita&lt;/em&gt; who had fallen into a well declares &amp;rsquo;the rib-like sides of the well) cause me pain all round as co-wives make it too hot ( for the husband or for themselves )&amp;rsquo;. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; [[1872The|The]] &lt;em&gt;Tai. S.&lt;/em&gt; (VI. 6. 4.3) gives a dogmatic and somewhat picturesque explanation of polygamy that &amp;lsquo;on one sacrificial post he passes round two girdles, so one man secures two wives; that he does not pass one girdle round two posts, so one wife does not obtain two husbands&amp;rsquo;. The &lt;em&gt;Ait. Br.&lt;/em&gt; (12. 11 ) similarly declares &amp;rsquo;therefore one man [[has|has]] many wives, but one wife has not many husbands at the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 Duties of Widows</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/12_Duties_of_Widows/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/12_Duties_of_Widows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-duties-of-a-widow-some-privileges-of-women-and-the-purdah-system&#34;&gt;The Duties of a Widow, Some Privileges of Women and the Purdah System&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vidhavādharmaḥ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So far the social position and the duties and rights of a wife during her husband&amp;rsquo;s [[life-time|lifetime]] have been considered. We shall now consider the rules laid down for a wife if she has the heavy misfortune to become a widow.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;vidhavā&lt;/em&gt; occurs several times in the [[.8.|e.g.,]] &lt;em&gt;Ṛgveda&lt;/em&gt; (e.g., IV.18.12, X.18.7, X.40.2 and 8); but these passages contain very little that is indicative of their condition in society except &lt;em&gt;Ṛs&lt;/em&gt;. X.40.2 (vide under &lt;em&gt;niyoga&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;em&gt;Ṛg&lt;/em&gt;. I.87.3 [&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;] says &amp;lsquo;in the rapid movements of the Maruts the earth trembles like a woman deprived of her husband,&amp;rsquo; That shows that widows trembled either from sorrow or from fear of molestation and ill-treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 Niyoga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/13_Niyoga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/13_Niyoga/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Niyoga (appointment of a wife or widow to procreate a son from intercourse with an appointed male). Great divergence of views prevails about the origin and purpose of this practice. It will be best first to begin by examining the most ancient [[smṛtis|smṛtis]] that permitted this practice. [[Gaut. 1407 18. 4-14|Gaut. 18. 4-14]] have great bearing on this point, Gaut. 18. 4-8 are: &amp;lsquo;[[A woman|&amp;amp; woman]] whose husband is dead and who desires offspring may [[secure|socure]] [[a son|&amp;amp; son]] from her brother-in-law. She should obtain the permission of the elders &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and have intercourse only during the menstrual period ([[excluding|exoluding]] the first four days). She may obtain a son from a [[sapiṇḍa|sapiṇda]], [[a|&amp;amp;]] [[sagotra|sagotra]], [[a|&amp;amp;]] [[sapravara|sapravara]] or one who belongs to the same caste (when there is no brother-in-law). Some (hold that this practice is allowed) with nobody except a brother-in-law. She shall not bear more than two sons (by this practice). Gaut. 18. 11 says that a child begotten at the request of a living husband on his wife belongs to the husband. Gaut. (28. 32) says that such a son is called [[kṣetraja|kṣetraja]]. The wife is called [[kṣetra|kṣetra]] &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (field), the husband of the wife or widow is called [[kṣetrin|kṣetrin]] or [[kṣetrika|kṣetrika]] (to whom the wife or widow belongs) and the person appointed to produce offspring is called [[bījin|bijin]] (one who [[sows|Bows]] the seed) or [[niyogin|niyogin]] (Vas. 17. 64, one who is appointed).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 Remarriage of Widows</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/14_Remarriage_of_Widows/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/14_Remarriage_of_Widows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;remarriage-of-widows&#34;&gt;Remarriage of widows&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;meaning-of-punarbhū&#34;&gt;Meaning of punarbhū&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;punarbhū&lt;/em&gt; is generally applied to a widow that has remarried. Before going into the detailed history of the remarriage of widows it is desirable to probe into the meaning of the word &amp;lsquo;punarbhū&amp;rsquo;. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Nārada (&lt;em&gt;Strīpuṁsa&lt;/em&gt;, v. 45) says that there are seven sorts of wives (mentioned in order) who have been previously married to another man (&lt;em&gt;para-pūrvā&lt;/em&gt;); among them, the &lt;em&gt;punarbhū&lt;/em&gt; is of three kinds &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;svairiṇī&lt;/em&gt; (wanton woman) is of four kinds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 Satī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/15_satI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/15_satI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;satī--self-immolation-of-widows-&#34;&gt;Satī ( Self-immolation of widows )&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word is often written as &amp;lsquo;suttee&amp;rsquo; in English works and papers. This subject is now of academic interest in India, since for over a hundred years (i.e., from 1829) self-immolation of widows has been prohibited by law in British India and has been [[deolared|declared]] to be a crime. A portion of sec. 1 of the Regulation XVII of 1829 passed by the Governor-General Lord William Bentinck is set out below. We are now in [[&amp;amp;|a]] position to take a dispassionate view of the practice, to trace its origin and follow its working down to the date of its being declared illegal. It is not possible in the space available here to go into all details. Those interested may read the latest book on the subject by Mr. Edward Thomson. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The burning&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 Veśyā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/16_veshyA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/16_veshyA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vesya&#34;&gt;Vesya&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[[P636]]&#xA;[[Vesya—(Courtezan)|Veśyā—(Courtesan)]]. This work dealing among other matters with the position of women and marriage in India would be incomplete if nothing were said about prostitutes and concubines. Prostitution has existed from the dawn of history in all countries and in the absence of statistics it is difficult to say whether it flourished more in one country than in another or whether it existed to a greater or lesser extent in ancient days as compared with modern times. The article in the [[Enoyolopædia Britannica|Encyclopædia Britannica]] on prostitution will be an eye-opener to many who will be inclined to turn their nose at Indian conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 Āhnika and Ācāra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/17_Ahnika_and_AchAra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/17_Ahnika_and_AchAra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XVII ĀHNIKA AND ACARA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Daily and periodical duties and ceremonies )&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This forms &amp;amp; very important topio of dharmasastra. The daily duties of the brahmacārin have been already desoribed above and those of the vānaprastha and yati will be spoken of later on. Under this section we are concerned principally with the duties of the snātaka (the would-be householder) and the grhastha ( the householder).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Before the āhnika duties are described a few remarks about the importance of the stage of householder would not be out of place. It has already been shown(pp. 424-425) how one school of dharmaśāstra writers represented by Gautama and Baudhayada looked upon the stage of householder as the only Aśrama. The eulogies of the housebolder are sung in numerous passages of the Dharmaśāstra works. Gaut, 1498 (III. 3) declares that the house holder is the source ( support ) of all the other aśramas, because the other three do not produce offspring. Manu (III. 77-78 ) states that as all creatures live by receiving support from the air, 80 other asramas subsist by relying for support on the housebolder and that as men belonging to all the three other orders ( aśramas) are supported from day to day by the house holder alone with (gifts of ) food and sacred knowledge, the housebolder&amp;rsquo;s is therefore the most excellent asrama. Manu (VI. 89-90 ) reiterates the same sentiments under a different figure just as all big and small rivers find a resting place in the ocean, so men of all aśramas find support in the householder and the householder is declared to be the most excellent of all the asramas by the precepts of the Veda and smrtis, sinoe be supports the other three&amp;rsquo;. Viṣṇu Dh. 8. (59. 27-29 ) contains almost the same remarks as Manu. Vide Vas. VIII. 14-16 ( 15 being identical with Manu VI. $0). Vas. VII. 17 (and X. $1 ), Baud. Dh. S. IL 2. 1, Udyogaparva 40. 25 say that a house holder observing the rules laid down for him does not fall&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 Pañca Mahāyajñas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/18_pancha_mahAyajnas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/18_pancha_mahAyajnas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XVIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PAÑCA MAHĀYAJÑAS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pañca Mahājajñas :-(the five daily great observances or sacrifices).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From early Vedic times five daily observances called mahāyajñas were presoribed. The Sat. Br. (XI. 5. 6. I.) 1864 says &amp;rsquo;there are only five mahāyajñas, they are like great sacrificial sessions, viz. the sacrifice to beings, the sacrifice to men, the sacrifice to the Fathers, the sacrifice to the gods, the sacrifice to brahman (Veda)&amp;rsquo;. These are then briefly defined. In the Tsi.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
