<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;04 Descriptive Studies on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;04 Descriptive Studies on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Newar Buddhist *Homa* Ritual Traditions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/01_Newar_Buddhist_Homa_Ritual_Traditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/01_Newar_Buddhist_Homa_Ritual_Traditions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Todd Lewis and Naresh Bajracharya&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;images&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition to the wealth of Sanskrit manuscripts from their private and monastic archives, which provided the textual foundations of modern Buddhist studies, the Newars of the Kathmandu Valley likewise perform a rich repertoire of rituals also originating in later Indic Buddhism. Among them are a large variety of &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; rituals done in a Buddhist modality, each with its specific details of performance and purposes. This chapter provides an overview of this Newar Buddhist tradition, including a complete outline of the ritual that was performed at Harvard (by the co-author of this chapter) at the outset of the “Homa Variations” conference at which a brief form of this paper was presented. It will first situate this central ritual tradition in the characteristically complex sociocultural matrix in which Newar Buddhism exists today,1 discuss the basic features of the many extant variants, describe the details of practice, and then conclude with observations of how modern Newar Buddhists conceptualize the Buddhist identity of their &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; practices.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 The *Navarātra Homa*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/02_The_Navartra_Homa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/02_The_Navartra_Homa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;LIVER, ENCHANTMENT, AND ENGENDERING THE DIVINE &lt;em&gt;ŚAKTI&lt;/em&gt;S&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nawaraj Chaulagaini&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;images&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This essay discusses the &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; rituals as performed during the annual &lt;em&gt;navarātra&lt;/em&gt; (literally, “nine-day festival,” also known as the &lt;em&gt;navadurgāpūjā&lt;/em&gt;) in the former Nepalese royal palaces of Gorkhā and Hanumānḍhokā during the rule of the Śāha kings (ca. 1559–2008). The &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; was part of a series of &lt;em&gt;navarātra&lt;/em&gt; rituals observed in the lunar fortnight of Āśvina (September–October).1 The rituals were carried out for the propitiation of the goddess Kālī, who is often portrayed in the violent and terrifying form of the goddess Durgā (consort of the god Śiva) and represented in various forms such as divine icons (images), plants, virgins, concentric magical/mystical diagrams (&lt;em&gt;yantra&lt;/em&gt;s), mantras, and weapons. This festival was observed in commemoration of the victory of the goddess over the demonic forces as recounted in popular mythological texts such as the &lt;em&gt;Devī Māhātmya&lt;/em&gt;, which forms part of the &lt;em&gt;Mārkaṇḍeya Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;Devī Bhāgavata Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;, and the *Kālikā Purāṇa.*2 With the conquest and expansion of the Nepali nation-state, especially in the latter half of the eighteenth century, the &lt;em&gt;navarātra&lt;/em&gt; was gradually made into a national festival and appropriated for the cultural unification of Nepal under the leadership of the Hindu kingship. Even after the demise of the Hindu kingship in 2008, the core forms of these rituals have persisted. However, the meaning of the rituals has shifted from its relation to the king and kingship to its importance for the welfare of the nation and national unity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Fire on the Mountain</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/03_Fire_on_the_Mountain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/03_Fire_on_the_Mountain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE SHUGENDŌ &lt;em&gt;SAITŌ GOMA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Richard K. Paynei&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;images&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Shugendō (種験道) is a religious tradition that centers on the practice of austerities in remote mountainous settings.1 Several mountains in Japan—Fuji, Omine, Haguro, for example—provided the ritual worlds in which various Shugendō confraternities practiced and served to define the different confraternities from one another. Contemporary practitioners (&lt;em&gt;shugenja&lt;/em&gt; 種験者, or &lt;em&gt;gyōja&lt;/em&gt; 行者, also popularly called &lt;em&gt;yamabushi&lt;/em&gt; 山伏) claim that its origins date back to the earliest history of Japan,2 and the tradition continues to play an important part in contemporary Japanese religious culture.3 Although it can be considered “indigenous” in the sense that it originated in Japan, over the course of its history Shugendō has been molded by other praxes, perhaps most particularly by esoteric Buddhism. Over the centuries Shugendō practitioners actively borrowed both conceptual and ritual elements from religious Daoism and esoteric Buddhism alike.4 One of its most dramatic rites, and one of the most easily recognized, is the &lt;em&gt;saitō goma&lt;/em&gt; (柴燈護摩),5 an outdoor ritual in which votive offerings are made into large bonfires, the fires having being ritually transformed into the bodies of the deities evoked. The &lt;em&gt;saitō goma&lt;/em&gt; exemplifies the appropriation and adaptation of esoteric Buddhist practice into Shugendō practice, and it provides a case study for an examination of the processes of ritual adaptation from one tradition into another.6&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 *Agnihotra* Rituals in Nepal</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/04_Agnihotra_Rituals_in_Nepal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/04_Agnihotra_Rituals_in_Nepal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Michael Witzeli&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;images/00015.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;images&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;TODAY FIVE GROUPS of brahmins reside in the Kathmandu Valley:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the Newari-speaking Rājopādhyāya; the Nepali-speaking Pūrbe, who immigrated in the last centuries before the Gorkha conquest (1768–1769 C.E.), the Kumaĩ; the Newari- and Maithili-speaking Maithila; and the Bhaṭṭas from South India, who serve at the Paśupatināth temple. Except for the Bhaṭṭas, all are followers of the &lt;em&gt;White Yajurveda&lt;/em&gt; in its Mādhyandina recension. It could therefore be expected that all these groups, with the exception of the Bhaṭṭas, would differ from each other in language and certain customs brought from their respective homelands, but that they would agree in their (Vedic) ritual. However, this is far from the case. On the contrary, the brahmins of the Kathmandu Valley, who have immigrated over the last 1,500 years in several waves,2 constitute a perfect example of individual regional developments in this border area of medieval Indian culture, as well as of the successive, if fluctuating, influence of the “great tradition” of Northern India.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
