<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 Antyeṣṭi, Āśauca, Śuddhi on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v4/2_antyeShTi_Ashaucha_shuddhi/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 Antyeṣṭi, Āśauca, Śuddhi on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v4/2_antyeShTi_Ashaucha_shuddhi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>07 Eschatology</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v4/2_antyeShTi_Ashaucha_shuddhi/07_Eschatology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v4/2_antyeShTi_Ashaucha_shuddhi/07_Eschatology/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER VII
ESCHATOLOGY
What happens after death to a human being (which is the subject matter of Eschatology) has been a great mystery that has intrigued and baffled mankind in all ages and was a question of vital importance among almost all ancient peoples such as the Indians, Egyptians, Chaldeans, Greeks and Persians. The word Eschatology is derived from a Greek term meaning &amp;rsquo;last things and is applied to the study of opinions that men have held from time to time concerning the future, including such matters as the state of man after life on this earth and the end of the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Śuddhi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v4/2_antyeShTi_Ashaucha_shuddhi/08_shuddhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v4/2_antyeShTi_Ashaucha_shuddhi/08_shuddhi/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER VIII
SUDDHI
Śuddhi (purification ) is a very comprehensive topic including within it purification after āśauca (impurity on birth and death), purification of a person after contact with an impure object or on account of certain occurrences. purification of pots, wells, food &amp;amp;c., after they are polluted. Aśauca, however, is the most important subject under śuddhi and therefore the Śuddhi.kaumudi &amp;lsquo;defines &amp;lsquo;śuddhi&amp;rsquo; as &amp;rsquo;the state of being fit for or capable of performing the rites that are understood from the Veda&amp;rsquo;1.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
