<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Occupation differences on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Occupation differences on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Archaka job</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/archaka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/archaka/</guid>
      <description>brAhmaNa-s Archaka-posts in certain Agamika temples were reserved for initiated brAhmaNa-s, due to such decision by a deity or a highly revered sage. Rare reservations were made for other communities as well (see practice page). Deities appointing specific lineages [sEkkizAr&amp;rsquo;s periyapurANam, mANikkavAcakar - TW17, kAmikAgama 6.6 - 6.9 TW17 ]. The vaikhAnasa samhitas mention that this community was created by Vishnu and not thru brahma. The child is initiated at the foetal stage through viShNu-bali.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kingship</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/kingship/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/kingship/</guid>
      <description> A kShatriya had maximal theoretical legitimacy for kingship. This led rulers to claim kShatriya status, and some brAhmaNa-s (like gAgAbhaTTa - see ministership page) to strive to make space for them within the dharmashAstra framework. In the absence of de-jure kShatriya-s, ability and heridity still brought maximal available legitimacy. Principles of proper governance very much applied to kings irrespective of varNa status. </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ministership</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/ministership/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/occupation/ministership/</guid>
      <description>General eligibility &amp;ldquo;mahAbhArata&amp;rsquo;s prescription (an ostensibly &amp;ldquo;brahmanical&amp;rdquo; source) placed in the mouth of the dying grandfather bhISma, as part of his lectures on statecraft, that a king should have 4 brAhmaNa &amp;amp; 4 shUdra ministers, 8 kSatriya ministers and 21 vaishya ministers. This may be due to the complexity of regulating various trades and crafts in an ncreasingly sophisticated society.&amp;rdquo; brAhmaNas serving shUdra kings Support &amp;ldquo;Kamalākarabhaṭṭa&amp;rsquo;s cousin Nilakaṇṭha, the author of Vyavahāra mayūkha explains the word nr̥pa &amp;ldquo;king&amp;rdquo; [ Vyavahāramayūkha, p.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
