<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/kauTilIyam/artha-shAstram/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/kauTilIyam/artha-shAstram/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Date</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/kauTilIyam/artha-shAstram/articles/date/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/kauTilIyam/artha-shAstram/articles/date/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/Saatvata/status/2013689138705207637&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is likely a layered text and some form of the text must&amp;rsquo;ve existed by the 2nd century AD (as evidenced by the Spitzer Manuscript), but the core text likely dates to the Śuṅga period.&#xA;Modern scholars have largely &amp;ldquo;discontinued any presumed connection between the Arthaśāstra and the Mauryan period.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;not-mauryan&#34;&gt;Not mauryan&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Arthaśāstra is most-likely NOT a Mauryan era text.&#xA;The terminus post quem for its composition is the Śuṅga era.&#xA;The author of the Arthaśāstra is familiar with silk, knows of settlements beyond Puṇḍravardhana like Suvarṇakuḍya (Sonkuriha in Assam, &amp;ldquo;sauvarṇakuḍyakaṃ raktapītaṃ mātuluṅgagandhi&amp;rdquo;) as well as a type of nutmeg (or jasmine?)-colored incense from beyond the Brahmaputra (bhadraśriyaṃ pāralauhityakaṃ jātīvarṇam).&#xA;Excavations at Ambari date back to the Śuṅga period, not the Mauryan period.&#xA;The author also knows of coral from Roman Alexandria or &amp;ldquo;Ālakanda&amp;rdquo; (pravālakam ālakandakaṃ vaivarṇikaṃ ca raktaṃ padmarāgaṃ ca karaṭagarbhiṇikāvarjam iti).&#xA;Direct sea trade between the Roman Egypt (centered on Alexandria) and peninsular India began only after Hippalus discovered the monsoon winds around ~100-50 BCE.&#xA;This is around the same time that Roman Red Sea ports (e.g. Berenike, Myos Hormos) emerge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
