<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1.1 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1.1 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Meaning of Dharma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/01_meaning_of_dharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/01_meaning_of_dharma/</guid>
      <description>Dharma is one of those Sanskrit words that defy all attempts at an exact rendering in English or any other tongue. That word has passed through several vicissitudes. The dictionaries set out various meanings of Dharma such as “ordinance, usage, duty, right, justice, morality, virtue, religion, good works, function or characteristic.&amp;quot; Dharma is also personified as a deity, as in the well-known verse. &amp;lsquo;Ādityacandrāvanilo’nalaśca&amp;hellip; dharmaśca jānāti narasya vṛttam&amp;rsquo;(Mahābhārata, Ādi., chap. 74.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Sources of Dharma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/02_sources_of_dharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/02_sources_of_dharma/</guid>
      <description>Sources of Dharma The Gautamadharmasūtra1 says &amp;rsquo;the Veda is the source of dharma and the tradition and practice of those that know it (the Veda).&amp;rsquo; So Āpastamba2 says &amp;rsquo;the authority (for the dharmas) is the consensus of those that know dharma and the Vedas.&amp;rsquo; Vide also the Vasiṣṭhadharmasūtra3 (I. 4-6). The Manusmṛti4 lays down five different sources of dharma &amp;rsquo;the whole Veda is (the foremost) source of dharma and (next) the tradition and the practice of those that know it (the Veda); and further the usages of virtuous men and self-satisfaction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Date of Dharmaśāstra works</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/03_date_of_dharmashAstra_works/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/03_date_of_dharmashAstra_works/</guid>
      <description>The important question is to find out when formal treatises on dharma began to be composed. It is not possible to give a definite answer to this question. The Nirukta (III. 4-5) shows that long before Yāska heated controversies had raged on various questions of inheritance, such as the exclusion of daughters by sons and the rights of the appointed daughter (putrikā). It is very likely that these discussions had found their way in formal works and were not merely confined to the meetings of the learned.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 The Dharmasūtras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/04_the_dharmasUtras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/04_the_dharmasUtras/</guid>
      <description>It seems that originally many, though not all, of the dharmasūtras formed part of the Kalpasūtras and were studied in distinct sūtrucaraṇas. Some of the extant dharmasūtras here and there show in unmistakable terms that they presuppose the Gṛhyasūtra of the caraṇa to which they belong. Compare Āp. Dh. S. I. 1. 4. 16 with Āp. Gṛ. S. I. 12 and II. 5; and Baud. Dh. S. II. 8. 20 with Baud.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 The Dharmasūtra of Gautama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/05_the_dharmasUtra_of_gautama/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/05_the_dharmasUtra_of_gautama/</guid>
      <description>This has been printed several times (there is Dr. Stenzler&amp;rsquo;s edition of 1876, the Calcutta edition of 1876, the Ānanadāśrama edition with the commentary of Haradatta, and the Mysore Government edition with the bhāṣya of Maskarin; it was translated by Būhler in S. B. E., Vol. II. with an introduction). The Anandāśrama edition of 1910 which is incorrect in a few places (e. g. 21.7) has been used in this work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 The Baudhāyana Dharmasūtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/06_the_baudhAyana_dharmasUtra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/06_the_baudhAyana_dharmasUtra/</guid>
      <description>06 The Baudhāyana Dharmasūtra
This has been edited several times (text by Dr. Hultzsch at Leipzig in 1884, text in the Ānandāśrama collection of smṛtis and in the Mysore Government Oriental Series in 1907 with the commentary of Govindasvāmin; translated in S. B. E., Vol. 14, with an Introduction). The Mysore edition has been used in this work. Baudhāyana is a teacher of the Kṛṣṇayajurveda. A complete set of the Baudhāyanasūtras has not yet been recovered and has not been as carefully preserved as the sūtras of Āpastamba and Hiraṇyakeśin.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Dharmasūtra of Āpastamba</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/07_dharmasUtra_of_Apastamba/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/07_dharmasUtra_of_Apastamba/</guid>
      <description>07 Dharmasūtra of Āpastamba
Dharmasutra of Āpastamba. This has been edited several times (viz. by Būhler in the Boinbay Sanskrit Series with large extracts from Haradatta&amp;rsquo;s commentary called Ujjvalā and also at Kumbhakonam with the complete commentary of Haradatta and translated by Būhler with an introduction in S. B. E. vol. II). The Apastan bakalpasūtra of the Taittiriya Sākhā of the black Yajurveda is divided into 30 pruśnas. According to Būhler, the first 24 praśnas contain the treatment of Srauta sacrifices; the 25th contains paribhūṣās, pravarakhanda, and Hautraka prayers to be recited by Hotr priests ; 26th and 27th praśnas constitute the Gșhyasūtra, the 28th and 29th Dharmasūtra and the 30th praśna is Sulvasūtra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Hiraṇyakeśi-Dharmasūtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/08_hiraNyakeshi-dharmasUtra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/08_hiraNyakeshi-dharmasUtra/</guid>
      <description>08 Hiraṇyakeśi-Dharmasūtra
The Hiraṇyakeśi-dharmasūtra forms the 26th and 27th praśnas of the Hiraṇyakeśi-kalpa. The Śrauta-sūtra has been published by the Ānandāśrama Press (Poona). The Hiraṇyakeśi-gṛhya-sūtra was edited with extracts from the commentary of Mātṛdatta by Dr. Kirsto (Vienna, 1889). The Gṛhya forms the 19th and 20th praśnas of the Kalpa, each praśna being divided into eight paṭalas. The Śrauta-sūtra is largely based on the Śrauta-sūtra of Āpastamba Tho Gṛhya-sūtra is indebted to the Gṛhya-sūtra of Bhāradvāja.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Vasiṣṭha-dharmasūtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/09_vasiShTha-dharmasUtra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/09_vasiShTha-dharmasUtra/</guid>
      <description>09 Vasiṣṭha-dharmasūtra
Vasistha-dharmasutra. This dlurmusutra has been printed several times. The collec tion of Jivanada (part II, pp. 456-496 ) contains only 20 chapters and a portion of the 21st and so does the collection of Mr. M. N. Dutt (Calcutta 1908). The Anandāśrama collection of sinītis ( 1905, pp. 187-231 ) and the edition of Dr. Fūhrer in the B. S. series (1916) contain thirty chapters. According to Dr. Jolly (R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Viṣṇudharmasūtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/10_viShNudharmasUtra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/10_viShNudharmasUtra/</guid>
      <description>Viṣṇudharmasutra. The Viṣṇudharmasūtra has been printed several times in India, viz. by Jivananda in his Dharmasastrasangraha (1876 part I pp. 70-176 ) by the Bengal Asiatic Society (1881, ed. by Dr. Jolly with extracts from the commentary Vaijayanti ), by M. N. Dutt (Dharmaśāstra texts, vol. II pp. 541-666, Calcutta, 1909) and translated by Dr. Jolly (in the S. B. E. vol. VII with an Introduction). In the present work Dr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 The Dharmasūtra of Hārīta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/11_the_dharmasUtra_of_hArIta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/11_the_dharmasUtra_of_hArIta/</guid>
      <description>11 The Dharmasūtra of Hārīta
The Dharmasutra of Harita That Hārīta was an ancient sūtrakāra on dharma is quite patent from the fact that the dhurmasitras of Baudhā. yana, Apastamba and Vasiṣtha quote him as an authority. 118 6.g. para 637 : JUTE potrafavaraanageTAAT aftage: fouse
वाचीति । ( Viṣṇu&amp;rsquo;s sutra seems to have been बीजग्रहणानुविधायमर्श
TERITE); para 719 375 HTEN: ( on fai&amp;rsquo;s FLE &amp;lsquo;foraya T na garnit pe ) que sentiafafa; pura 736 347 prae: भिनोदराणामिति निर्धारणे षष्ठी ( on विष्णु&amp;rsquo;सूत्र ‘भिन्नोदराणां संसृष्टिनी</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 The Dharmasūtra of Saṅkha-Likhita</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/12_the_dharmasUtra_of_sankha-likhita/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/12_the_dharmasUtra_of_sankha-likhita/</guid>
      <description>12 The Dharmasūtra of Saṅkha-Likhita
The Dharmasutra of Saṅkha-Likhita From the Tantravārtika we learn (note 55 above ) that the Dharmasūtra of Saṅkha-Likhita was specially studied by the Vājasaneyins ( the followers of the white Yajurveda ). The Tantravārtika also quotes a few words from thnt Dhar. masūtra which constitute an Anustubh pada.138 The Mahā bhārata ( in Sāntiparvan, chap. 23. 18-43 ) narrates the story of the two brothers, Saṅkha and Likhita, who resided in sepa rate dwellings surrounded by trees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 Mānavadharmasūtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/13_mAnavadharmasUtra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/13_mAnavadharmasUtra/</guid>
      <description>Mānavadharmasutra-Did it exist? 143
Mānavadharmasutra-Did it exist ? Following the orthodox view of Western Sanskrit scho lars that most of the dharinasūtras are older than almost all, if not all, the metrical smrtis, I gave the first place of honour to the dharmasutras of Gautama and others. But my own views differ to a great exteut from those of the orthodox school of Sanskritists represented by Max Mūller and Būhler.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14 The Arthaśāstra of Kauṭilya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/14_the_arthashAstra_of_kauTilya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/14_the_arthashAstra_of_kauTilya/</guid>
      <description>14 The Arthaśāstra of Kauṭilya
The Arthasastra of Kautilya There are three words in ancient Sanskrit Literature that are used very often in the same sepse viz. Arthasastra, Dandaniti and Rajasāstra or Rājaniti or Rājanitisāstra or simply Nitisāstra. The Mahābhārata descants on Rāja dharma in several parvans, as in Sabhā 5 ( the chapter called kaccit-praśna), Vanaparva 150, Uddyoga (chap. 33-34). In Sabbā 5 one hundred verses occur on Rājaniti; for example, ( verse 41 refers to 18 tirthas (state dignitaries) tested by spies (as in Kaut.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15 Vaikhānasa-dharma-praśna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/15_vaikhAnasa-dharma-prashna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/15_vaikhAnasa-dharma-prashna/</guid>
      <description>15 Vaikhānasa-dharma-praśna
Vaikhānasa-dharn-prasna 257
Vaikhānasa-dharma-prasna The work has been published in the Trivandrum Sanskrit Series by Pandit T. Gunapati Sastri (1913) and also edited by Dr. Caland in B. I. Series (1927) and translated into English ( 1929 ) with a learned Introiluction. Mahadeva in his commentary called Vaijayanti ( Anandā srama ed.) on the Satyasādha Franta sūtra speaks of six Srauta Sutras of the Black Yajurveda viz. Baudhāyana, Bharadvāja , Āpastamba, Hiranyakeśin, Vādhūla and Vaikhā nasa, and frequently cites passages from the Vaikhānasa srautasūtra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 Atri</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/16_atri/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/16_atri/</guid>
      <description>Atri That Atri was an ancient writer on hurma follows from &amp;amp; reference to him in Manu (III. 16 ) as holding the view that a crijati taking as wife a sūdra woman became fallen (patita). In the Deccan College collection there are several mss. ( Nos. 185-187 of A 1881-82 ) of the Atreyadharmaśāstra in nine adhyayas. They trent of gifts, prayers (japya ) and tupus by which men are free from all sins.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>17 Uśanas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/17_ushanas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/17_ushanas/</guid>
      <description>Usanas Kāvya Uśanas is an ancient sage in the Rgveda ; vide æg. I. 83. 5, where Kavya Uśanas is said to have been an helper of Indra and brought out the cows (carried away and concealed by the Panis). In Rg. VIII. 23. 17 that sage is said to have established Agni for Manu and in Rg IX. 87. 3 Uśanas is called a ṛsi and vipra and one who knew the hidden place where cows were concealed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18 Kaṇva and Kāṇva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/18_kaNva_and_kANva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/18_kaNva_and_kANva/</guid>
      <description>Karva and Kānva 273
Kanya and Kānva From the Ap. Dh. S. it appears that Kanva and Kāụva were two distinct writers on dharma. In I. 6. 19. 2 Āpastamba starts the question as to the persons, food at whose house was permitted. He states various views on that point and says that Kanya was of opinion that food may be taken at anybody&amp;rsquo;s house provided the latter offered it with a request (I.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>19 Kaśyapa and Kāśyapa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/19_kashyapa_and_kAshyapa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/19_kashyapa_and_kAshyapa/</guid>
      <description>Kasyapa and Kasyapa Baudhayana ( Dh. S. I. 11. 20) cites a verse which con tains the view of Kaśyapa that a woman who is bought can. not be a patnī and that she is not authorised to take part in religious ( daiva ) rites or rites for the Manes.254 This verse is ascribed to Katyayana in the Smrticandrika ( I. p. 87 ). The Vanaparva quotes gāthcs of Kāśyapa on forbearance ( 29.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>20 Gārgya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/20_gArgya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/20_gArgya/</guid>
      <description>Gārgya Viśvarūpa (on Yaj. I. 4-5) quotes a verse of Vṛddha Yājñavalkya in which Gārgya is enumerated among the expo unders of Dharma ( dharmavaktūraḥ). He quotes two sūtras, one from Gārgya ( on Yāj. I. 72260 ) and the other from Vṭddha Gārgya361 (on Yāj. I. 195). Therefore it seems that a sutra work of Gārgya on dharma did exist. The Mit. (e. g. on Yāj. III. 326 ), Aparārka and the Sinșticandrika quote several verses of Gārgya on õhnika, śrāddha and prāyascitta.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21 Cyavana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/21_chyavana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/21_chyavana/</guid>
      <description>Cyavana 277
The Anuśnsanaparva ( 18.38 ) states that Garga acquired on the banks of the Sarasvati astronomy with its 64 angas. In the same parure it is said that vrddha-Gārgya inquired about vrgotsarga ( 125. 77 ff). Salya parva ( 37. 14-15 ) narra tes that oli Garya by his tapis acquired on the sacred Sara svatī knowledge of Kāla, movements of the planets, of evil and good ut pātas and that the place is therefore called Gargasrotas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>22 Jātūkarṇya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/22_jAtUkarNya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/22_jAtUkarNya/</guid>
      <description>Jatukarnya Viśvarūpa (on Yāj. I. 4-5) quotes a verse of Vrudha Yājñavalkya in which Jātukarya is mentioned as an expounder of dharma.389 The name is variouly written as Jātūkarni or Jātākarnya or as Jatukarna. The Smyticandrikā quotes a passage from Angiras in which Jātūkarnya is enumerated among writers of Upasmrtis. Viśvarūpa quotes prose passages from Jātūkarnya a number of times.363 On Yāj. I. 1, he gives a sūtra about “pratilomas&amp;quot;; on Yāj.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>23 Devala</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/23_devala/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/23_devala/</guid>
      <description>Devala The name Devala as that of a sage frequently occurs in the Mahābhārata and is closely connected with Asita. Vide Sabhāparva 59. 9-11, Salya 50 and Sāntiparva 230. In Subhā ( 72. 5) it is stated that Devala declared that a man has three lights viz. son, actions and correct knowledge. In the Gita also (in X. 13 ) Arjuna says all the sages, the Devasși Nārada, Asita, Devala and Vyāsu speak of you as done in X.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>24 Paiṭhīnasi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/24_paiThInasi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/24_paiThInasi/</guid>
      <description>Paithinasi Though not enumerated in Yājsavalkya, Paithinasi seems to have been a comparatively ancient sūtrakāra on Dharma. On Yāj. III. 262 Viśvarūpa quotes a sutra of Paithinasi on the prāyaścitta for kiling a cow. Dr. Jolly (R. und $. p. 12 ) following Dr. Caland (&amp;ldquo;Ahnencult &amp;amp;c.&amp;rsquo; pp. 99, 109) thinks that Paithinasi belenys to the Atharvaveda as the prose quotations on frāddha agree with the ritual of the Atharvans.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>25 Budha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/25_budha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/25_budha/</guid>
      <description>Budha This sūtrakāra is not mentioned by Yāj. nor by Parāśara. He is very rarely cited. Aparārka on Yāj. I. 4-5, Kalpataru on Brahmacāri pp. 24, 78, 160, on Gr. Kanda p. 262, Naiyata K. p. 211 (quoted in Vira-mitrodaya, Paribhāsa p. 16), Hemādri.378 Jimūta-vābana&amp;rsquo;s Kāla viveka are probably the 478 खियो गृहदेवताः । तासां न शौचं न व्रतं नोपवासः । पतिशुश्रूषया गच्छान्त
परमां गतिम् ॥पैठी in व्यव० कल्प. p.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>26 Bṛhaspati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/26_bRhaspati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/26_bRhaspati/</guid>
      <description>Brhaspati That Bphaspati was an ancient teacher of Arthaśāstra follows from the Kauṭiliya, wherein the Bārhasratyas are cited six times. In the Mahabharata (Sinti. chap. 59. 80-85) Brhaspati is said to have compressed into 3000 chapters the work on dharma, artha and kāma composed by Brahma. The Vanaparva ( 32. 61) speaks of Brhaspati-niti. The Maha bhārata several times cites verses (yrithas or slokas ) said to have been sung by Brhaspatia80 ( vide Sinti.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>27 Bharadvāja and Bhāradvāja</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/27_bharadvAja_and_bhAradvAja/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/27_bharadvAja_and_bhAradvAja/</guid>
      <description>27 Bharadvāja and Bhāradvāja
Bharadvāja and Bharadvaja 291
observance of Sandhyā and the kindling of fire ;38? on Yāj. 1. 32 Bharadvāja is quoted as prescribing a penance for even thinking of causing harm to beings ; 388 on Yāj. I. 185 a lengthy sutra of Bharadvaja on the purification of certain things is quoted, wherein is cited the view of soine that boys are purified by a mere bath when touched by antyajas ; 289 on Yaj I.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>28 Śātātapa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/28_shAtAtapa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/28_shAtAtapa/</guid>
      <description>Satatapa Śatātapa is enumerated among the expounders of dharma by Yāj. (I. 4-5) and by Parasura. Viśvarūpa, Haradatta and Aparārka quote several proge passages of Śatātapa on prāyascitta. Viśvarūpa (on Yāj. III. 236 ) tells us that Śatātapa -spoke of only eight, upapatakas and that without dealing with śrāddha as a principal topic he spoke of some of the subsidiary details of srāddha.294 The latter passage quoted from Sātātāpa is a half verse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>29 Sumantu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/29_sumantu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/29_sumantu/</guid>
      <description>Sumantu For a Dharmasūtra of Sumantu vide Madras Tri. Cat. of Sanskrit M88. (1919-22 ) pp. 5160-62. From Viśvarūpa, Haradatta and Aparārka it follows that Sumantu composed a sūtra work on dharma, particularly on ācāra and prāyaścitta. Viśvarūpa quotes prose passages from Sumantu on upapātakas, 390 on prāyaścitta for Brāh mana-murder ( on Yāj. III. 237), for drinking wine ( on Yāj. III. 250 ), for theft of gold (on Yaj.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 The Smṛtis</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/30_the_smRtis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/30_the_smRtis/</guid>
      <description>The Smrtis 299
fine for selling and purchasing land without the consent of the neighbouriny members of the family and says that in case of pre-emption the neighbours on the east are preferred to all and those on the south come last. :02 Sunintu defines a mort gage by conditional sale (callel uktilihhakraya&amp;rsquo;) and a sale for arrears of revenue by the king&amp;rsquo;s orders (called ajna kraya ).303
Vide reconstruction of Sumanta by Prof.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>31 The Manusmṛti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/31_the_manusmRti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/31_the_manusmRti/</guid>
      <description>31. The Manusmṛti So many editions of this work have been published in India since 1813 ( when the Manusmṛti was first published at Calcutta ), that it is not possible to name them. In this work the Nirṇayasāgara edition with the commentary of Kullūka has been used throughout. Another edition of Manu well known on this side of India is that of the late V. N. Mandlik, who published several commentaries such as those of Medhātithi, Govindaraja and others.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>32 The Two Epics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/32_the_two_epics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/32_the_two_epics/</guid>
      <description>The Two Epics The two great Epics of India, the Mahābhārata and the Rāmāyaṇa, contain ( particularly the first) numerous passa ges bearing on meny topics of Dharmaśāstra and are relied upon as authorities in medieval and later works. The Mabu bhārata itself claims (in Adiparva, 2. 83) that VyDS composed the work as a great Dharmaśāstra, as Arthasastra ( treatise on politics and Government), Moksaśāstra and also POONA</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>33 The Purāṇas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/33_the_purANas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/33_the_purANas/</guid>
      <description>The Puranas The Yājṅavalkyasmști provides that Purāṇa, NMAYA (Tarkaśāstra ), Mimāṁsā, Dharmaśāstra, the ( six, subsidiary lores of the Veda (angas ) and the Vedas (four )-these fourteen FOUNDET
AL..datno
The Purāṇas 409
are the sources ( means) of Vidyo and of Dharma. It would be noticed that the 14 sources are arranged by Yājñavalkya in a rising scale of importance and authoritativene88.460 The word Purāṇa ( a class of works ) occurs in the Atharvaveda (XI.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>34 The Yājñavalkyasmṛti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/34_the_yAjnavalkyasmRti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/34_the_yAjnavalkyasmRti/</guid>
      <description>The Yājnavalkyasmrti This smrti has been published dozens of times. In the following the Nirnayasāgara edition edited by Sāstri Moghe ( 1892 A. D. ) has been used and the Trivandrum edition when speaking of Viśvarūpa. The name of Yājña valkya is one of the most illustrious among Vedic sayes. He is credited with having promulgated the White Yajurveda. In the Suntiparva (chap. 312 ) we are told that there was a rupture between Vaiśampāyana and his pupil Yājṅavalkya and that by worshipping the Sun the latter received the revelation of the White Yajurveda, the Satapatha etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>35 The Parāśara Smṛti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/35_the_parAshara_smRti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/35_the_parAshara_smRti/</guid>
      <description>The Parāsara Smrti This work has been published several times, but the edi. tion of Jivananda (part II. pp. 1-52 ) and that in the Bombay Sanskrit Series with the voluminous gloss of the great Mādhava are the best known. In the following pages Jika nanda&amp;rsquo;s edition has been used.
The smști of Parāśara must have been an ancient one as Yāj. (1.4 ) mentions him among the ancient writers on dha wim</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>36 The Nāradasmṛti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/36_the_nAradasmRti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/36_the_nAradasmRti/</guid>
      <description>The Nāradasmrti 467
The Naradasmrti There are two versions of Nārada on Vyavahāra, a smaller and a larger one. The smaller version was translated by Dr. Jolly in 1876 (Trūbner &amp;amp; Co., London ). The text of the longer version was published by the same scholar in the Bib liotheca Indica series (1885 ) and was translated by him in the Sacred Books of the East Series ( vol. 33).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>37 Bṛhaspati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/37_bRhaspati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/37_bRhaspati/</guid>
      <description>484
Brhaspati Brbaspati as a sūtra writer on politics has been dealt with above ( section 26 ). In this section Brhaspati the jurist will be spoken of. The complete smrti of Bșhaspati on law has not yet been discovered. It will be, when discovered, a very precious monument of ancient India, exhibiting the high water mark of Indian acumen in strictly legal principles and definitions. Dr. Fūbrer collected together 84 verses ascribed to Brhaspati in the legal treatises of Aparārka and others with German translation and notes ( Leipzig, 1879 ) and Dr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>38 Kātyāyana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/38_kAtyAyana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/38_kAtyAyana/</guid>
      <description>496
Katyayana Nārada, Bșhaspati and Kātyāyana form a triumvirate in the realm of the ancient Hindu Law and procedure. The work of Kātyāyana on Vyavahāra, like that of Bphaspati, has yet to be recovered. After the first volume of H. of Dh. was published in 1930, I contributed to a Law Journal in Bombay &amp;amp; collec tion of Kātyāyana&amp;rsquo;s verses gathered from quotations in 21 works and later (in 1933 ) published in a book form 973 verses of Kātyāyana with English translation, two Appendices and a General Index (in all 372 pages).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>39 Aṅgiras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/39_angiras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/39_angiras/</guid>
      <description>Angiras Angiras is one of the ten primordial sages mentioned in Manusmrti 1.34-35). It is &amp;amp; very ancient oame even in the Rgverle. On Yāj. I. 50 Viśvarūpa quotes a verge of Angiras that what is done according to one&amp;rsquo;s owo will without follow ing the dictates of Sāstra is fruitless.578 On Yaj. III. 248 Viśvarūpa says that the vrutie called Vajra wu8 prescribed by Angiras for Brāhmunas guilty of deadly sins.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>40 Ṛṣyaśṛṅga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/40_ShyashRnga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/40_ShyashRnga/</guid>
      <description>510
ilistory of Dharmaśāstra
Rsyasrnga This is a writer who is frequently quoted on ācāra, āśauca, srāddha, and prāyaścittu by the Mit., Aparārka, Smṛticand rikā and other works. A parārka (p. 724 ) quotes as Rsyas roga&amp;rsquo;s a verse ascribed to Sarkha in the Mitāksarā ( on Yāj. II. 119 ) and other works, which states that when one copar cener recovers with his own efforts family property that was lost to the family, he gets a fourth share of it and the others become sharers in the rest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>41 Kārṣṇājini</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/41_kArShNAjini/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/41_kArShNAjini/</guid>
      <description>Karsnajini This writer is quoted by the Mit. (YĀj. III. 265 three verses ), Aparārka, Smṛticandrikī and other works mostly op srāddha. A parārka (p. 138 ) quotes a verse from him which enumerates the seven sons of Bralmā, viz. Sanaka, Sanandana, Sanātana, Kapila, Asuri, Vodha (?) and Panca sikha. A parūrka (p. 424 ) quotes a verse of Kārsnājini which refers to the two signs of the Zodiac, Kanyā, and Vrścikā.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>42 Caturviṁśatimata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/42_chaturvishatimata/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/42_chaturvishatimata/</guid>
      <description>Caturvimsatimata There are two Mgs. of this work in the Bhandarkar Institute, Poona (No. 244 of A. 1881-1882 and 111 of 1895-1902). It contains 525 verses. The work is so called because it embodies the essence of the teachings of 24 sages, Manu, Yājña valkya, Atri, Viṣṇu, Vasistha, Vyāsa, Usanas, Apaskambe, 584 पूर्वनष्टा तु यो भूमिमेकश्येदुद्धरेत् क्रमात् । यथाशं तुं लभन्तेन्ये वाचशित a81494 11
FOUNDED
1917
Caturviñsatimata 511
Vatsa, Harita, Guru ( Brhaspati), Narada, Parāsara, Gautama, Yama, Baudhāyana, Daksa, Saikha, Aigiras, Śatātapa, Sārkhya (Sārkhyāyana?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>43 Dakṣa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/43_daxa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/43_daxa/</guid>
      <description>Daksa Dakṣa is one of the writers on dharma enumerated by Yāj. Vigvarūpa quotes verses of Daksa several times, viz. on Yāj. 1. 17 (on clods of earth for purifying the body ), on Yāj. III. 30 (two verses on āśauca ), on Yāj. III. 66 ( about &amp;amp; parivrājaka ), on Yāj. III. 191 (about padmāsada ). The Mit. (on Yāj. I. 89) quotes a half verse of Daksa to the effect that a dvija should not remain unattached to an asrama (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>44 Pitāmaha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/44_pitAmaha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/44_pitAmaha/</guid>
      <description>Pitāmaha Pitāmaba is enumerated among writers on dharma in a verse of Vṛddha-Yājsavalkya quoted by Viśvarūpa. The Smrti of Pitāmaha (part I p. 10) is drawn upon mostly on Vyavabāra. Viśvarūpa cites (on Yaj. I. 17 ) &amp;amp; verse from him on sauca.603 The Mitākṣarā and Aparārka respective ly quote about 45 and 75 verses from Pitāmaba only on Vyavabāra and specially on ordeals and the Kalpataru on Vyavahāra quotes about 90 verses on the same topics from Pitāmaha.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>45 Pulastya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/45_pulastya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/45_pulastya/</guid>
      <description>Pulastya Pulastya&amp;rsquo;s name is among the ten primordial sages men tioned in the Manusmrti I. 34&amp;ndash;35. Pulastya is one of the expounders of dharma enumerated by Vrddha-Yājñavalkya. Viśvarūpa quotes a verse from him on sārīraśauca.604 The Mit. (on Yāj. I. 261 ) cites &amp;amp; verse from Pulastya that a Brāhmaṇa should principally use asce tic&amp;rsquo;s food (i. e. vegetable food ) in srāddha, that ksatriyas and vaisyas should use meat and būdras madhu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>46 Paiṭhīnasi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/46_paiThInasi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/46_paiThInasi/</guid>
      <description>Paithīnasi Paithīnasi, though not named among the Smṛtikāras enu merated in Yāj. I. 4-5, is mentioned among the 36 Smṛtis quoted by Aparārka (p. 7) from the Bhaviṣyapurāua and also in the quotation from Paithinasi about the thirty-six names of the expounders of Dharmaśāstra in the Smiṣti-Candrikā (p. 1). Another reason is that he appears to have dealt in his work with all three branches of Dharmaśāstra, viz. ācāra, vyavahāra and prayascitta.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>47 Pracetas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/47_prachetas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/47_prachetas/</guid>
      <description>Pracetas Pracetas fiuds a place among the sages enumerated by Perāsara (though not in Yājñavalkya), in the list of 36 Smrti kāras by Paithināsi in Smṛticandrikā p. 1). In both Mit. and Aparārka there are passages in prose and verse ascribed to Pracetas on daily duties, srāddha, āśauca, prāyascitta. The Mit. (on Yāj. III. 27 ) quotes &amp;amp; verse from Pracetas saying that workmen, artisans, physicians, male and female slaves, kings, royal officers have not to observe periods of impurity 811 (on death).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>48 Prajāpati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/48_prajApati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/48_prajApati/</guid>
      <description>Prajapati Prajāpati is cited as an authority by the Baudhāyana dharinasūtra (II. 4. 15 and II. 10. 71 ). Vasistha several times quotes Prājāpatya blokas (viz. III. 47, XIV. 16-19, 24-27, 30-32). It has been shown above that most of these Verses are found in the Manusmrti or have close correspon dence with verses of Manu. So it is not unlikely that both the writers of dharmasūtras mean Manu by Prajāpati.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>49 Marīci</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/49_marIchi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/49_marIchi/</guid>
      <description>Marici The name Marici is very ancient. In Manusmṛti II. 34-35 Marici is mentioned first among the ten Prajāpatis.
This sage is relied upon as an authority by the Mit., Aparārka, Smrticandrika on Ahnika, Asauca, Sraddha, Prāyascitta and Vyavahāra. Aparārka quotes several verses on
है आपके
813 मातामहस्य गोत्रेण मातुः पिण्डोदकक्रियाम् । कुर्वीत पुत्रिकापुत्र एवमाह
प्रजापतिः ॥ अपरार्क. 814 साक्षी विभेदो विज्ञेयः कृत एकोऽपरोऽकृतः । लेख्यारूढः कृतो ज्ञेयः मुक्तकोऽ.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>50 Yama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/50_yama/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/50_yama/</guid>
      <description>Yama The Vasistha-dharmasutra (18. 13-15 and 19. 48 ) cites four slokas of Yama and quotes (11. 20 ) one verse in which Yama is spoken of as an authority. All the slokas except one
818 सप्तम्यां रविवारे च गृही जन्मदिने तथा । भृत्यपुत्रकलत्रार्थी न कुर्यात्तिल
atunt il 34727* p, 132 ; ffaao ( 341 p. 123 ). 619 TDAH perfish tat hal peat: larg Fri 7 gata sararaan</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>51 Laugākṣi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/51_laugAxi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/51_laugAxi/</guid>
      <description>Laugaksi Laugākṣi is mentioned among the 36 expounders of Dharmaśāstra set out by Paithīnasi (on p. 1 of Smṛ. Ch.) and Angiras quoted on the same page includes Laugākṣi among Upasmṛtis.
The Mit. (on Yāj. III, 1-2, 260, 289 ) quotes verses of Laugāksi on āśauca and prāyascitta. Aparārka quotes nine proge passages (pp. 28–29, 33, 122, 145, 166, 176 and 530) on Ācāra including Srāddha and ten verses on ten pages on Acāra, Āśauca and the order of forest hermits and one very long prose passage on p.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>52 Viśvāmitra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/52_vishvAmitra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/52_vishvAmitra/</guid>
      <description>Viśvamitra Vievāmitra is one of the writers on dharma enumerated by Vrddha-Yājījavalkya as quoted by Viśvarūpa. Aparārka, the Smṛticandrikā, the Kālaviveka of Jimūtavāhana and other works quote verses of Viśvāmitra on almost all topics of dharma except vyavahāra, such as on the five deadly sins, on srāddhas, prāyaścitta etc. Viśvāmitra defines dharma as that which is esteemed by Aryas ( respectable people who know the Vedas. 640 Aparārka quotes 18 verses from Visvā.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>53 Vyāsa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/53_vyAsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/53_vyAsa/</guid>
      <description>Vyāsa In Jivananda (part II, pp. 321-342 ) and in the Anandā srama collection of smṛtis there is a smrti ascribed to Vyasa (pp. 357-371 ). The two texts are the same with a few variations. It is in four chapters and contains about 250 verses. Vyāsa is said to have declared the Smrti in Benares. 640 यमार्याः क्रियमाणं तु शंसन्त्यागमवेदिनः । स धर्मों यं विगर्हन्ति तमधर्म
Tad il pictato ( 1T1 p.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>54 Ṣaṭ-triṁśan-mata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/54_aT-trishan-mata/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/54_aT-trishan-mata/</guid>
      <description>54 Ṣaṭ-triṁśan-mata
Sat-trimsan-mata The title literally means &amp;rsquo;the doctrines of thirty-six (Smṛtis )&amp;rsquo;. This appears to have been a work like the Catur vimśatimata. It has been stated above that Paithinasi enumerated thirtysix propounders of Dharma (vide Smrtican drikā p. 1). Quotations from Șat-trimsan-mata cited in the 653 पलान्यष्टौ सुवर्णस्य सुवर्णाश्च चतुर्दश । एतनिष्कप्रमाणं तु व्यासेन परिकीर्तितम् ॥
quoted by plago (jo ) p. 99, 97. AT. ( 200 ) p.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>55 Saṁgraha or Smṛtisaṁgraha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/55_saMgraha_or_smRtisagraha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/55_saMgraha_or_smRtisagraha/</guid>
      <description>55 Saṁgraha or Smṛtisaṁgraha
Samgraha or Smrtisamgraha This work is frequently cited by the Mitākṣarā, Aparārka, the Smṛticandrikā and other works on all topics of dharma, The quotations on vyavahāra are copious and are very im 659
657 तिलहोमायुतं चैव पराकद्वयमेव च । गायत्र्या लक्षमेकं च समान्याह बृहस्पतिः॥
अपरार्क p. 1249. 658 समुच्छिष्टस्तु यो भुङ्क्ते मुद्दे वा मुक्त भोजनः । एवं वैवस्वतः प्राह भुक्त्वा
सान्तपनं चरेत् ॥ अपराके p. 1174. प्रामाण्यमेव ये वेदे न वदन्ति कुदृष्टयः । तेषां बौद्धार्हतादीनां पाषण्डाख्या प्रकीर्त्यते ॥ प्रव्रज्य वसिता (प्रवज्यावसिता) ये तु पाषण्डास्ते प्रकीर्तिताः। पौरुषेयतया वेदं (वेदे?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>56 Saṁvarta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/56_savarta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/56_savarta/</guid>
      <description>Samvarta Saṁvarta occurs as a Smrtikāra in the list of Yājña valkya. He is cited on all topics of dharma by Viśvarūpa, Medhātithi, the Mit., Haradatta, Aparirka, the Smṛticandrikā and a host of other writers. Viśvarūpa quotes either wholly or in part about twenty verses of Samvarta on evening sandhyā vandana, on the duties of a yuti and on the prāyaścittas for theft, adultery of various kinds, deadly sius. Medhātithi quotes verses of Surivarta on Manu V.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>57 Hārīta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/57_hArIta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/57_hArIta/</guid>
      <description>Harīta The verse quotations from Hārīta on topics of vyavahāra deserve some treatment. He defines vyavahāra as that where by the recovery of one&amp;rsquo;s own wealth and the avoidance of (doing ) the duties peculiar to another (caste or class ) are effected in due course of law.878 He further says that that judicial proceeding is proper which is based on the dictates of dharmaśāstra and arthasāstra, which is in conformity with the usages of respectable people and which is free from fraud.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>58 Commentaries and Nibandhas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/58_commentaries_and_nibandhas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/58_commentaries_and_nibandhas/</guid>
      <description>58 Commentaries and Nibandhas
Commentaries and Nibandhas ( digests ) The literature on Dharmaśāstra falls into three well marked but somewhat over-lapping periods. The first period is that of the ancient dharmasūtras and of the Manusmrti. It is a period dating from at least the 6th century B. C. to the beginnings of the Christian era. Next comes the period when most of the versified smrtis were composed and it ranges from the first centuries of the Christian era to about 800 A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>59 Asahāya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/59_asahAya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/59_asahAya/</guid>
      <description>Asahāya Dr. Jolly in his edition of the Nāradasmrti (B. I. series ) bas incorporated a portion of the bhāsya of Asahāya as re vised by Kalyānabhatta. Even this revised version comes up to only verse 21 of the fifth title abhyupetya-asuśrūṣā. The exact relation of Kalyānabhatta&amp;rsquo;s labours to the original bhāsya cannot be accurately gauged from the opening888 words &amp;rsquo; finding that the Nāradathāsya composed by Asahāya was spoilt (bhrasta ) by bad scribes, Kalyāṇa composes this after revising the ancient one&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>60 Bhartṛyajña</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/60_bhartRyajna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/60_bhartRyajna/</guid>
      <description>| āo. Bharteyajĩa This seems to have been a very ancient commentator. Medhātithiros in his bhāsya on Manu 8. 3 says &amp;lsquo;other explana tions have been well brought out by Bhartļyajña and they should be understood from his work&amp;rsquo;. Trikānda-mandana (who flourished before 1100 A. D.) in his Āpastambasūtra dhvanitārtha-kāriki708 (I. 41) refers to the views of Bhartr yajña that one who had committed to memory the text of the Veda had the privilege ( the adhikāra ) of consecrating the sacred fires, though he may be innocent of the meaning of the Vedic texts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>61 Viśvarūpa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/61_vishvarUpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/61_vishvarUpa/</guid>
      <description>Viśvarupa The commentary of Viśvarūpia called Bālakrīdā on the Yājsavalkya-smrti has been recently published in two parts by M. M. T. Ganapati Sāstri in the Trivandrum Sanskrit Series. The Mit. states in the introductory verses that the dicta of Yij. were expanded by the voluminous or ample (vikata ) explanations of Viśvarūsra. In commenting on Yāj. 1. 81 the Mit. tells us that Viśvarūjia looked upon the words of Yāj.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>62 Bhāruci</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/62_bhAruchi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/62_bhAruchi/</guid>
      <description>Bhāruci The Mit. on Yij. (I. 81) says that Bhiruci like Viśvaripa held the view that the rulertau bhūryam gacchet&amp;rsquo; was a niyanma and not a paristkrinkhayti. On Yij. II 124 the Mit. says that the explanation of&amp;rsquo; the fourth share&amp;rsquo; to be given to un married sisters oflered by Asahiya and Medhitithi was the 732 अत एवोक्तं श्राद्धकलिकायां-मासिकानि सपिण्डं च अमावास्या तथाब्दिकम् ।
अन्नेनैव तु कर्तव्यं यस्य भाया रजस्वला ॥ इति । अनेनैव कर्तव्यं न त्वामान्नादिनेति च कलिकाविवरणेपि श्रीमद्विश्वरूपाचार्यव्याख्यानम् । Ms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>63 Śrīkara</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/63_shrIkara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/63_shrIkara/</guid>
      <description>Srikara The Mit. on Yāj. II. 135 alludes to the view of Srikara and others that the widow succeeded is heir to her deceased husband&amp;rsquo;s estate if it was small.743 The Smytisāra744 of Harinātha attributes the same view to Srikara and disappro ves of it. On Yāj. II. 169 the Mit.746 cites the view of Srikara about that topic and disapproves of it. Viśvarūpa also gives two explanations of that verse of Yāj.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>64 Medhātithi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/64_medhAtithi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p1/64_medhAtithi/</guid>
      <description>Medhātithi Medhātithi is the author of an extensive and erudite commentary ( bhusyu ) on the Manusmrti. It is the oldest extant commentary on that smrti. The bhāsya of Medhātithi was first published about forty years ago by Rao Saheb V. N. Mandlik in Bombay and recently Mr. J. R. Gharpure of Bombay brought out an edition of Medhātithi which closely follows Mandlik&amp;rsquo;s edition. A critical edition of the bhāsya based upon all the available Msg.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
