<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;shUdra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;shUdra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Occupation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/occupation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/occupation/</guid>
      <description>He was encouraged to serve a dvija for livelihood; but this was not a compulsion. Attenuation: There was always the widely used āpad-dharma loophole that enabled him to do something else (essentially the occupation of a vaiśya or a kṣatriya) if he thought that the former occupation cannot meet his needs, or if the country was in disarray. So, ultimately only the occupations of a vedic brāhmaṇa were barred to him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privileges</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/privileges/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/privileges/</guid>
      <description>Intro Fewer ritual demands. Almost no food or drink restrictions. No gotra/ pravara based marriage restrictions, since in most cases they wouldn’t even be known. Pursuit of nearly any occupation (we’ll dwell on the few restrictions later). Little or no penance for deviating from the śāstra. In contrast, dvija-s (especially brāhmaṇa-s) had a great many restrictions placed on them with regard to rituals, daily practice (ācāra), livelihood, education and food. For example, a brāhmaṇa was barred from accumulating wealth, was required to perform numerous lengthy rituals daily and seasonally, spend a decade or more learning the veda-s and its limbs, restrict his dietary options and abstain from most spirits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social status</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/social_status/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/shUdra/social_status/</guid>
      <description>Legal disabilities Higher punishment for certain offences. For example: Adultery with a dvija woman, slander against a dvija. Attenuation: In several cases, a person of a higher varṇa was subject to greater prāyaścitta and daṇḍa. For example, Manu and Gautama require that a brāhmaṇa, a kṣatriya and a vaiśya would respectively be fined eight, four and two times more respectively than a śūdra. Kātyāyana and Vyāsa make this principle a general rule for all offences.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
