<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Delusions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-12_delusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-12_delusions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/01/12/delusions/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is fashionable these days for some parents to describe their&#xA;daughters by the following terms:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Modern 2) Forward 3) City-type 4) Progressive 5) Modern but Indian.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Modern but Spiritual. The simple message is that one must be beware&#xA;of such women- they are verily living graveyards for the deluded.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Hindu youth have been deluded in many ways by the waves of mlecchaic&#xA;subversion lashing the Indian shores. These are affecting both the sexes&#xA;in drastic ways but in the case of daughters often Hindu parents live a&#xA;disconnected world of their own making, much as chAchA Nehru imagined&#xA;that he was the center of the world. These deluded Hindu youth are&#xA;characterized by the following fancies: 1) In movies they watch entire&#xA;lives compressed into 1-3 hr capsules. Every emotion is intense and&#xA;instant. Sex happens right away, sexual romance is instant, heroes and&#xA;heroines achieve their goals in that brief span of the movie. As a&#xA;result the youthful watcher believes in instant gratification.&#xA;Everything he or she wants should come immediately or else they will&#xA;throw tantrums. 2) They are much richer than the older generation, so&#xA;they lose track of the value of money and are willing to spend it on&#xA;vices. 3)Macho Moslem men and handsome men and women are projected as&#xA;their ideals. So they strive to emulate these, in the process losing&#xA;their own sense of identity and also get secularized. 4) Their peer&#xA;pressure guilds prevent them from doing anything profound and drive them&#xA;to wallow in shallow thoughts, cheap entertainment and low-grade humor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marriage according to agni-vivAha smR^iti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/MT_lekhAH/2003-07-29_marriage-according-to-agni-vivaha-smriti/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/MT_lekhAH/2003-07-29_marriage-according-to-agni-vivaha-smriti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2003/07/29/marriage-according-to-agni-vivaha-smriti/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While there are reams of writings on the yeses and nos of Hindu marriage there is a short sanskrit tract called the agni-vivAha smR^iti that provides its somewhat atypical account of the same. The text is attributed to a certain puShkara and contains 19 verses. The tract may be dated to approximately to the period of the first 6 centuries of the common era. I examined it because it throws interesting light on old Indian customs. Below are some excerpts:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
