<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Chidambaram sc judgement</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/chidambaram-sc-judgement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/chidambaram-sc-judgement/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Ten year ago on this day - 06th Janauary 2014 - One of the finest judgments concerning Hindu Communities&amp;rsquo; fundamental rights to administer and maintain their temples was delivered by Hon&amp;rsquo;ble Justice B.S. Chauhan and Hon&amp;rsquo;ble Justice S.A. Bobde in Hon&amp;rsquo;ble Supreme Court of India. The judgment while established or rather re-established the fundamental religious and administrative rights of the ancient community of Podhu Dikshitars of Chidambaram Sri Nataraja Temple - also enunciated when, if at all, a Hindu Temple&amp;rsquo;s administration can be taken over and for how long.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goa temples</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/goa-temples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/goa-temples/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Temples of Goa – A Case Study of Privately Run Temples
We keep hearing how Hindu temples should not be freed and State should keep controlling them. They are motivated by ignorance and desire to justify all State actions.
They are wrong. Here is how.
Private run temples are much better run than govt. controlled temples. Goan temples are case in point. Anyone who has been to Goan temples knows this truth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ks varadAchArya on antiquity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/ks-varadAchArya_on_antiquity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/ks-varadAchArya_on_antiquity/</guid>
      <description>(From : kAshyapa-kRShNa)
Alwar swamin said KSV had talked about this. He said there is not much proof about any temple before 2000 years back. Even the sthala puranas of each older temple like ranganatha temple and even melkote as being there for yugas, are mainly to enhance faith in people and not historical. Even the ramayana and any other reference are weak references to state that temple culture was so ancient.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mlechChAdi entry consequences</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/mlechChAdi-entry-consequences/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/mlechChAdi-entry-consequences/</guid>
      <description>SHOULD NON-HINDUS THE BE ALLOWED TO ENTER TEMPLES?
SCRIPTURAL PERSPECTIVE
Source: TW
Entry of Mlechhas and Anti Vedics in a temple is an insult to the other devotees, if they enter the temple then the temple must be purified by the rite of Samprokshanam.
PARAMAPURUSHA SAMHITA 7.28-30
Those born out of anuloma marriage and the mlechhas, they must worship Hari standing outside the Gopura.
BHRIGU SAMHITA 36.11
If a turk touches the vigraha or enters the mandapa hall, the temple should be purified with the methods described prior.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Olivelle post 5th ce</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/olivelle_post_5th_ce/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/olivelle_post_5th_ce/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
When did large Hindu temples come into being? Not before 500 AD
Dharmashastras opposed temple-based religious and ritual activities. Vishnu Smriti says that Vedic recitation shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be conducted &amp;lsquo;in a temple, in a cemetery, at a crossroads, or on a road.&amp;rsquo;
Patrick Olivelle
17 January, 2024
I would like to do a little thought experiment today. Imagine taking a trip to India a century or so before the Common Era using, thanks to AI, the recently discovered technology of time travel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TN Temple control</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/TN-temple-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/TN-temple-control/</guid>
      <description>Source: Sreedharan K S (@SreedharanKs)
In this interview @RangarajPandeyR asked @jsaideepak why Justice Party wanted Govt Control of Temples, as they were the rich people administering temples. Here is some history.
In early 19th century EIC had nominal control over temples, till it relinquished in 1863 by Act XX. The temples became one of the power centres. Where there was no Zamindar, Pandarasandhi, rich and powerful people got themselves associated with temples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unseen temples</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/unseen_temples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/temple/articles/unseen_temples/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Unseen Temples of India – Legacy and Narrative – Part 1
Building a separate structure to house murtis, carriers of divinity, for personal and public worship of deities is an old tradition prevalent in India. Manisha Chitale takes us through the history and evolution of temple architecture in the country and how temples have shaped the Sanatana dharmik civilisation.
March 16, 2023
By: Manisha Chitale
Sanchi in Madhya Pradesh has an important landmark, printed on our currency notes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
