<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;3 Sadācāra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/3_sadAchAra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;3 Sadācāra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/3_sadAchAra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>32 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/3_sadAchAra/32_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/3_sadAchAra/32_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXXII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SADACARA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CUSTOMS AND MODERN CUSTOMARY LAW1606&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From Gautama 1606 downwards many writers dilate upon the sources of dharma. Gautama. I. 1-2 states: &amp;rsquo; the Veda is the source ( mula) of dharma and also the tradition (or smṛtis ) and practice of those who know the Veda&amp;rsquo;. Similarly Ap. Dh. S. (I. 1. 1.1-%) says: &amp;lsquo;we shall propound the acts (that produce merit) which are evolved from conventions and practices; the authority ( for finding out the dharmas) are the conventions of those who know the dharma and the Vedas&amp;rsquo;. Vas. I. 4-7 pro vides: &amp;lsquo;dharma is declared by the Vedas and Smptis; on failure of these two the practice of the sistas is the authority (for finding out what dharma is); a sista however is one whose heart is free from (worldly ) desires and (only ) such acts of sigtas are ( to be held as ) dharma for which no ( worldly&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33 Customs and Dharmaśāstra Works</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/3_sadAchAra/33_Customs_and_dharmashAstra_Works/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/3_sadAchAra/33_Customs_and_dharmashAstra_Works/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXXIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CUSTOMS AND DHARMASASTRA WORKS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is now necessary to see how Dharmaśāstra works have dealt with the authority and binding force of customs and usages. Sadācāra is defined by Harita as follows 1657:- the word &amp;lsquo;sat&amp;rsquo; means &amp;lsquo;good&amp;rsquo; and the good are those who are free from (inoral) taint; the practices of such people are called sadācāra. Vide Manu II. 18, which also defines sadācāra. Even the most ancient sūtras testify to the fact that numerous customs and usages had arisen in different countries and vil lages. The Aśv. gr. (1. 7.1-2) says, 1658 various indeed are the observances of ( different ) countries and villages; one should follow those in marriages; what, however, is common (to all or most ) shall be declared by us&amp;rsquo;. The Ap. gr. (II. 15) declares, * people should understand from women what procedure is to be observed (according to custom)&amp;rsquo; and the Ap. Dh. S. provides (1. 7. 20. 8 = II. 11. 29. 14 ) that one 1659 should regulate one&amp;rsquo;s course of action ( in difficult or doubtful matters ) according to the conduct which is unanimously approved of in all countries by the Āryas (men of the three higher castes ), who have been properly disciplined, who are aged, who have restrained their senses and who are neither covetous nor hypocritical and con cludes with the aphorism (II. 11. 29. 15 ) &amp;lsquo;some teachers hold that the rest of the dharmas (not set out in this work ) may be understood from women and from men of all castes&amp;rsquo;. Baud. Dh. S. 1660 (1. 5. 13) states (on the subject of śrāddha) &amp;rsquo;the us. ages of people should be followed as to other rites to be per formed&amp;rsquo;. Several gļhyasūtras (like Pāraskara II. 17, Mānava&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>34 Kalivarjya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/3_sadAchAra/34_Kalivarjya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/3_sadAchAra/34_Kalivarjya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXXIV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;KALIVARJYA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(ACTIONS FORBIDDEN IN THE KALI AGE. )&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been stated above (pp. 865-866 ) that one of the several ways in which the conflict between several smṛti texts was got over was to hold some of them as legislating for a bygone age (yugāntara ). For example, when Hārsta allowed upanayana to women, both the Sm. C. (1. 24 ) and Par. M. (1. 2. p. 83 ) hold that the text refers to another kalpa (aeon). In H. of Dh. vol. II. (on pp. 151, 162, 424, 451, 603,612, 620,750,790, 796, 928, 929,934,953, 1005 n, 1201 n) reference has been made to several matters forbidden in the Kali age. It is remarkable in this connection to note that, though the Parāśarasmrti ( in I. 24 ) claims par excellence to lay down the dharmas for the Kali age, several inportant provisions contained in it, viz. the remarriage of a married woman 1730 (Parāsara IV. 30), the variation in the period of impurity due to births and deaths depending on the learning and character of a brāhmaṇa Parāśara II. 5-6), permission for a brāhmaṇa to partake of the food of five classes among sūdras (XI. 21 ) are included among Kalivarjyas by the Adityapurāṇa (as quoted by writers of the 12th and later centuries ). It is necessary, therefore, to investigate into the origin and development of the Yuga theory and of the topic of Kalivarjya.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>35 Customs in Modern Indian Law</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/3_sadAchAra/35_Customs_in_Modern_Indian_Law/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v3/3_sadAchAra/35_Customs_in_Modern_Indian_Law/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXXV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CUSTOMS IN MODERN INDIAN LAW&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Though an elaborate treatment of customs in niodern Anglo-Indian Law is far beyond the scope of the present work, yet a few words on customs in modern times may not be altogether out of place here. When the British began to acquire political domination in India they realized the importance attach. ed to customs by all persons in India and the Charter of the Mayor&amp;rsquo;s court at Bombay in 1753, unconsciously following the ancient dicta of Manu (VII. 203 ) and Yaj. (I. 343), contains the earliest trace in British royal charters of a reservation to the peoples of India of their laws and customs. 1887 The British Parliament and the Indian Legislatures have allowed customs to occupy a very high place in the administration of law and justice. The preamble to 21 Geo. III chap. 70 ( 1781 A. D.). recited that one of the purposes for which the Act was passed was that the inhabitants of Bengal, Bihar and Orissa should be maintained and protected in the enjoyment of all their laws, usages, rights and privileges and sec. 17 of that Act provided among other things that, in the case of the inhabitants of Calcutta, their inheritance and succession to lands, rents and goods and all matters of contract and dealing between party, and party shall be determined in the case of Mahomedans by the laws and usages of Mahomedans and in the case of Gentus by the laws and usages of Gentus 1888 and, where only one of the parties shall be a Mahomedan or Gentu, by the laws and usages of the defendant. 37 Geo. III chap. 142 (1796 A. D.), sec. 13, Bombay Regulation IV of 1827, sec. 26, the Government of India Act of 1915 (5 and 6 Geo. V chap. 61, sec. 112 ), Gov ernment of India Act 1935 ( 25 Geo. V chap. 2, sec. 223), the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
