<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Agglomerativeness</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/non-hindu-cases/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/non-hindu-cases/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://swarajyamag.com/culture/am-i-a-hindu&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve observed anti-hindus (esp. christians) attack &amp;ldquo;sati&amp;rdquo; (properly - anugamana), and hindus going on the defensive. A response I prefer is to proudly accept that practice as a noble choice in certain rare circumstances and point to famous non-hindu dramatizations. In this thread, let us collect such (Please add further high-quality ones).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;europe&#34;&gt;Europe&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Noble Brünnhilde after Siegfried in Wagner&amp;rsquo;s Götterdämmerung &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bhdVNvd7yKo&#34;&gt;YT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;diódōros&#34;&gt;Diódōros&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Diódōros&amp;rsquo;s account - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A2008.01.0541%3Abook%3D19%3Achapter%3D34&#34;&gt;Perseus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Note that Diódōros described the Greeks as condemning the practice (calling it ἄγριος &amp;ldquo;wild&amp;rdquo; and χαλεπός &amp;ldquo;savage&amp;rdquo;), but the fact that Greek soldiers in the vicinity of India adopted this practice demonstrates that many non-Indians did indeed see something beautiful and noble in the practice, and it was not a practice forced upon people.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The most striking account, from the years after the death of Alexander, is the case of the wife of the general Ceteus. 53 Ceteus died in the first major battle between the two successor generals, Antigonus and Eumenes, in late 317 BCE, which took place somewhere in the desert of central Iran. He was in charge of the Indian troops, and had two Indian wives, both of whom vied for the honour of being burned alive with his corpse. The younger asserted that the elder was pregnant and therefore could not be burned, while the elder demanded that as the senior wife she should have the right to carry out the sacrifice. Midwives were fetched to determine that the elder was indeed pregnant, on which she departed weeping, rending the wreath that was about her head and tearing her hair? The younger wife rejoiced, and advanced on the pyre dressed as if for a wedding, with ribbons in her hair; she gave away her jewellery – rings set with precious stones, necklaces and a circlet for her head, of golden stars studded with jewels - mounted the pyre, assisted by her brother, and, after the army had marched three times around the pyre, submitted calmly to the flames.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asada anugamana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/asada-anugamana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/asada-anugamana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Suicide of an Officer&amp;rsquo;s Wife.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Tokyo papers report the suicide of the wife of Lieut. Asada, who was killed in the last Manchurian campaign undertaken by Gen. I &amp;ndash; in order to recover Feughwau.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Mrs. Asada was a daughter of Major Okami, who commanded the third battalion of the Maruyama force. She was brought up under a rigid system and had only married the lieutenant the year before last. She was very virtuous, and was regarded by all who knew her as the model of a soldier&amp;rsquo;s wife. The lieutenant held his commission in the battalion commanded by his father-in-law, and it was from her father that the young widow received the tidings of her husband&amp;rsquo;s death. After writing an account of the battle, the letter went on to this effect:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GA on anugamana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/ghorAngIrasa_on_anugamana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/ghorAngIrasa_on_anugamana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some interesting points about sati:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It seems to be a kSatriya practice of NW provenance as far as bhArata is concerned. However, the practice definitely had external roots.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Initial reaction by brAhmaNas, prominently medhAtithi, was stern opposition as the shruti condemns those who end their life before the expiry of its natural term. Even if brAhmaNas couldn’t prevent sahagamana’s popularity among kSatriyas, they disliked it for their own women. Subsequent rise in prominence &amp;amp; support for sahagamana rests on secondary citations of smRtis as exceptions to the shruti’s general rule against suicide; most of which are not traceable to the cited sources.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>John Jones - sati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/john_jones_sati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/john_jones_sati/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My aunt was dressed in a red silk &lt;em&gt;sari&lt;/em&gt;, with all the ornaments on her person; her forehead daubed with a very thick coat of &lt;em&gt;sindur&lt;/em&gt;, or vermilion; her feet painted red with &lt;em&gt;alta&lt;/em&gt;; she was chewing a mouthful of betel; and a bright lamp was burning before her. She was evidently wrapped in an ecstasy of devotion, earnest in all she did, quite calm and composed as if nothing important was to happen. In short, she was then at her &lt;em&gt;matins&lt;/em&gt;, anxiously awaiting the hour when this mortal coil should be put off. My uncle was lying a corpse in the adjoining room. It appeared to me that all the women assembled were admiring the virtue and fortitude of my aunt. Some were licking the betel out of her mouth, some touching her forehead in order to have a little of the sindur, or vermillion ; while not a few, falling before her feet, expressed a fond hope that they might possess a small particle of her virtue. Amidst all these surroundings, what surprised me most was my aunt&amp;rsquo;s stretching out one of her hands, at the bidding of an old Brāhman woman, and holding a finger right over the wick of the burning lamp for a few seconds until it was scorched, and forcibly withdrawn by the old lady who bade her do so in order to test the firmness of her mind. The perfect composure with which she underwent this fiery ordeal fully convinced all that she was a real Sati, fit to abide with her husband in Boykunta, paradise. Nobody could notice any change in her countenance or resolution after she had gone through this painful trial.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nithin Shridhar - perspective</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/shrIdhar-nitin-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/shrIdhar-nitin-perspective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://indiafacts.org/sati-dharmic-perspective/&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;विस्तारः (द्रष्टुं नोद्यम्)&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Author’s Note: This is to clarify that the purpose of the article is to understand the practice of Sati-Anugamana as it was practiced in the past using value-system prevalent at those times. The author neither suggests that Sati has to be revived today nor supports any such attempts by anyone in current times.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nithin Sridhar&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nithin Sridhar has a degree in Civil Engineering, and having worked in the construction field, he passionately writes about various issues from development, politics, and social issues, to religion, spirituality, and ecology. He is currently Editor of IndiaFacts- a portal on Indian history and culture; He is editor of Advaita Academy dedicated to the dissemination of Advaita Vedanta. He is a Consulting Editor to Indic Today Magazine. He is based in Mysuru, Karnataka. His first book “Musings On Hinduism” provided an overview of various aspects of Hindu philosophy and society. His latest book ‘Samanya Dharma’ enunciates upon general tenets of ethics as available in Hindu texts. However, his most widely read book is “Menstruation Across Cultures: A Historical Perspective” that examines menstruation notions and practices prevalent in different cultures &amp;amp; religions from across the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rjrasva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/rjrasva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/anugamana/articles/rjrasva/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;widow-status&#34;&gt;Widow status&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rambles and Recollections of an Indian Official, Volume 1 by Sir William Henry Sleeman&#xA;Published: 1844&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I must do the family the justice to say, that they all exerted themselves to dissuade the widow from her purpose; and had she lived, she would assuredly have been cherished and honoured as the first female member of the whole house. There is no people in the world among whom parents are more loved, honoured, and obeyed, than among the Hindoos; and the grandmother is always more honoured than the mother. No queen upon her throne could be more&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
