<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 Studies in Early Saivism on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 Studies in Early Saivism on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>25 Sources for Reconstructing Ancient Forms of Śiva Worship</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/25_Sources_for_Reconstructing_Ancient_Forms_of_shi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/25_Sources_for_Reconstructing_Ancient_Forms_of_shi/</guid>
      <description>Śiva Caturmukha
The myth of Tilottamā
In chapter 203 of the ādiparvan of the Mahābhārata we are told that, in order
to kill the Asuras Sunda and Upasunda, who could only be killed by each other, Viśvakarman, ordered by Brahmā, creates a woman of unparallelled
beauty. The Grandfather tells her to go to the two demons and to seduce them in order that they may kill one and other in their rivalry over her̥ This beauty, named Tilottamā, promises to do so and takes her leave of the gods by making a circumambulatioṇ Among those gods is Bhagavat Maheśvara, who sits to the south (scil.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>26 At the Right Side of the Teacher</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/26_At_the_Right_Side_of_the_Teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/26_At_the_Right_Side_of_the_Teacher/</guid>
      <description>Imagination, Imagery, and Image in Vedic and Śaiva Initiation Then shall the King say unto them on his right hand,
Come, ye blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom
prepared for you from the foundation of the world.
Matthew 25: 34 (cf. Ecclesiastes 10: 2)
Introduction
The transformation of the Vedic religion into new systems of belief and practice, early Hinduism for short, is a process of cultural change that, despite two centuries of research, has only partly been understood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>27 Thanesar, the Pāśupata Order and the Skandapurāṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/27_Thanesar_the_pAshupata_Order_and_the_skandapurA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/27_Thanesar_the_pAshupata_Order_and_the_skandapurA/</guid>
      <description>Studies in the Skandapurāṇa IX
The tradition of the four pupils of Lāguḍi
By the middle of the sixth century the city of Kanauj seems to have emerged as the capital of the rising dynasty of the Maukharis under its king Īśānavarmaṇ 1
This town, in the Sanskrit tradition named Kānyakubja/ Kanyakubja, is known
from the Skandapurāṇa, and from this text only, as the seat of one of the Pāśupata lineages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>28 The Gospel of Kauṇḍinya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/28_The_Gospel_of_kauNDinya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/28_The_Gospel_of_kauNDinya/</guid>
      <description>The Descent of God in Gujarat and the Practice of Imitating God Kauṇḍinya’s Pañcārthabhāṣya
Kuśika and the divine revelation
When we speak of the gospel of Kauṇḍinya, we call forth an association with texts which describe the birth, life, and deeds of a saviour, texts which are meant to bring good news, an evangelium, into the world. This evocation is deliberate. As a tribute to Jan Bremmer’s life-long engagement, scholarly and otherwise, with gospels and kindred texts that have just failed to reach that status, I would like to show, that a text called ‘The Five Topics’, Pañcārtha,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>29 Origin and Spread of the Pāśupata Movement</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/29_Origin_and_Spread_of_the_pAshupata_Movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/29_Origin_and_Spread_of_the_pAshupata_Movement/</guid>
      <description>About Heracles, Lakulīśa and Symbols of Masculinity
Lāguḍi
The study of the origins of organized Saivism received a completely new perspective with the publication of the Pāśupatasūtras (PS) and Kauṇḍinya’s com-
mentary thereon, the Pañcārthabhāṣya, by r̥ Ananthakrishna Sastri in 1940.
Research by Minoru Hara, Daniel Ingalls, Alexis Sanderson, Thomas Oberlies, Peter Bisschop, and Diwakar Acharya, to mention just the major players in this field, built on this new evidence and has paved the way for our present investigation, which draws heavily on their work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 The Quest for the Pāśupata Weapon</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/30_The_Quest_for_the_pAshupata_Weapon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/30_The_Quest_for_the_pAshupata_Weapon/</guid>
      <description>The Gateway of the Mahādeva Temple at
Madhyamikā (Nagarī)
Hans Bakker &amp;amp; Peter Bisschop
Introduction
The village of Nagarī is situated in the Chittorgarh District (Rajasthan), 11 km north of the famous forṭ The present archaeological site lies to the south of the village on the right bank of the River Berach. The original citadel along the river extended further northwards and included the space presently occupied by the village (Plate 129).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>31 Composition and Spread of the Skandapurāṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/31_Composition_and_Spread_of_the_skandapurANa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/sAmya-vaiShamye/AchArAntaram/articles/holy-ground_Bakker/03_Studies_in_Early_Saivism/31_Composition_and_Spread_of_the_skandapurANa/</guid>
      <description>An Artist’s Impression
!
Friends, if you will permit me, let me be that kavi today. 1 Allow me to take advantage of this unique occasion to read an essay in the indicative mood. No modal auxiliaries: neither ‘would’ nor ‘should’; neither ‘may’ nor ‘could’. In other words, a thoroughly unscholarly exposition, but a, hopefully light, and delightfully careless artist’s impression, which puts ‘how beautiful it may have been, possibly’ into an apodictic style: ‘so beautiful it was, definitely’.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
