<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;विवाहः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;विवाहः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Child-marriage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/child-marriage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/child-marriage/</guid>
      <description>shatAvadhAnI gaNesh&amp;rsquo;s view here. Child marriage is referred to in the distant past, but very rarely. Consummation ritual ought to happen on the fourth day of marriage - this indicates that adult marriage was intended. But later practice changed this and introduced a delay. [TW17] Common ages of marriage, classically, were: 20 for men (having completed 12 years of education starting at 8) and about 16 for women. Note: It should not be considered inferior to adult marriage out of hand.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inbreeding</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/inbreeding/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/inbreeding/</guid>
      <description>स्वाभिप्रायः mahAmahopAdhyAya PV kANe, author of the &amp;ldquo;History of dharmashAstra&amp;rdquo; and others (of the tattvaniShTha-parivartanavAdI-sabhA which included a prominent shankarAchArya) proposed this reform: &amp;ldquo;sApiNDya rules exactly suffice on both sides.&amp;rdquo; bhAradvAja-s and jAmadagnya-s have a tough time in south India. The dhArmikatA would be the last constraint to loosen, yes - but there are other constraints to relax. Such as geographical location, language/ ethnicity and even sagotra-barrier. bhAradvAja-incel धर्मशास्त्रेष्व् अभिप्रायः असपिण्डा च या मातुर् असगोत्रा च या पितुः । सा प्रशस्ता द्विजातीनां दारकर्मणि मैथुने ॥ इति मनुः। विस्तारो ऽत्र। Gautama (4.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Remarriage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/Remarriage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/Remarriage/</guid>
      <description>Practice Gazetteer of the Ambala District: 1883 &amp;ldquo;As regards remarriages of widows the only classes that remarry are Jats Lohárs Jhínwars Tarkháns Mehtams who are allowed by their custom to go through the ceremony of Karewa Among Musalmans with the exception of Saiyads Moghals Pathans Shekhs and Rájpúts all women remarry. Among a the inferior castes who are in short Shúdras when one brother dies the widow is not allowed to go out of the family but is claimed by one of the other of the brothers who look upon her as belonging to the family money having been spent upon her and litigation in the courts both on Civil and Criminal sides to enforce these supposed rights froquently takes place I mention the Criminal as well as Civil Courts since it is not an uncommon matter for a brother to prosecute his sister in law and any second husband she may take for Bigamy because she has failed to transfer her affections to the surviving brother&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; Theory Generally prohibitted manusmRti न दत्त्वा कस्य चित् कन्यां पुनर्दद्याद् विचक्षणः । दत्त्वा पुनः प्रयच्छन् हि प्राप्नोति पुरुषानृतम् ॥ Manusmriti 9.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
