<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०० on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/kauTilIyam/artha-shAstram/00/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०० on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/kauTilIyam/artha-shAstram/00/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>मैसूरु-टिप्पनी</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/kauTilIyam/artha-shAstram/00/maisUru-TippanI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/kauTilIyam/artha-shAstram/00/maisUru-TippanI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[कौटिलीयम्-अर्थशास्त्रम्&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=MjQwMTYyOTE0NjMyMDA1&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHIEF EDITOR&amp;rsquo;S NOTE.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;_____________&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;IT is with no small diffidence that I allow the present volume to go forth as a number of the Mysore Government Oriental Library Series, the edition being based on a single manuscript of the text and a second one containing only a gloss on a very small section of the work. My only excuse for sending forth the volume at all is a long-cherished desire to make known, to the scholars engaged in the study of the ancient Sanskrit Literature in its bearing on Indian History specially and on historical research generally, the existence of what seems to be the oldest and most elaborate and systematic work extant on the &lt;em&gt;Arthasàstra,—&lt;em&gt;the social and civil polity of the ancient Hindus,**—**which will surely throw a flood of light on the material, moral, social and political condition of the ancient Hindus during the four or five centuries preceding the Christian Era. There is ample evidence to shew that Chànakya alias Vishnugupta&amp;rsquo;s Arthasàstra, known also as &lt;em&gt;Dandaniti,&lt;/em&gt; with which this work is identified, has been the basis of many a shorter treatise on the subject, including the &lt;em&gt;Nitisàra&lt;/em&gt; of K&lt;/em&gt;à&lt;/em&gt;mandaka. While venturing to publish such an important work edited from a single manuscript, I cherish a hope that, if any scholar should own a manuscript of the whole work or even of its part, he will be so kind as to place it at my disposal for a short time, so that all the better readings it may contain may be noted in the supplementary part which, among other things will contain a full index and a glossary of technical terms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
