<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;5 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/5/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;5 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/5/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Appendix of Long Sanskrit Passages</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/5/Appendix_of_Long_Sanskrit_Passages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/5/Appendix_of_Long_Sanskrit_Passages/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;828&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[Vol.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;APPENDIX-of long Sanskrit Passages&#xA;Page 118 Note 267. On pp. 117–118 above reference has been made to the re-admission into the Hindu fold of those that had been converted to Christianity or Islam by force or fraud or even voluntarily. Not only was there re-admission of those that were converted, but non-Hindus, such as Yavanas, Kirātas, Sakas, were absorbed into the Hindu fold and were induced to adopt the practices of Hindus (such as śrāddhas and gifts to brāhmaṇas). Vide Sāntiparva chap. 65. 13-21 quoted above in note 830 (p. 364). A. Greek ambassador of king Antalikita (Antialkidas) named Heliodora, son of Diya (Dion), was accre dited to the court of king Bhāgabhadra, called himself Bhāga vata and raised a column in honour of Vasudeva in the 2nd century B. C. (JRAS 1909, pp. 1053 and 1087 and JBBRAS vol. 23 p. 104). Uṣavadāta, son of Dinika and son-in-law of Ksatrapa Nahapāna, is described in one of the Nasik inscrip tions (No. 14a in E. I. vol. VIII at p. 85) as a saka, but made very extensive donations to brāhmanas at Broach, Prabhāsa and other places. Part of one of his inscriptions is cited on p. 710 note 1618 above. Though the name Usavadāta (Rṣabha datta) is a Sanskritized one the two names Dinika and Naha pāna of the Kṣaharāta race appear to be non-Indian, Abhiras, Hūpas and Gurjaras became absorbed into the Hindu commu nity. People, after being made Moslems, returned to their ori ginal communities and gods. Moslem writers make this clear. Vide Elliot and Dowsons&amp;rsquo; History of India&amp;rsquo; vol. I. p. 126 (&amp;rsquo;the people of India had returned to idolatry, excepting those of Kasa&amp;rsquo;) and Alberuni&amp;rsquo;s India (tr. by Sachau) vol. II, pp. 162-163 where he refers to the return of Hindu slaves in Moslem coun tries to their country and religion. Prof. D. R. Bhandarkar in &amp;ldquo;Some aspects of Ancient Indian Culture&amp;rsquo; (1940) pp. 59-65 presents a very lucid and informing summary of the evidence on this point of the re-admission of those that were converted and of the absorption of non-Hindus. But it is not known what procedure was followed for this purpose. Therefore, a model rite for the return of a convert is set out here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General Index</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/5/General_Index/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/5/General_Index/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;GENERAL INDEX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;OF 5 , Vol. IV (of the History of Dharmaśāstra ) -&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institute&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;GENERAL INDEX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;OF Vol. IV ( of the History of Dharmaśāstra ) (N. B. This Index deals with pages 1-727 only. As the list of tirthas from p. 730 onwards is arranged alphabetically, no entries from these pages are included in this Index, except in very rare cases for special reasons. When the name of a person or work occurs both in the body of the book as well as in the foot-notes on the same page, only the page is entered and nothing else ).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Index of Important Words</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/5/Index_of_Important_Words/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v4/5/Index_of_Important_Words/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INDEX OF DIPORTANT WORDS&#xA;ora 2 Bhandarkar Oriental Research InstituteINDEX OF IMPORTANT WORDS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Abhicāra 35 Abhidroha 5 Abhiśasta 13 Abhivanya 426 Abhyudayikasrāddha 359n Ācārya, 2810 Adhāna 574n Adya ( sraddha) 518n Agas 5-6 Agha (sin) 6 Agha (āśauca) 267-268 Agnisvātta 195n, 343 Agradidbiṣu 11 Agredidhisu 11n, 394n. Agrahāyani 354 Ahāva 503n Akalkaka 5621 Akrtidabana 225 Akṣayyodaka 508n Āmantrana 408 Amatya 199n Ambas 6 Amhati 7 Anadya 4020 Anasaka 42 Anavasthā 61n Ansta 5, 7 Anugrābaka 17 Anukalpa 387, 513 Anupataka 15 Anustarani 206 Apankteya 391 Aparāhna 376 Aposana 496 Aprita 315n Aratni 470n Arghya 419, 435n Aranyāni 5610 Arudhapatita 114 Asaucasampata or asauca-san nipata 292 Asmā 238 Astakā 3540 Asucikara 12, 14 Asutặpa 1939&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
