<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 Astrology and Dharmaśāstra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 Astrology and Dharmaśāstra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>14 Conception of Kāla</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/14_Conception_of_kAla/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/14_Conception_of_kAla/</guid>
      <description>SECTION II
KĀLA, MUHŪRTA, the influence of Astrology on DHARMASĀSTRA and CALENDAR
CHAPTER XIV
Conception of Kāla
Among the first of the great problems of philosophy is that of the nature of Space (dik) and Time (kāla).
The questions that arise are: Are Space and Time ultimately real? Is the world we apprehend spaceless and timeless or has the universe a beginning in time; are Space and Time themselves things or real attributes or relations of things.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15 Units of Kāla</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/15_Units_of_kAla/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/15_Units_of_kAla/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XV
Units of Kāla We shall now turn to the units of time from yuga backwards to muhūrta, leaving aside Manvantara, Kalpa and Pralaya for the moment.
The word &amp;lsquo;yuga&amp;rsquo; occurs at least 33 times in the Ṛgveda and appears to have been used in several senses. Vide H. of Dh. vol. III. p. 886-890. Two senses stand out as prominent, viz. a short period or a very long period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 Muhūrta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/16_muhUrta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/16_muhUrta/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XVI
Muhūrta
The word &amp;lsquo;muhūrta&amp;rsquo; occurs twice in the R̥g. In the dialogue between the rivers and sage Viśvamitra that had come to the confluence of the Śutudri (modern Sutlaj) and the Vipāś (modern Beas) occurs the following 1 &amp;lsquo;for the sake of my words (of your praise) that will be followed by the offering of soma may you, that follow the established order (of nature ), stop from 2 flowing for a short while&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>17 Muhūrtas for Religious Rites</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/17_muhUrtas_for_Religious_Rites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/17_muhUrtas_for_Religious_Rites/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XVII
MUHŪRTAS FOR RELIGIOUS RITES
We shall now turn to the muhūrtas for religious rites and actions of individuals. Only a few of the rites and actions can be briefly dealt with here.
A few general rules may however be first stated. The Ātharvaṇa 1 Jyotiṣa says that a wise man should perform an act or rite with the concurrence of all the four, viz. tithi, nakṣatra, karaṇa and muhūrta, if he wants success in it: if a proper tithi cannot be secured then the other three should be availed of, if the first two are not available then the next two, if the first three are not available then secure muhūrta alone; but if there be necessity to hurry and none of the four can be secured, then with the loud declaration by (learned ) brāhmaṇas that it is an auspicious day he should do the act and success is secured.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18 Calendar and related topics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/18_Calendar_and_related_topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/18_Calendar_and_related_topics/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XVIII
Calendar, eras, various reckonings about years, months &amp;amp;c.
In order to be able to perform vratas and celebrate utsavas at the proper times and in order to find out the appropriate times for religious rites like sacrifices, upanayana and marriage people require a calendar or almanac. A calendar is a methodical combination or book about days, months and years for the purpose of registering in advance religious festivals and astronomical or astrological phenomena and for purposes of civil life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>19 Kalpa, Manvantara, Mahāyuga, Yuga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/19_Kalpa_Manvantara_mahAyuga_Yuga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/19_Kalpa_Manvantara_mahAyuga_Yuga/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XIX
Kalpa, Manvantara, Mahāyuga, Yuga
After dealing with time measures from yuga ( of five years) down to weekdays and the day one must now briefly deal with the other measures of time such as Yuga, Mahāyuga, Manvantara and Kalpa. The word Kalpa has its germ in the R̥gveda 1 X. 190. 3, where it is said that the Creator created the Sun and the Moon, the heaven, the earth and mid-region as before.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
