<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 Introduction on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 Introduction on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 INTRODUCING THE *HOMA*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/01_INTRODUCING_THE_HOMA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/01_INTRODUCING_THE_HOMA/</guid>
      <description>Since research on the homa is important for both ritual studies and the study of Asian religions, it is a nexus of interaction for these two fields of study. It is important for ritual studies because this one ritual, despite particular sectarian inflections, has a history of more than two millennia, and the Indo-Iranian and Vedic rituals that form an important part of the source material for its development, extends that history to as much as four millennia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 RITUAL, CEREMONIAL, FESTIVAL</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/02_RITUAL_CEREMONIAL_FESTIVAL/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/02_RITUAL_CEREMONIAL_FESTIVAL/</guid>
      <description>As described in the essays that comprise this collection, the homa can be performed in a variety of different settings. In one case, for example, it is found as one element within a much larger complex of religious activities, such as the Navarātra described by Nawaraj Chaulagain in his chapter. In other cases, the homa is performed as a stand-alone ritual, such as in the Shugendō saitō goma discussed by Richard Payne.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 STUDYING THE DYNAMICS OF RITUAL CHANGE: THE *LONGUE DURÉE*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/03_STUDYING_THE_DYNAMICS_OF_RITUAL_CHANGE_THE_LONGUE_DURE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/03_STUDYING_THE_DYNAMICS_OF_RITUAL_CHANGE_THE_LONGUE_DURE/</guid>
      <description>The theoretical movement away from functionalist explanations, which emphasized stability and the return to the norm, has opened consideration of change and disruption as the normal state of affairs. As Pamela J. Stewart and Andrew Strathern put it, “studies of ritual practices today take into account not only variation but also creativity and innovation. This is in line with a general shift towards the study of change as distinct from continuity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 HOW TO CROSS THE *LONGUE DURÉE*: TEXTS \&#43; ETHNOGRAPHY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/04_HOW_TO_CROSS_THE_LONGUE_DURE_TEXTS_ETHNOGRAPHY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/04_HOW_TO_CROSS_THE_LONGUE_DURE_TEXTS_ETHNOGRAPHY/</guid>
      <description>For the historical study of ritual, that is over the longue durée, it is necessary to have recourse to texts. Philippe Buc has claimed, however, that dependence solely upon texts is methodologically problematic “because we do not have access to ritual practices, but only to texts depicting them (a given that renders impossible from the very start the use of certain kinds of anthropological models).”93 This is, however, one of the things that makes the homa especially valuable for the longitudinal study of ritual change.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 ORGANIZATION AND CONTENTS OF THIS COLLECTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/05_ORGANIZATION_AND_CONTENTS_OF_THIS_COLLECTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/05_ORGANIZATION_AND_CONTENTS_OF_THIS_COLLECTION/</guid>
      <description>The essays of this collection are purposely not arranged according to any of the three systematics that are effectively normative for the study of religious traditions, whether in Asia or not. These three—chronological, geo-political, and sectarian—have become effectively naturalized as the proper categories for the study of religions. However, change is not chronologically uniform and developmental, religions engaged with power structures that were different from those familiar to us today (nation-states), and participants in traditions sometimes actively sought out other traditions for purposes of adaptation, appropriation, or rebuttal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 CONCLUSION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/06_CONCLUSION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/06_CONCLUSION/</guid>
      <description>Several significant themes run through these essays, though not necessarily evident in all of them. These include the interiorization of ritual. Although the psychologized character of contemporary society may lead us to presume that this means performing the ritual as a mental visualization, Indic religious culture gives greater emphasis to an embodied basis for such interiorization.119 This usually involves a psycho-physical symbolism, and in some cases includes equations between ritual actions and breathing, digestion, and sexual intercourse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/07_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/07_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>REFERENCES
App, Urs. The Birth of Orientalism. Philadelphia and Oxford: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2010.
Bell, Catherine. Ritual Theory, Ritual Practice. New York and Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1992.
Bellah, Robert N. Religion in Human Evolution: From the Paleolithic to the Axial Age. Cambridge, MA, and London: Harvard University Press, 2011.
Beyer, Stephan. “Notes on the Vision Quest in Early Mahāyāna.” In Lewis Lancaster, ed. Prajñāpāramitā and Related Systems: Studies in Honor of Edward Conze, pp.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
