<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Arya-dharmopadeshaH on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/shrIvatsa-somadevaH/Arya-dharmopadeshAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Arya-dharmopadeshaH on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/shrIvatsa-somadevaH/Arya-dharmopadeshAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>RAmachandraH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/shrIvatsa-somadevaH/Arya-dharmopadeshAH/rAmachandraH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/shrIvatsa-somadevaH/Arya-dharmopadeshAH/rAmachandraH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ariya Dharma Upadeshangal&#xA;Ariya Dharma Upadeshangal&#xA;By Srivathsa Ve. Somadeva Sarma&#xA;Translated by P. R. Ramachander&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[I obtained the Tamil book &amp;ldquo;Ariya Dharmopadesangal&amp;rdquo; which has been published by Sri Ramamurthy Srouthigal, Sri Sadguru Dattatreya Nivasa, Vidyaranyapura, Sringeri - 577 139 from my friend Sri P. V. Anatha Narayanan. I am sure this book would be very much useful to all Brahmins to know the correct Acharas.]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Introduction By Srivathsa Ve. Somadeva Sarma: Achara (rituals) are only Dharma. The Acharas followed by holy people is Sadachara and Aacharas followed by eminent followers of the religion is Sishtachara. Though we generally tell Achara as Dharma, the rules which help practice Dharma is Sadachara. In some places Dharma is the dress and Achara are the limbs. For example, performing Sandhyavandana is a Dharma, but performing it after taking bath, after marking the forehead with sacred marks and wearing a Panchakacha is the aacharas. Even Vedas do not support a person who does not have aacharas. By following Achara we can get a long span of life and also become prosperous. Many Dharma Sasthras say that Dharma is born out of aacharas and anyone who leaves aacharas has a very short span of life. Karma or Dharma is a medicine that removes sins. Achara is the discipline that we have to follow in taking the medicine. When you do not follow the disciplines, in spite of taking medicine, the disease is not cured. Sometimes even the discipline only cures the diseases. One Purana says that a hunter who only followed Achara got a Brahmin birth. Any religious deed without following the aacharas does not give results.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
