<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 Astrology and Dharmaśāstra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 Astrology and Dharmaśāstra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>14 Conception of Kāla</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/14_Conception_of_kAla/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/14_Conception_of_kAla/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECTION II&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;KĀLA, MUHŪRTA, the influence of Astrology on DHARMASĀSTRA and CALENDAR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XIV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Conception of Kāla&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Among the first of the great problems of philosophy is that of the nature of Space (&lt;em&gt;dik&lt;/em&gt;) and Time (&lt;em&gt;kāla&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The questions that arise are: Are Space and Time ultimately real? Is the world we apprehend spaceless and timeless or has the universe a beginning in time; are Space and Time themselves things or real attributes or relations of things. Great divergence of views has prevailed on these problems from ancient times to this day. It is therefore advisable to indicate briefly the speculations on Time contained principally in Sanskrit works.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 Units of Kāla</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/15_Units_of_kAla/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/15_Units_of_kAla/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;units-of-kāla&#34;&gt;Units of Kāla&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We shall now turn to the units of time from &lt;em&gt;yuga&lt;/em&gt; backwards to muhūrta, leaving aside &lt;em&gt;Manvantara, Kalpa and Pralaya&lt;/em&gt; for the moment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;yuga&amp;rsquo; occurs at least 33 times in the Ṛgveda and appears to have been used in several senses. Vide H. of Dh. vol. III. p. 886-890. Two senses stand out as prominent, viz. a short period or a very long period. For the first sense we may cite Ṛg. I. 158. 6 ( &amp;lsquo;Dīrghatamas, the son of Mamatā, became old in the 10th Yuga, he became brahmā high priest and leader of the waters flowing to their goal&amp;rsquo;.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Here yuga cannot mean a period of more than ten years and probably means a period of five years; in Ṛg. III. 26.3 we read &amp;rsquo;like a neighing horse by its mother, Vaiśvānara ( Agni) is kindled by the Kuśikas in each yuga&amp;rsquo;; vide Ṛg. 111.55.18.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the Vedāṅgajyotiṣa &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (verses 1 and 5 ) yuga is said to comprise five years. There is nothing to prevent us from taking this sense in the two passages cited from the Ṛgveda. In R̥g. III. 55.18 it is possible to recognize a recondite reference to five year units of time each divided into six seasons. In the Ṛgveda &lt;em&gt;saṁvatsara&lt;/em&gt; means a year in several passages such as I. 110. 4, I. 140.2, I. 161. 13, I. 164. 44, VII, 103. 1, 7, 9, X. 190.2. In R̥g. X, 87. 17 we have the derivative form &amp;lsquo;Saṁvatsariṇa&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from saṁvatsara &amp;lsquo;O Agni that observest what men do! May the demon possessing magic devices not partake of the cow&amp;rsquo;s milk that springs after a year&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 Muhūrta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/16_muhUrta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/16_muhUrta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XVI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Muhūrta&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;muhūrta&amp;rsquo; occurs twice in the R̥g. In the dialogue between the rivers and sage Viśvamitra that had come to the confluence of the Śutudri (modern Sutlaj) and the Vipāś (modern Beas) occurs the following &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;lsquo;for the sake of my words (of your praise) that will be followed by the offering of &lt;em&gt;soma&lt;/em&gt; may you, that follow the established order (of nature ), stop from &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; flowing for a short while&amp;rsquo;. In another place the R̥gveda says &amp;rsquo;the opulent Indra, employing many tricks, often assumes different forms from off his own body, since he, being invoked by mantras addressed to him and upholder of the cosmic order and drinking soma at (usual and even) unusual times, comes thrice from heaven for a short time.&amp;rsquo; In both these passages &amp;lsquo;muhūrta&amp;rsquo; means &amp;lsquo;a short time, a few moments&amp;rsquo;. This meaning of muhūrta is found in the Śat. Br. I. 8. 3. 17 (tan muhūrtam dhārayitvā) and II. 3. 2. 5 (atha prātaḥ anaśitvā muhūrtam sabhāyām-āsitvāpi) and in classical Sanskrit works like the Raghuvaṁśa ( V. 58).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 Muhūrtas for Religious Rites</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/17_muhUrtas_for_Religious_Rites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/17_muhUrtas_for_Religious_Rites/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XVII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;MUHŪRTAS FOR RELIGIOUS RITES&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We shall now turn to the muhūrtas for religious rites and actions of individuals. Only a few of the rites and actions can be briefly dealt with here.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A few general rules may however be first stated. The Ātharvaṇa &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Jyotiṣa says that a wise man should perform an act or rite with the concurrence of all the four, viz. &lt;em&gt;tithi, nakṣatra, karaṇa and muhūrta&lt;/em&gt;, if he wants success in it: if a proper tithi cannot be secured then the other three should be availed of, if the first two are not available then the next two, if the first three are not available then secure muhūrta alone; but if there be necessity to hurry and none of the four can be secured, then with the loud declaration by (learned ) brāhmaṇas that it is an auspicious day he should do the act and success is secured. Certain religious acts have to be done at stated times and in those cases, one should not consider the conditions of Jupiter and Venus called &lt;em&gt;bālya&lt;/em&gt; and old age or the fact of Jupiter being in Lion sign, or of &lt;em&gt;dakṣiṇāyana&lt;/em&gt; or there being an intercalary month, as for example, in the rites from &lt;em&gt;puṁsavana&lt;/em&gt; up to &lt;em&gt;annaprāśana&lt;/em&gt;. The Rājamārtaṇḍa &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; states &amp;rsquo;the correct astrological position of planets and days is not meant for times of distress, all these ( rules about auspicious positions) are to be considered when life is easy (matters are in good condition); so says Bhr̥gu&amp;rsquo;. Monday, Wednesday, Thursday and Friday confer success in all actions ( begun on those days ); only those actions succeed on Sunday, Tuesday and Saturday, for which those days are expressly laid down as proper. But the Nāradapurāṇa says that Wednesday, Thursday and Friday are the best, Sunday and Monday are middling and the other two, Viz. Tuesday and Saturday, are condemned for Upanayana. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 Calendar and related topics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/18_Calendar_and_related_topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/18_Calendar_and_related_topics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XVIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Calendar, eras, various reckonings about years, months &amp;amp;c.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In order to be able to perform &lt;em&gt;vratas&lt;/em&gt; and celebrate &lt;em&gt;utsavas&lt;/em&gt; at the proper times and in order to find out the appropriate times for religious rites like sacrifices, upanayana and marriage people require a calendar or almanac. A calendar is a methodical combination or book about days, months and years for the purpose of registering in advance religious festivals and astronomical or astrological phenomena and for purposes of civil life. In India about thirty calendars are in use by Christians, Parsis, Moslems and Hindus. Confining oneself to Hindus there is a bewildering variety of calendars in use at present. Some are based on the data of the Sūryasiddhānta and some on those of the Aryasiddhānta, while others follow comparatively later manuals like the Grahalāghava; some begin the year with Caitra &lt;em&gt;śukla pratipad&lt;/em&gt; (or &lt;em&gt;pratipadā&lt;/em&gt;), others with Kārtika śukla pratipad and there are small tracts like the Halar &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;prānt&lt;/em&gt; ( in Kathiawad) where the year begins with the 1st day of the bright half of Āṣāḍha. Gujarat and North India except Bengal use the Vikrama era, while the Deccan and South India generally employ the Śaka year, but Kashmir follows the &lt;em&gt;Laukika&lt;/em&gt; reckoning. In some parts (North India and Telaṅgaṇa) and communities the months are pūrṇimānta (i.e. end with Full Moon), while other parts ( Bengal, Mahārāstra and south India) follow the amānta (month ending with amāvāsyā) reckoning, The result is that some fasts and celebrations universally observed throughout India such as the Ekādaśi and Śivaratri fasts and the celebrations of the birth of Srikr̥ṣṇa are observed on two different days in different parts of the country and by different sects and there is a difference of one month between the days of some observances i.e. while on the pūrṇimānta reckoning a certain festival may be observed in Āśvina dark half, the same month may be called Bhādrapada dark half ( by amanta reckoning ) and the same festival may be celebrated one month later.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 Kalpa, Manvantara, Mahāyuga, Yuga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/19_Kalpa_Manvantara_mahAyuga_Yuga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/2_Astrology_and_dharmashAstra/19_Kalpa_Manvantara_mahAyuga_Yuga/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kalpa, Manvantara, Mahāyuga, Yuga&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After dealing with time measures from &lt;em&gt;yuga&lt;/em&gt; ( of five years) down to weekdays and the day one must now briefly deal with the other measures of time such as Yuga, Mahāyuga, Manvantara and Kalpa. The word Kalpa has its germ in the R̥gveda &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; X. 190. 3, where it is said that the Creator created the Sun and the Moon, the heaven, the earth and mid-region as before.&amp;rsquo; The earliest datable reference to Kalpa is found in Aśoka&amp;rsquo;s edicts e.g. the 4th Rock edict &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; at Girnar and Kalsi have &amp;lsquo;āva savaṭa kapā&amp;rsquo; (yāyat saṁvartakalpam ) and &amp;lsquo;āva kapam&amp;rsquo; in the 5th Rock Edict at Shahabazgarhi and Mansera. This establishes that the theories about the vast extent of Kalpa had been promulgated in India long before the third century B.C. The Buddhists also took over the theory of Kalpas as is clear from the Mahāparinibbānasutta III 53 &amp;lsquo;Vouchsafe, Lord, to remain during the Kalpa. Live on, O Blessed One, through the Kalpa for the good and happiness of the great multitudes &amp;amp;c.&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
