<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;3 Sadācāra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/3_sadAchAra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;3 Sadācāra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/3_sadAchAra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>32 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/3_sadAchAra/32_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/3_sadAchAra/32_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXXII
SADACARA
CUSTOMS AND MODERN CUSTOMARY LAW1606
From Gautama 1606 downwards many writers dilate upon the sources of dharma. Gautama. I. 1-2 states: &amp;rsquo; the Veda is the source ( mula) of dharma and also the tradition (or smṛtis ) and practice of those who know the Veda&amp;rsquo;. Similarly Ap. Dh. S. (I. 1. 1.1-%) says: &amp;lsquo;we shall propound the acts (that produce merit) which are evolved from conventions and practices; the authority ( for finding out the dharmas) are the conventions of those who know the dharma and the Vedas&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>33 Customs and Dharmaśāstra Works</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/3_sadAchAra/33_Customs_and_dharmashAstra_Works/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/3_sadAchAra/33_Customs_and_dharmashAstra_Works/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXXIII
CUSTOMS AND DHARMASASTRA WORKS
It is now necessary to see how Dharmaśāstra works have dealt with the authority and binding force of customs and usages. Sadācāra is defined by Harita as follows 1657:- the word &amp;lsquo;sat&amp;rsquo; means &amp;lsquo;good&amp;rsquo; and the good are those who are free from (inoral) taint; the practices of such people are called sadācāra. Vide Manu II. 18, which also defines sadācāra. Even the most ancient sūtras testify to the fact that numerous customs and usages had arisen in different countries and vil lages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>34 Kalivarjya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/3_sadAchAra/34_Kalivarjya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/3_sadAchAra/34_Kalivarjya/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXXIV
KALIVARJYA
(ACTIONS FORBIDDEN IN THE KALI AGE. )
It has been stated above (pp. 865-866 ) that one of the several ways in which the conflict between several smṛti texts was got over was to hold some of them as legislating for a bygone age (yugāntara ). For example, when Hārsta allowed upanayana to women, both the Sm. C. (1. 24 ) and Par. M. (1. 2. p. 83 ) hold that the text refers to another kalpa (aeon).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>35 Customs in Modern Indian Law</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/3_sadAchAra/35_Customs_in_Modern_Indian_Law/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/3_sadAchAra/35_Customs_in_Modern_Indian_Law/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXXV
CUSTOMS IN MODERN INDIAN LAW
Though an elaborate treatment of customs in niodern Anglo-Indian Law is far beyond the scope of the present work, yet a few words on customs in modern times may not be altogether out of place here. When the British began to acquire political domination in India they realized the importance attach. ed to customs by all persons in India and the Charter of the Mayor&amp;rsquo;s court at Bombay in 1753, unconsciously following the ancient dicta of Manu (VII.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
