<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Woman स्त्रीः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Woman स्त्रीः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Access to education and scholarship</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Access_to_education_and_scholarship/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Access_to_education_and_scholarship/</guid>
      <description>rAjashekhara clearly says in Kavyamimamsa 10th chapter: &amp;ldquo;पुरुषवद्योषितोऽपि कवीभवेयुः । संस्कारो ह्यात्मनि समवैति, न स्त्रैणं वा पौरुषं वा विभागमपेक्षते । श्रूयन्ते दृश्यन्ते च राजपुत्र्यो महामात्रदुहितरो गणिकाः कौतुकिभार्याश्च शास्त्रप्रहतबुद्धयः कवयश्च ।&amp;rdquo; Commentary: &amp;ldquo;यथा पुरुषास्तथा योषितोऽपि स्त्रियोऽपि कवीभवेयुः काव्यकर्त्र्यः स्युः । सहेतुकं विवेचयति संस्कार इति । कवित्वं संस्कारविशेषजन्यम् । संस्कारश्च आत्मनि समवैति समवायसम्बन्धेन वर्त्तते न स्रियाः शरीरे वर्त्तते । अतश्च अयं स्त्रीत्वावच्छिन्नः अयं पुरुषावच्छिन्न आत्मा इत्येवं रूपेण स्त्रिया आगतं स्त्रैणं पुरुषादागतं पौरुषं विभागं नापेक्षते । दृष्टान्तेन उपपादयति - श्रूयन्त इति । श्रूयन्ते कर्णाभ्यामिति शेषः । नहि श्रवणमात्रे सत्यता इत्यतो दार्ढ्यायोच्यते - दृश्यते चक्षुर्भ्यामिति शेषः । राज्ञां सुताः । महामात्राणाममात्यसचिवादिकानां कन्यकाः । गणिकाः वेश्याः कौतुकिनां नटानामैन्द्रजालिकानां वा भार्याः अथवा कौतिकिन्यो भार्याश्च । शास्त्रेषु प्रहताः क्षुण्णाः अथवा शास्त्रद्वारा प्रहताः सम्मार्जिता उभयथापि निर्मला इत्यर्थः बुद्धयो यासां ताः शास्त्रप्रहतबुद्धयः । अथ च कवयः कवयित्र्यः ॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Access to lore and ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Access_to_lore_and_ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Access_to_lore_and_ritual/</guid>
      <description>Access is, of course, graded. This is a consequence of the allowance for exclusivism in the hindu way (see here). Neo-Traditional female brAhmaNI ritual specialists - IMG. Ritual purity and mestural cycles A mensturating woman is considered ritually impure for most purposes. This is atleast as old as Apastamba shrauta sUtra [IMG]. yAga-dIxa overcomes this [IMG]. Access to veda-s [Discussions - BVP] Not uncommon access for brahmavAdinI-s in texts. हारितः - &amp;ldquo;तत्र ब्रह्मवादिनीनाम् उपनयनम्, अग्नीन्धनम् वेदाध्ययनं स्वगृहे च भिक्षाचर्येति।&amp;rdquo; Women got the upanayana initiation (as a symbolism before marriage or as a serious initiation depending on the case) well into the gRhya-sUtra and early dharma-shAstra ages (काणे-विचार-सारो ऽत्र।) &amp;ldquo;पुरा कल्पेषु नारीणां मौञ्जीबन्धनमिष्यते । अध्यापनं च वेदानां सावित्रीवचनं तथा ॥&amp;rdquo; Access to upavIta : see upavIta.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Female foeticide</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Female_foeticide/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Female_foeticide/</guid>
      <description> Foeticide is a grave sin according to hindu-shAstra-s. Yet, in violation of this, people have killed female foetuses in the past. There has been tradition based attempts to address this problem: example girl-child-11-trees-village. </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overall status</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Overall_status/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Overall_status/</guid>
      <description>Consider shatAvadhAnI-gaNesha&amp;rsquo;s commentary on the role of women in ancient India (esp. compared with contempraneous societies elsewhere). Also see examples here. Lower from ritual and mokSha perspective Womanhood as a lower status birth (hindu society was patriarchal, as in other contemporary societies) At a ritual and social (rather than family) level, there is no doubt that status of women was lower. women and shUdra-s are considered by some, barring exempt pUja-s, to be ineligible for saying paurANika mantra-s - japa-s and homa-s are to be conducted through a brAhmaNa [DS78].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional dimorphism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Professional_dimorphism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Professional_dimorphism/</guid>
      <description>Female participation in the army. In the era of large armies/ warring class: Sparing participation makes great sense given the importance of wombs. [IMG, ] &amp;ldquo;Loss of females is a real loss of fitness for the social group, while loss of even a fraction of the males will not change seriously change fitness as long as the number of females are intact. Thus, inter-group conflict is likely to eventually evolve a strong bias towards male only participation, which will be further exacerbated in favor of males when there is strong sexual dimorphism in mean size, speed and strength between the two sexes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rape</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Rape/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Rape/</guid>
      <description>bRhadAraNyaka case Arguable reference to wife beating and rape in bRhadAraNyaka : IMG. ( षष्ठोऽध्यायः । चतुर्थं ब्राह्मणम् । मन्त्रः ७) FB15. shankara considers such to be smRtyanuvAdinI, as representing smArta, rather than shrauta karma-s. Example: 6.3.1 commentary (- http://i.imgur.com/GmoWeUa.png । अनुवादोऽत्र - http://i.imgur.com/2boHAYb.jpg ।). smRti-s according to some dharmashAstra commentators have less authority than shruti. Unsatisfactory excuses: Some authorities interpret it as encoding a secret (eg: होळेनरसीपुरवासिनः परमपूज्याः श्री श्री सच्चिदानन्देन्द्रसरस्वतीपरमहंसाः IMG1) - so it should not be taken literally.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Right to property</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Right_to_property/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/women/Right_to_property/</guid>
      <description> Right to property? Is woman property to be &amp;ldquo;given&amp;rdquo; away or sold during marriage? shabarasvAmin answering this misassertion over 1.5k years ago [6.1.13e, TW]. The shAstra-s catered to parents who yearned for girls (Apastamba - IMG) and scholarly girls (बृहदारण्यकोपनिषद्(शुक्लयजुर्वेद)- अथ य इच्छेद् दुहिता मे पण्डिता जायेत सर्वमायुरियादिति तिलौदनं पाचयित्वा.). </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
