<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;varNa theory on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;varNa theory on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ananda access</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/Ananda-access/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/Ananda-access/</guid>
      <description>Intro Unrestricted ability to enter intellectual/ spiritual life and pursue the ultimate Ananda (joy). Prior to the turuShka invasion, the nAstika sects especially offered channel of entry to an intellectual life and social respect by common people. &amp;ldquo;far from the non-brāhmaṇa population being disenfranchised and deprived of knowledge and rituals, the brāhmaṇa-s constantly innovated new texts, paths and strategies to significantly circumvent any restrictions, which may have been in place&amp;hellip; As it is in a diverse, polytheist society, every group of Hindus, has a general right to create its own traditions and develop an exclusive ritual space for its own needs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Animals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/animal_observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/animal_observations/</guid>
      <description>General Division of labor has been observed in nature - most famously in case of insects such as wasps, ants, bees etc.., whose colonies have led to group selection. So, it is plausible that specialization since childhood, and subsequent limitations on social mobility may have provided a competitive edge to early human societies. Chimpanzee Chimps greet alpha males with this distinctive call, the pat grunt. As a formal signal of submission everybody is going up to greet the big guy&amp;hellip; &amp;ldquo;You are dominant than me, you are tougher than me, I am saying this to you so you won&amp;rsquo;t beat me up&amp;hellip; Chimpanzees tell u who is on top&amp;amp;who is on the bottom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contrast with individualism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/contrast_with_individualism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/contrast_with_individualism/</guid>
      <description>Via MT:
The moderns have a certain separation from society, and even family. This is why the less thoughtful and less educated among them cannot see from the eyes of the first dharmaśāstrakāra-s in India.
Many moderns, especially those inspired by the western Abrahamosphere, invert the arrow making the individual privilege greater than that of the group. Thus, as that Portuguese thinker noted recently they keep making new laws to safeguard every specialized classes of individuals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crossing seas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/seas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/seas/</guid>
      <description>Secondary references kANe v3. Also see &amp;ldquo;India entry&amp;rdquo; page and in AryAvarta topic v2p13 for context regarding the fluid definition of AryAvarta. Prohibitions baudhAyana lists sea voyage among patanIya-s. manu says that a brAhmaNa who has crossed the seas is not worthy of being invited to a shrAddha. &amp;ldquo;अस्माकमुदधिपारगतत्वमाकाशमार्गचारिणा वायुयानेनाऽभवन्न तु जलकपोतयानेन समुद्रसंयानेन वा (कृष्णयजुर्वेदीयतैत्तिरीयशाखाया: बौधायनधर्मसूत्रेषु २.१.२.२. – “समुद्रसंयानम्” – अत्र विवरणव्याख्यानकर्तुः श्रीगोविन्दस्वामिनोऽभिप्राय: समुद्रयानेन/जलपोतयानेन द्वीपावान्तरयात्रायां पर्यवस्यति न त्वाकाशमार्गेण वायुयानेन) ।&amp;rdquo; इति केचित्। shivAchArya-s &amp;ldquo;Dr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pros</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/pros/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/pros/</guid>
      <description>मनुः - &amp;ldquo;सर्वस्यास्य तु सर्गस्य गुप्त्यर्थं स महाद्युतिः । मुखबाहूरुपज्जानां पृथक्कर्माण्यकल्पयत्॥ &amp;quot; (1.31), &amp;ldquo;सर्वस्यास्य तु सर्गस्य गुप्त्यर्थं स महाद्युतिः । मुखबाहूरुपज्जानां पृथक्कर्माण्यकल्पयत् ॥&amp;rdquo; (1.87) Excellence in critical areas A memeplex that places emphasis in the following order: scholarship and conservation of Arya values (brAhmaNa-s) &amp;raquo; governance and defence (kShatriya-s) &amp;raquo; commerce (vaiShya-s) &amp;raquo; service (shUdra-s) This orients a society to hold sacredness and spirituality above mere material achievements. brAhmaNa regimentation A brAhmaNa varNa fully dedicated to conserving Arya ideals is a great advantage to the memeplex- see vaidika-brAhmaNa-glue part of this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Untouchability</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/untouchability/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/untouchability/</guid>
      <description>Intro The following classes of people / circumstances were subject to untouchability rules according to the smRti-s:
A person who has committed a grave sin (mahApAtaka), but has not performed prAyashchitta. People whose spiritual practices were abhorrent to certain other people. Eg - bauddha-s jaina-s nAstika-s, even pAshupata-s and sAnkhya-s according to some texts. People following undersirable professions. Eg. a devalaka, a purohita for an entire village, hunter, butcher, fisherman etc.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
