<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2.1 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2.1 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>19 Devayajña</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/19_devayajna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/19_devayajna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;DEVAYAJÑA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Devayajña &amp;ndash;As stated in the Tai. Ār. quoted above ( p. 696 ) the Devayajña was performed by offering fuel sticks into fire. According to the Ap. Db. S. I. 4. 13. 1, Baud. 1688 Db. S. II. 6. 4 and Gaut. V. 8-9, the Devayajña consisted in offering into fire offerings ( of food or at least a fuel stick ) with &amp;lsquo;svāhā&amp;rsquo; uttered after the name of the deities in the dative case. Manu also (III. 70 ) looks upon homa as devayajña. The devatās to whom homa or devayajña was offered are different according to different gshya or dharma sūtrae. For example, Aśv. gr. ( I. 2. 2) says that they are the deities of the Agnihotra (1. e. Sūrya or Agni, and Prajāpati), Soma Vanaspati, Agni and Soma, Indra and Agni, Heaven and earth, Dhanvantari, Indra, the Viśve Devas, Brahman&amp;rsquo;. According to Gaut. they are Agni, Dhanvantari, Visve Devas, Prajāpati, Agni Svistakst. Vide Mādava-gphya II. 12. 2 where the deities are different from those in Aśv. gr. and Gaut. In later smrtis a distinction is made between homa (or devayajña ) and devapūjā. Yāj. in I. 100 speaks of the worship of gods immediately after tarpana and then in I. 102 includes homa among the five yajñas. Manu II. 176 also makes this distinotion. Medieval writers came to look upon Vaiśvadeva as the devayajña, while others held that home to gods was different from Vaiśvadeva. Vide Haradatta 1886 on Ap. Dh. 8. I. 4. 13. 1. According to Marici and Hārita quoted in the Smrtimuktāphala ( abnika p. 383 ) devapūjā is performed after the morning homa or after brahmayajñs and tarpana 1687 in the noon. In medieval and modern times the ancient idea of homa&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 Vaiśvadeva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/20_vaishvadeva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/20_vaishvadeva/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;VAISVADEVA Vaiśvadeva.-offering of cooked food to all Gods ).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Daksa ( II. 56 ) says that in the 5th part of the day a house holder has to allow distribution of food according to his ability to the gods, Manes, men and even insects. Vai vadeva is to be offered according to Śatātapa ( quoted by Medhātithi on Manu V, 7 and by Aparārka p. 142) in the gphya fire if one has preserved it, or in the ordinary fire. If no fire is available one may offer it even in water or on the bare ground. Laghu. Vyāga II. 52 says the same.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 Manuṣyayajña</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/21_manuShyayajna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/21_manuShyayajna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXI NRYAJÑA OR MANUṢYA-YAJÑA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NȚyajña or Manusya-yajña : ( Honouring guests)-Manu (III. 70 ) states that this consists in honouring guests. In the oldest hymns of the Rgveda fire is described as a guest in the house of the sacrificer. In Rg. I. 73. 1 Agni is described as lying in a pleasant spot and pleased like a guest (syonasir atithir-na priṇāno). Vide Rg. V, 1. 8 1785 and 9, V, 4. 5, VIL 42. 4 for fire being called atithi. In Rg. IV. 4. 10 it is said of Agni&amp;rsquo;you become the protector, the friend, of him wbo offers you hospitality in the usual (or proper) order,&amp;rsquo; Vide Rg. IV.33.7 and Tai. S. I. 2. 10.1 for the word ātithya. Athar Vaveda IX. 6 is an eulogy of hospitality in which the various stages in the reception and feeding of a guest are metaphori cally represented as the various actions performed in a sacri fice. 1988 The Tai. 8. V.2.2. 4 refers to the faot that when &amp;amp; guest comes, hospitality in which ghee abounds, is offered to him&amp;rsquo; and it remarks that &amp;lsquo;one who comes in a chariot and one who comes in &amp;amp; cart are the two most honoured among guests. 1987: The Tai. S. (VI. 2. 1. 2) says &amp;lsquo;hospitality is offered to all the followers accompanied by whom a king comes&amp;rsquo;. Vide Ait. Br. IL. 9 for almost the same words. The San. Br. IL 9 remarks 1788 when a man offers oblations at sunrise, he indeed offers hospitality to a great god who has started on a journey.&amp;rsquo; The Tai. Br. (II. 1. 3) shows that a guest was honoured by having &amp;amp; lit lamp placed before him and then food was served to him. 1989 The Ait. Br. ( 25. 5) says that a guest&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 Bhojana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/22_Bhojana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/22_Bhojana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;BHOJANA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bhojana ( taking one&amp;rsquo;s meals ) :-Dakṣs (II. 56 and 68) states that in the fifth 1809 part of the day the householder should make according to his capacity the gods, pitrs, mon and even lower animals (lit. insects) participators (in food) and after doing that, he should himself partake of the remainder of the food cooked. Thus he was to take his mealy during one hour and a half after noon. Bhojana is one of the most important subjects treated of in Dharmaśāstra works and the greatest importance (next to rules about marriage) attaches to the numerous injunotions and taboos about food. The principal subjects to be dealt with under this head are: how many times food was to be taken; the kinds of foods and drinks allowed or forbidden; what causes food defilement; flesh-eating and drink ing wine; whose food was to be eaten; etiquette and ceremonies before taking food, at the time of taking it and after taking it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 Upākarma and Utsarjana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/23_upAkarma_and_Utsarjana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/23_upAkarma_and_Utsarjana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;UPĀKARMA OR UPĀKARANA AND&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;UTSARJANA OR UTSARGA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ning (upakran Asv. g!. III. 3:in the year. Ap.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Upākarma or Upākarana means &amp;lsquo;opening, starting or begin. ning&amp;rsquo; (upakrama as the Mit. on Yāj. I, 142 says) and Utsarjana or Utsarga (in Aśv. gļ, III. 5. 13) means &amp;rsquo;the cessation of Vedic studies for a certain period in the year.&amp;rsquo; Ap. gr. VIII. 1 and Ap. Dh S. I. 3. 11. % employ the word &amp;lsquo;samāpana&amp;rsquo; for utsarjana. In former times these two rites were performed on different dates and in different months, but with the decline of vedio studies in medieval times they came to be performed one after another on the same day. In several sātras the first of these two is spoken of as adhyayopākarspa (as in Āśv. gr. III. 5. 1.) or adhyiyopākarma (in Pār. gs. II. 10, Vas. Dh. S. 13. 1). In this case adhyāya means study of the Veda&amp;rsquo; or it may mean Veda itself because it is studied (pre-eminently). Therefore the rite which signalises the opening of the session for Vedic study in the year is itself called upākarma.1997 In Gaut. 16. I the rite of upākarmu is called vārșika either because it took place in varsā (the rainy season) or because it took place once a year (from varsa, a year). The Āśv. gr. III. 5. 19 also states that this rite is oalled vārṣika.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 Minor Gṛhya and Other Rites</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/24_Minor_gRhya_and_Other_Rites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/24_Minor_gRhya_and_Other_Rites/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXIV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;MINOR GRHYA AND OTHER RITES&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The grhyasūtras speak of certain other rites performed on certain fixed days in the year. Most of them have ceased to be performed in modern times, though vestiges of some of them appear even now. Gautama (VIII. 19 ) enumerates the seven pākayajā asamsthās among his forty sarskāras. Out of these seven pākayajñas, aṣtakā, pārvana and śrāddha will be dealt with under śrāddha later on, The seven haviryajñas and the seven somasamsthās will be treated of in the note on Srauta. A fow of the other rites are briefly described below.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 Dāna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/25_dAna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/25_dAna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;DANA (Gifts )&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Manu ( I. 86 ) and others state that in the four yugas ( ages ) viz. Kșta, Tretā, Dvāpara and Kali, the principal aspects of religious life were respectively tapas, metaphysical knowledge, sacrifices, 1973 and gifts. Manu (III. 78 ) eulogises the stage of householder as the most worthy because all men in the other asramas are cherished and fed with (Vedic ) knowledge (as a teacher of Vedic students) and with food by him. Yama speci fies the characteristic features of the four aśramas as follows: ‘quiescence is the dharma of ascetics, cessation from taking ordinary food that of forest hermits, dāna (making gifts) that of householders and obedience ( or service ) that of brahmacāring.&amp;rsquo; Vide Daksa 1. 12-13 also for the peouliar outward characteristios of the four asramas. Therefore the subject of dana ( gifts or obarity ) will now engage our attention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 Pratiṣṭhā and Utsarga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/26_pratiShThA_and_Utsarga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/26_pratiShThA_and_Utsarga/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXVI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PRATIṢTHA AND UTSARGA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pratistha and Utsarga (foundation of temples and dedica. tion of wells, tanks, parks &amp;amp;o, for the benefit of the publio).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The subject of gifts naturally leads on to the topics of pratiṣtha and utsarga. We saw above (p. 157 f. n. 370) how the construction of temples, wells and similar religious and charitable foundations and institutions was included under pūrtadharma and how sūdras were entitled to perform such dharma, The Mit. on Yāj. II. 114 points 8068 out that women (and widows) were entitled to spend on pūrta objects, though they were not authorized to perform iṣta dharma (i. 0. vedio sacrifices &amp;amp;o.). Modern decisions have gone so far that a Hindu widow whose powers of alienating for secular purposes property inherited from her husband are very limited has been held to possess greater powers of alienation if the alienation be made for the spiritual benefit of her deceased husband and dedications by ber of a small fraction of the property for the continuous benefit of the soul of the deceased owner have been upheld..067 Such works of public utility have been highly recommended from very ancient times. Sabara 2008 on Jaimini I. 3. 2 refers to the smrti rules about charitable objects which are based on such śruti passages as &amp;lsquo;O Agni, who art ancient and a king, thou art to the man who desires to offer a sacrifice like prapā (shed where water is distributed to travellers) in a desert&amp;rsquo;. In&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 Vānaprastha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/27_vAnaprastha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/27_vAnaprastha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXVII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;VĀNAPRASTHA (forest hermit )&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vaikbānasa appears to have been the ancient name for Vānaprastba. In the Anukramani one hundred Vaikbānasas are said to have been the seers of Rg. IX. 66 and a Vamra Vaikbānasa is the seer of Rg. X. 99. The Tai. A. I. 23 connects the word Vaikhādase with the nakhas of Prajāpati (yo nakbās te vaikhānasāḥ ), 8115 It appears that in ancient times there was some work called Vaikhānasa sāstra which treated of the rules for forest hermits. Gaut. III. 2 uses the word Vaikhānssa for this asrama. Baud. Dh. S. II, 6.19 defines a vānaprastha 116 as one who follows the practices laid down in Vaikhānasa-śāstra, Vṭddha-Gautama (chap. VIII, p. 564 ) appears to suggest that Vaikhānasas and Pancarātrikas were two schools of Vaiṣṇavas, the former calling Viṣṇu by the appellations of Puruṣa, Acyuta and Aniruddha, while the Pañoarātrikas spoke of Viṣṇu ag having the four mūrtis or vyuhas viz. Vasudeva, Saṅkarṣana, Pradyumna and Aniruddha,211? The Par. M. vol. I, part 2, p. 139 after quoting Vas. Dh. S. 9. 11 (śrāmanakenāgaimadhaya ) remarks that Srāmaṇaka is Vaikhā naga-sūtra that propounds the duties of tapasvins. Kalidasa in the Sakuntala speaks of the life led by the charming Sakuntala in Kanva&amp;rsquo;s bermitage as vaikhānasa vrata2118 (I. 27). Manu VI. 21 describes the Vānaprastha as abiding by the views ( mata ) of Vaikhānasa and Medhatihi explains that Vaikhānasa is a sāstra in which the duties of the forest hermit are expounded. The Maha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 Sannyāsa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/28_sannyAsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/28_sannyAsa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXVIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SANNYĀSA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sannyāsa.( the order of ascetics ). That the Chān. Up. was well aware of the three asramas of student-hood, house holder and forest hermit has been shown above (p. 420 ). It is somewhat doubtful whether the Chan. Up. regarded sannyaga as the fourth and the last stage in a man&amp;rsquo;s life when ideally planned. It merely states that one that holds fast by the realization of brahman attains immortality&amp;rsquo;. But it appears that a stage of the abandonment of worldly riches, &amp;amp; life of begging and contemplation of the Absolute and its reali zation had been known to the earliest Upanisads like the Bphadāraṇyaka. Whether it was the fourth stage or whether it could be reached even in the stage of brabmacarya or of a house-holder is left in doubt so far as the older Upaniṣads are concerned. The Jabalopaniṣad (4) has been quoted above (p. 421 ) to show that it gave an option either to regard sannyaga as the 4th stage in a man&amp;rsquo;s life or to resort to it immediately after any of the first two āśramas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 Śrauta Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/29_shrauta_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/29_shrauta_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SRAUTA ( VEDIC) SACRIFICES*&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Introductory A deep study of Vedic saorifices is quite essential for the proper understanding of the Vedic Literature, for arriving at approximately correct statements about the obronology, the development and the stratification of the different portions of that Literature and for the influence that that Literature exerted on the four varṇas and the caste-system, on the splitting up of the brāhmaṇas themselves among several sub-castes 88% and on the institution of gotras and pravaras. Early European scholars generally paid scant attention to the deep study of the Vedic sacrifices and endeavoured to understand the meaning of the Vedas principally by reference to grammar, comparative philology and the comparison of several passages containing the same word or words. Max Mūller put forward a tentative soheme of chronology based mostly on subjective considera tions and prompted by the great prejudice felt by European scholars generally against admitting any great antiquity for the Vedas. Therefore the endeavour of most European scholars has been to show that the mantras could not have been composed before 1400 B.O. It is beyond the scope of this work to enter into any discussion about the dates of the various sections of the Vedic Literature. It must be here said, however, that I do not subscribe to the view that 1400 B, O. is the uppermost limit of the original composition of the Vedic hymns. The hymns may have been composed for aught we know several thousand years&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 Darśapūrṇamāsa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/30_darshapUrNamAsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/30_darshapUrNamAsa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;DARSA-PŪRŅAMĀSA 2272&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Darsapārṇamāsa gaorifice is the pattern or archetype (pra. krti) of all other iṣtis (which are called vikṛtis or modifications). The srauta sūtras therefore describe first the Darsapūrpamāga at length, though in the order of time agnyadhana comes first. Asy. II. 1. 1 says that all iṣçis, sacrifices in which an animal is offered and those in which somis offered are explained by the Paurṇamāsa iṣti. According to Ap. III. 14. 11-13 &amp;amp; person, after he sets up the tbree fires, bas to perform the Darsapūrna māsa throughout his life ( till he becomes a samnyasin) or for thirty years ( after which he may stop ) or till he becomes very old (and unable to perform the rite ).3213&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 Cāturmāsyas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/31_chAturmAsyas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/31_chAturmAsyas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXXI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CĀTURMĀSYAS (seasonal sacrifices ) 2442&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;TD 1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;According to Aśv. II. 14. 1 the term Istyayana comprehends the Cāturmāsyas, Turāyana, Dākṣayana and other iṣtis. The cāturmāsyas are three (or four according to some ), viz. Vai ve deva, Varuṇapraghāsa, Sākamedha ( and Sundsirlya ). Each of these is called &amp;amp; parvan ( part or joint ) of the cāturmāsyas. They are called cāturmāsyas because each of them takes place after four months. 2448 They are performed respectively on the Full Moon days of Phalguna (or Caitra ), of Aṣādba, Kārtika and on the 5th full moon from the day on which the Sākamedha is performed (i.e. on Phālguns) or two or three days before it (com, on Āśv. II. 20.2). They indicate the advent of three seasons viz. vaganta ( spring ), varṣ&amp;amp; (rains) and hemanta *** (autumn). If the Vaiśvadevaparva is performed on Caitra Full Moon, then the Varuṇapraghāsas and Sākamedhas will be performed on Srāvapa and Mārgaśfrṣa Full Moon days respeo. tively. The Tai. Br. 1. 6.8 states the reward secured by the performance of the cāturmāsyas. 2445&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32 Nirūḍhapaśubandha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/32_nirUDhapashubandha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/32_nirUDhapashubandha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXXII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PASUBANDHA OR NIRŪDHAPASUBANDH A 2481&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(immolation of an animal in sacrifice ).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The animal sacrifice is an independent sacrifice and it is also performed in soma sacrifices as a constituent part (anga ). The independent animal sacrifice is oalled nirūdhapasubandha ( offering of an eviscerated animal) and the subordinate ones are called saumika ( Aśv. III. 8. 3-4). The nirudhapaśu is really &amp;amp; modification of an animal sacrifice in somayage (called agniṣomiya paśu ) 28 Jai. VIII. 1. 13 declares, but in many sūtras the full procedure of both is set out in the nirudha. paśu section ( vide Kāt. VI. 10.32 and com. on Kat. VI. 1. 31 ). The nirudhapasubandha itself becomes the prakști (arche type or model) of all other animal sacrifices, except savaniya paśu and anubandhyapasu. The independent animal sacrifice is to be performed every six months or every year by the āhitāgni throughout his life.348% If done once a year it was to be performed in the rainy season (i. e. in Srāvana or Bhadrapada) on New moon or Full moon day or if done six monthly then at the beginning of the southward and northward passages of the Sun ( dakṣiṇāyana and uttarayana ). Then it may have to be performed on any day and not necessarily on amā vāsyā or paurpam.si. According to Asv. (IIL. 1. 2-6) optionally an isti before and after the independent pagubandha rite may be per formed and if performed it is offered either to Agni or to Agai. Viṣṇu or to Agni and Agni-Viṣṇu. In this sacrifice there is a sixth priest called Maitrāvaruna ( or Praśāsts) in addition to the five required in the cāturmāsyas. An udumbara staff is given to the sacrifioer when he is initiated for a sporifice like Agniṣtoma, In the paśubandha when the Maitrāvaruṇa enters the sacrifioial ground after the priests are chosen the adhvaryu&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33 Agniṣṭoma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/33_agniShToma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/33_agniShToma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXXIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;AGNIṢTOMA2529&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sacrifices are often divided for convenience into ieti, pasu and soma. Acoording to Gaut. VIII, 21 and Lat. Sr. V. 4. 24 there are seven forms of some sacrifices, viz. Agniṣtoma, Atyagnistoma, Ukthya, Sodasin, Vājapeya, Atiratra and Aptor yāma. The Agniṣtoma is the model (prakrti) of all soma sacrifices. The Agnistoma is a one day (alkābika or ekāba ) sacrifice and it is an integral part of the Jyotiṣtoma so much so that the two are often identified. Soma sacrifices are classi fied into those that are finished in one day (and so called okāba ), those that are celebrated for more than one day up to twelve (and so called ahina ), those that extend over more than twelve days ( and are called Sattra ). The dvādaśaha is both &amp;amp; sattra and an absna.8530 The Jyotistoma ocoupies generally five days and the chief rites performed on these days are: (1) choosing of priests, madhuparka, dikṣaniyești, consecration of the sacrificer (dikṣā ); (2nd day) Prāyapiya iṣti ( i. e, opening iṣti ), purchase of soma, atitheyesti ( iṣçi offering hospitality to Boma ), Pravargya 2581 Upasad ( homage twice a day in the morning and evening); (3rd day) Pravargya and Upabad twice again ; (4th day) Pravargya and Upasad, Agniprapayana, Agnisomapranayana, havirdhāna-pranayana, animal sacrifice; (5th day called sutya or savaniya) pressing of soma, offering it and drinking it in the morning, mid-day and evening, the udayaniga (concluding iṣti), avabhștha (final purificatory bath). In the following pages only a skeleton outline of&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>34 Other Soma Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/34_Other_Soma_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/34_Other_Soma_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;GTKCHAPTER XXXIV OTHER SOMA SACRIFICES&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sūtras speak of seven forms ( samstbas ) of soma sacrifices. These seven forms are Agniṣtoma, Atyagnistoma, Ukthya, Sodasin, Vajapeya, Atirātra and Aptoryāma (according to Kat. X. 9. 27, Āāv. VI. 11. 1, Lat. V. 4. 24). The first of these has been described in some detail above. Owing to restrictions of space only a few words can be said about the other goma sacrifices. All sutras do not state the same number of soms sacrifices. Ap. XIV. 1.1 and Sat. IX.7. p. 958 expressly say that Ukthya, Sodasin, Atirātra and Aptoryāma are the modifications of Agnistoma and the commentaries of both point out that there were several views on the number of the modifica. tions of the Agniṣtoma. In the Brahmapas the Agniṣtoma, Ukthya, Sodasin and Atiratra are generally mentioned as formg of Jyotiṣtoma (vide Sat. Br. IV, 6. 3. 3, Tai. Br. I. 3.% and 4, which last mentions Vajapeya also ).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>35 Sautrāmaṇī and Other Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/35_sautrAmaNI_and_Other_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p2/35_sautrAmaNI_and_Other_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXXV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SAUTRAMANĪ2660 AND OTHER SACRIFICES&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This rite is included among the seven forms of bavir. yajñas (Gaut. VIII. 20, Lat. V. 4. 23). It is not a soma saorifice but is a combination of an iṣçi with animal sacrifice (Sat. Br. XII, 7, 2. 10). The chief characteristic of it is the offering of sura ( wine ) in it. In modern times milk is offered in place of sura in the Sautrāmapi. According to Lāt. V. 4. 20 and Ap. XIX, 5. 1 there are two kinds of this rite, viz. Kaukili and Caraka-sautrāmaṇi (or the ordinary one). Kaukill is an independent rite, while the ordinary Sautrāmaṇl is performed at the end of the Rajasdya (one month after it ) and also at the end of the piling of the fire-altar ( agniosyana ). Lat. V. 4. 21 states that there is chanting of sāmans only in the Kaukill and not in the other variety and according to Kāt. XIX, 5. 1 (oom.) it is the brahmā that chants the Sāman to Indra in the Bṛhati tune ( viz. Vāj. 8. XX. 30 ) Ap. XIX, 1. 2. states that in the ordinary sautrā mani the procedure is that of the nirūdh pasubandha and that ( XIX, 5. %) in Kaukill also the same procedure applies. There are two fires as in Varuṇapraghasa, but the southern one is not established on a vedi Kat. XIX. 2.1 and V. 4. 12). Some held (as is done by Sat. Br. XII. 7.3.7) there were two vedis behind which two mounds were raised, one for oups of milk and the other for cups of surā. The rite takes four days, during the first three out of which wine is prepared from various ingredients, while on the last day three oups of milk and three of surā are offered to Asvins, Sarasvati and Indra and animals are slaughtered for the same three.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
