<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;07 Mīmāṃsā and Dharmaśāstra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;07 Mīmāṃsā and Dharmaśāstra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>28 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/28_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/28_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>SECTION VII
CHAPTER XXVIII MĪMĀŃSA AND DHARMASĀSTRA
VI
The Yājñavalkya-smrti provides that there are fourteen sources of vidyās (knowledge ) and of Dharma, 1863 viz. Purāṇa, Nyāya, Mimāṁsā, Dharmaśāstra, Angas (six) and the Vedas (four). A similar verse is quoted by some as Manu&amp;rsquo;s, but it is not found in the extant Manusmrti. It is therefore necessary to consider the origin and meaning of the word Mimāmsā, to set out the principal doctrines of that Sāstra, to mention the important rules of interpretation and the maxims of the Mimāṁsā in their application to topics of Dharmaśāstra and to refer to some of the important works of that Śāstra together with their approximate dates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>29 Doctrines of Mīmāṃsā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/29_Doctrines_of_mImAMsA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/29_Doctrines_of_mImAMsA/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXIX
Some Fundamental Doctrines of Purvamimāmsā
Some of the characteristic fundamental doctrines of the Pūrvamimāṁsā will now be set out with some references and a few renarks as to some of them, the views of Prabhakara and his followers being also rarely referred to
(1) Veda is eternal, self-existent, not composed by any author, human or divine, and is infallible. This is the core of the P, M, system. Vide P.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 Mīmāṃsā Priniciples and Dharmaśāstra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/30_mImAMsA_Priniciples_and_dharmashAstra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/07_mImAMsA_and_dharmashAstra/30_mImAMsA_Priniciples_and_dharmashAstra/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXX On Mināmsā principles and rules of interpretation
in relation to Dharmasastra
The Pārvamimamas ayolyed a method of its own and a set of principles for the interpretation of Vedic texts. It is now time to get down and explain some of these principles and rulea and point out how they have been employed by Dharmasastra writers for solving their own difficulties.
The Mimārsā principles and rules of interpretation fall into several groups.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
