<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;राज-नीति-शास्त्रम् on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;राज-नीति-शास्त्रम् on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>R Ajeshvara r Ajan Iti s Ara H</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/rAjeshvara-rAjanIti-sAraH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/rAjeshvara-rAjanIti-sAraH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/bharatiyarajanitiprakasadravidrajeswarishastrisanskrit/page/%E0%A5%A8%E0%A5%A6/mode/1up&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>साम्राज्यनिबन्धनम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/gaNapatiH_sAmrAjya-nibandhanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/rAja-nIti-shAstram/gaNapatiH_sAmrAjya-nibandhanam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sampadanandamishra.medium.com/%E0%A4%B8%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%AE%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%B0%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%9C%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%AF%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%AC%E0%A4%A8%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%A7%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%AE%E0%A5%8D-s%C4%81mr%C4%81jyanibandhanam-by-vasishtha-kavyakantha-ganapati-muni-5d4554e69244&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सम्पदानन्द-मिश्र-प्रस्तावः&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;साम्राज्यनिबन्धनम् sāmrājyanibandhanam is a unique text written by Vasishtha Kavyakantha Ganapati Muni (1878–1936) through which he has proposed a constitution for India (भारतायेदं प्रक्रियते bhāratāyedaṁ prakriyate) . It was one of the Muni’s goals to to see Mother India free from the hands of the Britishers for which he practiced intense Tapas. His goal was not just confined to India’s freedom but he was much concerned about the governance of free India. Keeping this in mind he prepared a constitution for India. This is available to us under the title ‘sāmrājyanibandhanam’. There are five hundred and sixty sutras in twenty chapters. Each chapter has several sub-sections called adhikaraṇa. Altogether there are hundred and twenty-two subsections or adhikaraṇa-s. In the beginning the Muni makes it clear that this text is pertaining to nation head, rules and regulations for the governance by the nation head, the injunctions for the subjects of a nation, their rights, and instructions on the collective responsibility (प्रभुत्वबन्धकं तत्कृत्याधिकारनियामकं प्रजाधिकारमर्यादाविधायकं साङ्घिकधर्ममर्यादोपदेशकं च शास्त्रं साम्राज्यनिबन्धनम् prabhutvabandhakaṁ tatkṛtyādhikāraniyāmakaṁ prajādhikāramaryādāvidhāyakaṁ sāṅghikadharmamaryādopadeśakaṁ ca śāstraṁ sāmrājyanibandhanam).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
