<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;MT on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/smRtiH/manuH/articles/MT/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;MT on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/smRtiH/manuH/articles/MT/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Atomic thoughts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/smRtiH/manuH/articles/MT/atomic-thought/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/smRtiH/manuH/articles/MT/atomic-thought/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
The presence of atomic thought in the manu-smR^iti
One of the most profound philosophical achievements of the ancient Hindus was the development of the vaisheShika darshaNa or the theory of the particulate structure of all matter. While the principle text of the vaisheShikas is kaNAda’s work, there is clear evidence that the philosophy had a more ancient root in the speculative hymns of the vedic saMhitas (for example Atharva Veda [shaunaka shAkha] 12.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diet</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/smRtiH/manuH/articles/MT/diet/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/smRtiH/manuH/articles/MT/diet/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
The MDS, like most other Indo-Aryan cosmogonies envisages all living organisms as emerging from a common ancestor, the prajApati, through several cycles of vertical descent. The MDS notices some kind of hierarchy within which these organisms with a clear suggestion of the division of life into several classes, each containing related life forms (MDS 42-49):
042 येषान् तु ...{Loading}... येषां तु यादृषं कर्म
भूतानाम् इह कीर्तितम् ।
तत् तथा वो ऽभिधास्यामि</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>origin-myths</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/smRtiH/manuH/articles/MT/origin-myths/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/smRtiH/manuH/articles/MT/origin-myths/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Early History of the MDS and the origin mythologies contained in it
Intro Like all dharma shAstras or books of Hindu Law, the mAnava dharma shAstra (MDS) or the manu smRti is mainly concerned with the regulation of the life of an Indo-Aryan. The dharma shAstras have been extensively studied to understand various aspects of ancient Indian life and have also come under uninformed criticism by the various enemies of the Hindus determined find defects in Hindu thought.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
