<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;06 Tāntrik Doctrines and Dharmaśāstra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/06_tAntrik_Doctrines_and_dharmashAstra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;06 Tāntrik Doctrines and Dharmaśāstra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/06_tAntrik_Doctrines_and_dharmashAstra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>26 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/06_tAntrik_Doctrines_and_dharmashAstra/26_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/06_tAntrik_Doctrines_and_dharmashAstra/26_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>SECTION VI
CHAPTER XXVI Tūntrik doctrines and Dharmasastra
In H. of Dh. vol. II. p. 739 while dealing with the worship of Durgā, who is also worshipped as Sakti (cosmic power or energy ), it was stated that the influence of Sākta worship has boon great throughout India and a promise was given that a brief treatment of Sāktiem would follow in a later volume. It is now time to deal with Śāktas and Tantras, which exercised some influence over the Purāṇas and directly and through the Purāṇas over Indian religious ritual and practices in the medieval ages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>27 Nyāsas, Mudrās, etc</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/06_tAntrik_Doctrines_and_dharmashAstra/27_nyAsas_mudrAs_etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/06_tAntrik_Doctrines_and_dharmashAstra/27_nyAsas_mudrAs_etc/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXVII Nyāsas, Mudrās, Yantra, Cakra, Mandala, etc.
One of the important items in the Tantrik ritual and worship is nyūza, which means mentally invoking a god or gods, mantras and holy texts to come to occupy certain parts of the body in order to render the body a pure and fit receptacle for worship and meditation&amp;rsquo;. Soveral works such as the Jayākhya-samhitā (Patala XI), Prapancasāra (VI), Kulārṇava (IV. 18 ff) refer to several kinds of nyāga; the Saradātilaka (IV.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
