<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2.1 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2.1 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Topics of Dharmaśāstra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/01_Topics_of_dharmashAstra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/01_Topics_of_dharmashAstra/</guid>
      <description>Manifold are the topics that have been included under Dharmaśāstra from very ancient times. The Dharma-sūtras of Gautama, Baudhāyana, Āpastamba and Vasiṣṭha deal in greater or less detail principally with the following subjects: the several varṇas (classes), āśramas (stages of life), their privileges, obligations and responsibilities; the saṁskāras performed on an individual (from garbhādhāna to antyeṣṭi); the duties of the brahmacārin (the first āśrama); anadhyāyas (holidays on which Vedic study was stopped); the duties of a snātaka (one who has finished the first stage of life); vivāha (marriage) and all matters connected therewith; the duties of the gṛhastha (house-holder&amp;rsquo;s stage); śauca (daily purification of body); the five daily yajñas; dāna (gifts); bhakṣyābhakṣya (what food should one partake of and what not); śuddhi (purification of persons, vessels, clothes &amp;amp;c.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Varṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/02_varNa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/02_varNa/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER II
VARŅA
The number of works dealing with the origin and characteristics of the caste system in India is legion. Most of them, however, concern themselves with the detailed des cription of the bewildering variety of castes and subdivisions of castes in modern times and their present religious and social customs and usages. The origin of caste has given rise to great speculation and several schools of thought have arisen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Duties and Privileges of Varṇas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/03_Duties_and_Privileges_of_varNas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/03_Duties_and_Privileges_of_varNas/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER III
THE DUTIES, DISABILITIES AND PRIVILEGES
OF THE VARŅAS
at sacrifit means of has certain
The duties and privileges of varṇas occupy a very prominent place in all works on Dharmaśāstra. The study ( of the Vedas), offering sacrifices and giving gifts are said to be the duties absolutely enjoined on the brāhmaṇa, kṣatriya and vaiśya, 18 while each of these three varṇas has certain peculiar privileges, which are its principal means of livelihood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Untouchability</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/04_Untouchability/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/04_Untouchability/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER IV
UNTOUCHABILITY
Those who have written on the Indian caste system bave always been struck by the fact of the existence of certain castes that are treated as untouchables. But it should not be supposed that this is something confined only to India. Even nations that have no caste system at all have often carried out complete segregation of certain people dwelling in their midst, which in essentials is the same as the system of untouchability in India.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Slavery</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/05_Slavery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/05_Slavery/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER V
SLAVERY
Slavery has existed as a constant element in the social and economioal life of all nations of antiquity such as Babylon, Egypt, Greece, Rome and also of many nations of Europe. &amp;ldquo;20 It was however left to such Christian Dations of the West as England and the United States of America to carry on the institution of slavery in the most horrible manner possible never dreamt of by any nation of antiquity, viz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Samskāras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/06_samskAras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/06_samskAras/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER VI
SAMSKĀRAS
Gautama ( II. 1) says that before upanayapa, a boy may act, speak and eat as and what he likes (i. e. may follow his inclinations). Haradatta explains that this does not mean that he can kill a brāhmana or drink liquor, but that there is no restriction, although he be a brāhmana&amp;rsquo;s son, to his selling what is forbidden to a brābmana to sell, or he may eat onions and garlic or stale food or may eat four or five times a day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Upanayana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/07_Upanayana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/07_Upanayana/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER VII
UPANAYANA
This word literally means &amp;rsquo;leading or taking near&amp;rsquo;. But the important question is &amp;rsquo;near what&amp;rsquo;? It appears that it originally meant &amp;rsquo;taking near the ācārya&amp;rsquo; (for instruction); it may have also meant &amp;lsquo;introducing the novice to the stage of student-hood&amp;rsquo;. Some of the gṛhyasūtras bring out this sense clearly e. g. the Hir. gr. I. 5. 2 1 says &amp;ldquo;The teacher then makes the boy utter &amp;lsquo;I have come unto brahmacarya.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Āśramas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/08_Ashramas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/08_Ashramas/</guid>
      <description>T H T pp. 484-85.CHAPTER VIII
AŚRAMAS
east with. Brahmots connected with
theory of the
In the preceding pages several questions connected with brahmacarya have been dealt with. Brahmacarya is, according to the theory of the dharmasutras and smśtis, the first of the four āśramas. Therefore, before proceeding to the next samskāra, viz. vivāha ( marriage ) which is the starting point of the second āśrama, it is necessary to discuss the origin and deve lopment of the idea of asramas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Marriage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/09_Marriage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/09_Marriage/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER IX
MARRIAGE
This is the most inportant of all samskāres. Throughout the ages for which literary tradition is available in India marriage has been highly thought of. The several words that are employed to denote the idea of marriage indicate one or more of the elements of the samskāra of marriage. Such words are udvāha ( taking the girl out of her parental home ), vivāha ( taking the girl away in a special way or for a special purpose i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Madhuparka and Other Usages</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/10_Madhuparka_and_Other_Usages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/10_Madhuparka_and_Other_Usages/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER X MADHUPARKA AND OTHER USAGES
Madhuparka: ( offering of honey by way of honour to 8 distinguished guest). The word literally means&amp;rsquo; a ceremony in which honey is shed or poured&amp;rsquo;(on the hand of a person). The word occurs in the Jaiminiya Upaniṣad-Brāhmaṇa 1283 18. 4. The Nirukta ( I. 16 ) also refers to the usage of offering madhu parka with the word madhuparka repeated thrice. It appears that the Ait.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 Rights and Duties on Marriage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/11_Rights_and_Duties_on_Marriage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/11_Rights_and_Duties_on_Marriage/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XI
POLYGAMY, POLYANDRY AND RIGHTS &amp;amp;
AND DUTIES ON MARRIAGE
Polygamy: Though monogamy 127seems to have been the ideal and was probably the rule, the Vedic literature is full of references to polygamy. Rg. X. 145 (same as Atharvaveda III. 18) is a hymn meant as a charm for weaping the husband&amp;rsquo;s affections from a co-wife. It occurs in the Ap. M. P. (I. 15 ) and Āp. gp. IX.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 Duties of Widows</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/12_Duties_of_Widows/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/12_Duties_of_Widows/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XII
THE DUTIES OF A WIDOW, SOME PRIVILEGES
OF WOMEN AND THE PURDA SYSTEM
Vidhavādharmaḥ So far the social position and the duties and rights of a wife during her husband&amp;rsquo;s life-time have been considered. We shall now consider the rules laid down for a wife if she has the heavy misfortune to become a widow. 1361
The word vidhavā occurs several times in the Rgveda (.8. IV. 18. 12, X.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 Niyoga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/13_Niyoga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/13_Niyoga/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XIII
NIYOGA
Niyoga appointment of a wife or widow to procreate a
son from intercourse with an appointed male ). Great divergence of views prevails about the origin and purpose of this practice. It will be best first to begin by examining the most ancient smṛtis that permitted this practice. Gaut. 1407 18. 4-14 have great bearing on this point, Gaut. 18. 4-8 are: &amp;lsquo;&amp;amp; woman whose husband is dead and who desires offspring may socure &amp;amp; son from her brother-in-law.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14 Remarriage of Widows</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/14_Remarriage_of_Widows/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/14_Remarriage_of_Widows/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XIV
REMARRIAGE OF WIDOWS
Remarriage of widows.&amp;ndash;The word punarbhu is generally applied to a widow that has remarried. Before going into the detailed history of the remarriage of widows it is desirable to probe into the meaning of the word &amp;lsquo;punarbhū &amp;lsquo;.1489 Nārada (stripursa, v. 45 ) says that there are seven sorts of wives (mentioned in order) who have been previously married to another man (parapūrvā); among them, the punarbhũ is of three kinds 1430 and the svairiṇī ( wanton woman) is of four kinds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15 Satī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/15_satI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/15_satI/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XV
SATI ( Self-immolation of widows )
The word is often written as &amp;lsquo;suttee&amp;rsquo; in English works and papers. This subject is now of academic interest in India, since for over a hundred years ( i. e. from 1829 ) self-immolation of widows has been prohibited by law in British India and has been deolared to be a crime. A portion of sec. 1 of the Regulation XVII of 1829 passed by the Governor-General Lord William Bentinck is set out below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 Veśyā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/16_veshyA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/16_veshyA/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XVI
VESYA
Vesya-(Courtezan). This work dealing among other matters with the position of women and marriage in India would be incomplete if nothing were said about prostitutes and concubines. Prostitution has existed from the dawn of history in all countries and in the absence of statistics it is difficult to say whether it flourished more in one country than in another or whether it existed to a greater or lesser extent in ancient days as compared with modern times.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>17 Āhnika and Ācāra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/17_Ahnika_and_AchAra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/17_Ahnika_and_AchAra/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XVII ĀHNIKA AND ACARA
(Daily and periodical duties and ceremonies )
This forms &amp;amp; very important topio of dharmasastra. The daily duties of the brahmacārin have been already desoribed above and those of the vānaprastha and yati will be spoken of later on. Under this section we are concerned principally with the duties of the snātaka (the would-be householder) and the grhastha ( the householder).
Before the āhnika duties are described a few remarks about the importance of the stage of householder would not be out of place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18 Pañca Mahāyajñas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/18_pancha_mahAyajnas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v2p1/18_pancha_mahAyajnas/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XVIII
PAÑCA MAHĀYAJÑAS
Pañca Mahājajñas :-(the five daily great observances or sacrifices).
From early Vedic times five daily observances called mahāyajñas were presoribed. The Sat. Br. (XI. 5. 6. I.) 1864 says &amp;rsquo;there are only five mahāyajñas, they are like great sacrificial sessions, viz. the sacrifice to beings, the sacrifice to men, the sacrifice to the Fathers, the sacrifice to the gods, the sacrifice to brahman (Veda)&amp;rsquo;. These are then briefly defined.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
