<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Clans on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Clans on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Criticism and counters</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/criticism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/criticism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;counters-to-western-criticism-of-the-caste-system&#34;&gt;Counters to western criticism of the caste system&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/gregor.maehle/posts/1134184173262307&#34;&gt;FB15&lt;/a&gt;,) There is a fundamental problem here. The assumption that the &amp;ldquo;caste system&amp;rdquo; (not as you imagine it, but as it actually existed), was an inferior and immoral social system. This is a claim no one here seems to challenge, by which I presume that they&amp;rsquo;ve bought into it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Caste system&amp;rdquo; was not a fair system (in many meanings of the word &amp;ldquo;fair&amp;rdquo;). For example, my ancestors were just ineligible to rule a country, or focus on making money. But so is *your* current system, and the systems of *your* ancestors - they are and were unfair. In the current system, people want to sweep inequalities and hierarchies under the rug - sort of like saying: &amp;ldquo;there&amp;rsquo;s no prostitution in our country&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;My&amp;rdquo; system, acknowledged what exists naturally, and attempted to regulate and harmonize it.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Your forefathers&amp;rsquo; pagan pietas did not survive the onslaught of Abrahamisms (just like the buddhists of Afghanistan and central asia). Mine did very well in comparison. They preserved wonderful practices that everyone enjoys today such as Yoga, meditation, tantra, chanting, dances etc.; while Apollo and Jupiter lie in Roman and Greek ruins.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Newly encountered tribes were harmoniously brought into the system, while preserving their internal practices and autonomy (not made victims of a vicious genocide).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is more than enough points there to argue that, in terms of gross happiness, overall accomplishment and sheer survival, our &amp;ldquo;caste system&amp;rdquo; was in no way inferior or wholly immoral.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, when circumstances changed and the age turned, we happily changed due to our internal motivation (just as in Japan) - &amp;ldquo;High&amp;rdquo; caste people were at the very forefront of this remodeling. Now, they&amp;rsquo;ve gradually mechanized the unclean occupations, ridding us of untouchability as well. With mass education and printing, education and literate occupations are more widespread. I now do a shUdra&amp;rsquo;s job for a living ( as a computer programmer).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Future</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/future/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/future/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;justification-for-change&#34;&gt;Justification for change&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;jAti-varNa system emerged as a social convenience, and hindu-s are free (and happy) to change it after the need for it has expired.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As shrI-golvAlkar said: &amp;ldquo;varNa-vyavasthA is a social vyavasthA, not an avasthA&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The two occasions on which the Purusha Sukta is invoked in its first chapter there is a rider attached to it &amp;ndash; “for the sake of prosperity and flourishing in the worlds” in the first case (../1.31) and ‘‘in order to protect this universe” in the second (1.87). There is no such condition attached to the formulation of the four classes in the Purusha Sukta itself. Manu, unlike the Purusha Sukta, makes the doctrine of the four varnas accountable in terms of human flourishing. And what if the condition is not fulfilled? According to the Manusmrti (4.176), it should then be given up.&amp;rdquo; [(AS18)[https://swarajyamag.com/ideas/gender-caste-and-sanskrit-theres-space-for-a-multitude-of-views-and-none-need-prevail]] (See quotes in &lt;a href=&#34;varna-theory/&#34;&gt;varna-theory page&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The jAti/ varNa system (as classically concieved) no longer benefits the society without modification.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;current-maladaptiveness-of-varna-by-birth&#34;&gt;Current maladaptiveness of varNa by birth&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this post-industrial world we have:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lineage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/gotras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/gotras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;utility&#34;&gt;Utility&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pride in ancestral accomplishments can be a great motivator in one&amp;rsquo;s own life (especially when it comes to following dharma).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;examples&#34;&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If brAhmaNa archaka-s serve in those village temples suffering paltry salaries lower than what the watchman or sweeper gets, it is because of kulAbhimAna and sense of hereditary duty than anything else. Were it not for this familial urge and pride, the shAkha-s of veda which have come down to us would not at all have survived. (To illustrate the point, now that anyone can go to certain veda-pAThashAla-s and study the veda-s, relatively speaking, how many non-brAhmaNa-s have taken to them fully?)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non brAhmaNa gotras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/abrAhmaNa-gotram/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/abrAhmaNa-gotram/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As late as the 11th c. AD, in the Gotra-Pravara-Manjari of Purusottama-Pandita, it is written as still prevalent that the gotra-pravara system applies to brahman (arsheya) lineages only: the Baudhayana-Pravara-Adhyaya mentions that the (biological) descendants of the seven rishis plus Agastya as the eighth are called gotra: this is the arsha-gotra (pita-putra parampara).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The conventional sense is used as laukika-gotra (guru-shishya parampara/which non-brahmans use). Over the centuries, during to social and cultural changes, various groups in India have adopted the gotra system, but the pravara system still applies only to brahman gotras.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
