<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Hindu ID on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Hindu ID on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Benefits प्रयोजनम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/benefits/</guid>
      <description>Union and protection The protective umbrella of hinduism can resist and push back rabid memes [Eg. Indonesian dayaks - NYT]. Fitness qualification In its hard classical form, it meets this important qualification: One should never have alleigence to an ideology that reduces one&amp;rsquo;s (overall: individual/ group) fitness (in the biological sense). Vaccination against bad dogma A person or society not vaccinated with Chicken Pox is susceptible to Small Pox. At a personal level, many have not had the typically hindu/ pagan experience of dogma *and transcending dogma* [an essential feature of the diverse Hindu tradition, unlike the book-centred Abrahamisms].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hindus with updated beliefs</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/hindus-with-updated-beliefs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/hindus-with-updated-beliefs/</guid>
      <description>Many highly regarded, erudite and practicing hindu-s are/ have been quite happy to update their belief systems with modern scientific findings (eg: theory of evolution). They too do not find the concept of karma and rebirth to be central to the hindu tradition which they hold so dear.
shatAvadhAnI gaNesh (source: his lectures on &amp;ldquo;Foundations of Indian Culture&amp;rdquo;), the great poet and avadhAna-artist, an advaita-vedAntin. The fine scholar M Hiriyanna, who famously said (I paraphrase): &amp;ldquo;Art can replace religion in this age of rationality and equality&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/philosophy/</guid>
      <description>I use the term Philosophy in the Sanskrit cosmopolis&#39;&#39; (Sanskrit philosophy&amp;quot; for short) in order to cover all philosophical texts produced in a world in which Sanskrit was a major intellectual player, even for authors who wrote in other languages. - Elisa Freschi
Might use &amp;ldquo;Hindu philosophy&amp;rdquo; to cover all philosophical texts produced in a world in which Hindus were a major intellectual player, even for authors who belonged to counter-religions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Religion?</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/social-cultivation/hindu-id/religion/</guid>
      <description>Source of the problem Hinduism is not a single fully consistent theological system. Rather, it is a set of coexisting systems which acknowledge each others&amp;rsquo; deities and lore in various ways. Conceptually, but not at a social/ higher level, it is wrong to bring Hinduism to the level of Christianity/ Islam etc.. Abrahamist diseases more easily map to subclasses of Hindu darshana-s A view / darshana in the hindu context talks about these 5 issues: 1] jagat (world) 2] jIva (the individual) 3] Ishvara (God) 4] bandha (bondage) 5] moxa (liberation).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
