<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 Rājadharma on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 Rājadharma on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/01_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/01_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>RĀJADHARMA
( GOVERNMENT AND STATECRAFT)
CHAPTER I
Rajadharma has been a subject of discussion in works on dharmasastra from very ancient times. The Āp. Dh. S. II. 9.25.1 says &amp;ldquo;The general and special dharnus of all varṇas have been explained: but now we shall declare the dharmas of a king in particular! Āp. then states that the king should cause to be built a capital and a palace, the gates of which both should face the south; that the palace should be in the heart of the capital; that in front of the capital there was to be a hall called &amp;lsquo;aman trana&amp;rsquo; (hall of invitation); that to the south of the town there was to be an assembly house with doors on the north and south.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Seven Aṅgas of Rājya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/02_Seven_angas_of_rAjya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/02_Seven_angas_of_rAjya/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER II.
SEVEN ANGAS OF RAJYA
According to almost all of our authorities a state (rūjya) is constituted by seven elements 20 viz. svāmin (ruler or sovereign), amūtya (minister), janapada or rāṣtra (the territory of the State and its people), durga ( fortified city or capital), kośa ( accumula ted wealth in the ruler&amp;rsquo;s treasury), dandu (army), mitra (friends or allies). These seven are called angas or praktis. The word praksti in works on politics is also used for the constituents of a circle of states (of a mandala).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Duties of the Ruler</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/03_Duties_of_the_Ruler/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/03_Duties_of_the_Ruler/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER tft
DUTIES AND RESPONSIBILITIES OF
THE RULER.
All works are agreed that the first and foremost duty of the king is the protection of subjects. Sāntiparva (68.1-4) notes that all the seven expounders of polity (rājaśāstraprane tāraḥ) named by it extol protection as the highest dharma of the king. Manu VII. 144 states that the protection of subjects is the highest dharma and Kālidāsa in Raghuvamsa 14.67 alludes to this dictum of Manu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Ministers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/04_Ministers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/04_Ministers/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER IV
MINISTERS
Amatya -The second of the seven elements of rājya is the amālya, which word may be translated as &amp;lsquo;minister.&amp;rsquo; There are three words that are interchangeable though sometimes dis tinguished, viz. amõtya, saciva and mantrin, the first being the oldest of the three. A Kārikā on Pāṇini (IV. 2. 104) teaches the formation of the word with the affix tyap (tya ) from ama meaning near or with&amp;rsquo;( vide Mahābhāṣya, vol.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Rāṣṭra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/05_rAShTra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/05_rAShTra/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER V
RĀSTRA (THE TERRITORY OF A STATE)
DDT WI
The word &amp;lsquo;rastra&amp;rsquo; occurs even in the Rgveda (IV. 42.1, &amp;lsquo;mania dvitā rāstram kṣatriyasya”)-‘mine is the kingdom on both sides (or in both spheres)&amp;rsquo; says king Trasadasyu. In Rg. VII. 34,11 Varuna is praised as the Lord of rāṣtras ( rājā rāṣtrāṇām &amp;amp;c.). In Rg. VII. 84.2 and X. 109. 3 the word rāstra occurs. In a very famous benedictory 175 passage of the Tai.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Durgā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/06_Durga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/06_Durga/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER VI DURGA ( FORT OR CAPITAL)
Manu IX, 294 places the capital (pura) even before rastra. Medhātithi (on IX. 295 ) and Kullūka explain that the loss of the capital is a more serious danger than even the loss of some territory, because if the capital, which possesses all the stocks of food, in which are centred the principal elements and the army, is saved, then it is possible to retrieve even lost territory and to protect the country.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Kośa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/07_kosha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/07_kosha/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER VII
KOSA (TREASURY OR FINANCE)
Kaut (II. 1) states that a king whose treasury is depleted preys upon the citizens and the rural population and (II. 8) very 231 rightly remarks that all undertakings depend upon kośa (financial position of the king), therefore the king must pay the first attention to kośa. Gautama (as cited by 8. V. p. 46 ) holds that kośa is the basis or support of the other six elements of the State.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Bala</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/08_Bala/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/08_Bala/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER VIII
BALA (THE ARMY).
Bala is also called danda in Kaut and elsewhere. Accord ing to Sumantu dapda means &amp;lsquo;punishment, corporal or monetary&amp;rsquo; and the army with its four arms is included by Sumantu under kośa ( acc. to $. V. p. 46).260 In the Rgveda we have frequent references to armies, weapons, battles &amp;amp;c. The word senāni occurs in Rg. X. 84. 2 where Manyu ( martial Fury ) is invoked to be the Commander.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Mitra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/09_Mitra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/09_Mitra/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER IX SUHRT OR MITRA (ALLY OR FRIEND).
Manu inculcates the necessity of making friends in VII. 208 and cites the qualities of a good friend (for. a king) &amp;lsquo;a king does not prosper by the acquisition of gold and land so much as by securing a firm friend who would be powerful in future, though he may be of depleted resources at the time. That friend, though a weak one, is commended, who is righteous, grateful, whose subjects (or ministers) are contented, who is attached and who pursues (to the end) work undertaken&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Purpose of the Study of Rājadharma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/10_Purpose_of_the_Study_of_rAjadharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/1_rAjadharma/10_Purpose_of_the_Study_of_rAjadharma/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER X
PURPOSE OF THE STUDY OF RĀJADHARMA
AND THE ENDS OF THE STATE
In the preceding pages an attempt has been made to present a picture of the theory and practice of Government and state craft as delineated by ancient and medieval Indian writers on dharmaśāstra and arthaśāstra. One feature that would strike any reader is the religious colouring with which all theories and ideals are suffused. Another is that the ideal set before rulers and their officers is a highly moral one.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
