<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;05 Gaṅgā Snāna on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;05 Gaṅgā Snāna on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Puṇya and Pāpa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/01_puNya_and_pApa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/01_puNya_and_pApa/</guid>
      <description>A background for the introduction to Puṇya and Pāpa.
“What do puṇya and pāpa mean? Generally no one ponders about that. The words—‘Puṇya is accrued”, “Pāpa has perished”—uttered by people casually, sometime sound as though they have better knowledge than those who have understood them clearly. But, are they visible to the naked eyes like the coming and going of, say a cow or a calf? Then what are they? A solid?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Gaṅgā eminence</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/02_gangA_eminence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/02_gangA_eminence/</guid>
      <description>The eminence of the holy waters of Gaṅgā
The word Gaṅgā means something which gives mukti (‘सद्गतिं गमयतीति गङ्गा’) The word applies to a goddess and also to the river presided over by that goddess. Śāstras and traditions openly praise the holy bath in the sacred river in similitude with the (dhyāna) of that goddess. They profusely praise not just the holy bath in the river and drinking of its sacred water, but also the very sight and the remembrance of it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Gaṅgā - ailments and health</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/03_gangA_-_ailments_and_health/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/03_gangA_-_ailments_and_health/</guid>
      <description>03 Gaṅgā - ailments and health
The power of Gaṅgā to cure ailments and to bestow health. Many Ayurvedic texts tell us that, besides absolving people of sins, and blessing with Sadgati, the water of Gaṅgā is very tasty, removes a number of diseases, and helps to acquire good health.
“All the rivers which take their origin on the slopes of the Himālaya mountains have medicinal value. Their waters consumed by devarshis are really beneficial” says Caraka.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Modern views</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/04_Modern_views/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/04_Modern_views/</guid>
      <description>Views on the quality (properties) of Gaṅgā by people belonging to other religions, and experiments by modern physicians and their opinions.
History tells us that the healthy qualities of the waters of Gaṅgā have attracted not just the Hindus, but the followers of other religions also who were cognizant of its use and were dxiligently consuming it. A travelogue writer by name Iben Batuta tells that Mohammed Bin Tughlak used to get Gaṅgā water from Doulathabād regularly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Gaṅgatīrtha qualities</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/05_gangatIrtha_qualities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/05_gangatIrtha_qualities/</guid>
      <description>A Discussion on the praise of the qualities of Gaṅgatīrtha.
a) A discussion on its capacity to cure diseases
We have already noted scriptural evidences and also the statements of modern physicians based on experiments, which declare that Gaṅgatīrtha has the potential to remove sins and cure physical ailments. Here, some people argue “Only because it has the power to cure bodily ailments and improve health, it is called holy water.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Representative of Principles-a symbol</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/06_Representative_of_Principles-a_symbol/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/06_Representative_of_Principles-a_symbol/</guid>
      <description>06 Representative of Principles-a symbol
“The river of jnāna and dharma itself is the spiritual Gaṅgā. This is nothing but the image of God in the form of water.”-So say the jnānis. Also, we come across compositions of jnānis which express the following sense.-“The Idā nādī in our body is Gaṅgā. Piṅgalā is Yamunā and Sushumnā is Sarasvatī. And the place of confluence of these three viz. the place of meditational immersion between eyebrows (bhrūmadhya is nothing but the tīrtharājaprayāga.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 The map of tattvas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/07_The_map_of_tattvas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/07_The_map_of_tattvas/</guid>
      <description>Śrī Raṅgamahāguru used to expound-“The basin of Gaṅgā and the holy pilgrimages along its banks are indeed the maps drawn in the land of Bhārata by mother nature. This can be made clear by one or two examples.
Lord Mahādeva, who had held Gaṅgā captive in his head, laid her down at Bindusaras, to bless Bhagīratha. We see in the Rāmāyaṇa that the river branched into seven streams while descending.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 The forms and features of Goddess *Gaṅgā*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/08_The_forms_and_features_of_Goddess_gangA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/08_The_forms_and_features_of_Goddess_gangA/</guid>
      <description>08 The forms and features of Goddess Gaṅgā
Āgamas, history and purāṇas proclaim Goddess Gaṅgā as a river of divine knowledge, a stream of dharma and an embodiment of the supreme power of the Almighty. In the dhyānaśloka of that river, it is described that Gaṅgā has a unique third eye, holds a lotus, a pot and a rosary in her hands, sports varadamudrā, and has a crocodile as her vehicle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Ordinary view</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/09_Ordinary_view/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/09_Ordinary_view/</guid>
      <description>Answers coming from an ordinary vision
When viewed ordinarily, these appear to be the forms imagined by a poet. “As Gaṅgā is in the form of a river, a water filled pot is placed in her hand. The small quantity of water that can be filled in the kalaśa, later expands and flows as a great river.
“The term tīrtha also means āgama or vidyā (निपानागमयोस्तीर्थं). To suggest that the garland of letters i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Exrta-ordinary view</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/10_Exrta-ordinary_view/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/10_Exrta-ordinary_view/</guid>
      <description>10 Exrta-ordinary view
Answers that are perceptible to the extraordinary vision
But, when the disposition (of a person) is purified and the tattvas are pursued with an inner vision, it can be realized that they (the form of Gaṅgā and the parapheralia) are not mere imageries but sublime forms that are clearly and naturally visible in the divine ground. In the chapter ‘Devatā vigrahatattvādhikaraṇa of the Brahmasūtras, the subject matter viz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 Some problems</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/11_Some_problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/utsavAH/articles/rangapriya-on-festivals/01_Axaya_TRtIyA/05_gangA_snAna/11_Some_problems/</guid>
      <description>Some problems posed by the stories relating to Gaṅgā:
The Gaṅgā is a river which takes its birth at the top of the Himālayas. Let us believe that its water has the power to cure a number of ailments. But Itihāsas, purāṇas and āgamas pronounce strange statements about the river. “It is the holy water which was in the Kamanḍalu of Brahma Deva. When he (i.e. Brahma) the Lord of Satyaloka, washed the lotus feet of Trivikrama Nārāyaṇa, Gaṅgā took birth (there).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
