<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;गोरक्षा on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;गोरक्षा on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Context in conflict</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Context_in_conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Context_in_conflict/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;hindu-vs-muslim&#34;&gt;Hindu vs Muslim&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The context of hindu-muslim conflict (with the latter using cow slaughter to stick it to the hindus - Shaykh Ahmad Sirhindi,  Khwaja Moinuddin Chishti of Ajmer  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsgram.com/beef-controversy-origins-of-beef-consumption-in-india/&#34;&gt;NG15-B&lt;/a&gt;]) makes cow protection a particularly important issue.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;hindu-european-conflict&#34;&gt;hindu-european conflict&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dharampal writes in his book “The British Origin of Cow-Slaughter in India”: “‘It can be reasonably assumed that there was very little cow killing after about 1700 AD since the domination of Islam waned and converts to Islam did not take to eating of cow flesh.”&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;This steep increase in the British population (especially of those in the military) in India resulted in many fold increase in cow-slaughtering and beef consumption. Lodha report notes that, in some places, the increase was as high as fourfold. The report further notes that as against 20,000 cows per year that were killed during Islamic rule, around 30,000 cows were killed every year at the height of the British period.&amp;rdquo;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsgram.com/beef-controversy-origins-of-beef-consumption-in-india/&#34;&gt;NG15-B&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cross-cultural comparison</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Cross-cultural_comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Cross-cultural_comparison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;iran&#34;&gt;Iran&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Zoroastrian religion forbids cow flesh for consumption. The cow also figures symbolically in several aspects of that religion, and cow urine is drunk at the Navjote sacrament. It is another matter that Westernized Anglophile Parsis have ignored the dietary laws among many other things. &amp;hellip; even until recently, cows were not a part of regular diet in Iran. It was during Westernization under the Qajar dynasty that the Brits &amp;amp; French introduced beef eating big time (which is now widespread in Iran). That shift was a traumatic cultural change, especially in the countryside. Watch the Persian movie &amp;ldquo;Gaav&amp;rdquo; (Cow) [&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x9gthjarCho&#34;&gt;YT1&lt;/a&gt;], which depicts the attachment an Irani peasant has for his cow, and how the new beef industry sponsored cattle mafia snatch his kine from him, causing him to have a nervous breakdown. Khomeini, who was initially against film as a medium was convinced to allow the film industry to continue to operate after he watched that movie.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Current situation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Current_situation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Current_situation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Visceral reactions are an essential expression of a strong Hindu cultural immune system. The easier it is to identify the barbarian, the better the chances of survival of this very exalted &amp;ldquo;sanAtana&amp;rdquo; dharma.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Current cow protection efforts&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Comfortable sanctuaries for cows (go-shAlA)&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;examples - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g8Us1oGMSzQ&amp;amp;app=desktop&#34;&gt;pANDuranga16&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dalit communities and beef&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;A recent mapping of the food habits of SC communities published by Swarajya Magazine clearly shows that though 80% of the SC communities are meat eaters, they discourage beef.&amp;rdquo; [&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsgram.com/beef-controversy-origins-of-beef-consumption-in-india/&#34;&gt;NG15-B&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Royal enforcement</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Royal_enforcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Royal_enforcement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;It came to be a prime duty of the king to protect cows from slaughter in his domain.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(गोब्राह्मणेभ्यश् शुभमस्तु नित्यम् …)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Shivaji cut off hands of cow killers, gangAdevI decries wanton cow slaughter by the mlecCha-s.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;kerala&#34;&gt;keraLa&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Duarte Barbosa, a 16th century Portuguese writer : “The King then asks him if he will maintain the customs and rules of the other Nayres (Nairs), and he and his kinsmen respond ‘ Yes.’ Then the King commands him to gird on his right side a sword with a red sheath, and when it is girt on he causes him to approach near to himself and la, his right hand on his head, saying therewith certain words which none may hear, seemingly a prayer, and then embraces him saying ‘ Paje Gubrantarca, that is to say ‘ Protect cows and Bramenes (Brahmins)” [&lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.co.in/books?id=cAgkDwAAQBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PT40&#34;&gt;GB&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A similar oath was made by Samuthiris or Zamorins, the Nair kings of Calicut before their royal coronation “At Yagneswaram he is met by Vemaneheri Namputiri,  a descendant of Melattur Agnihotri. The Eralped (Zamorin) gives him an ola (text), promising to protect Brahmins, temples and cows.” [&lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/TheZamorinsOfCalicut&#34;&gt;Ar&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;It is interesting to note that Aithihyamala, a 19th century work detailing many folklore and legends of Kerala also records an incident in which the famous 18th century Raja of Cochin, Rama Varma Shaktan Thampuran executed a Muslim who had killed a cow.  The Raja also refused to observe Shivaratri vrata since the Muslim had killed the cow on that day.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
