<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 chāturmāsya on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 chāturmāsya on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Importance of *cāturmāsya*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/01_Importance_of_chAturmAsya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/01_Importance_of_chAturmAsya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;01 Importance of &lt;em&gt;cāturmāsya&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Though the name &lt;em&gt;cāturmāsya&lt;/em&gt; is familiar to many of us in the row of &lt;em&gt;vratas&lt;/em&gt;, there is an impression that it is related to monks and some &lt;em&gt;Maḍi hengasaru&lt;/em&gt; (some women in the olden days who were very orthodox) and people belonging to the other &lt;em&gt;Āśramas&lt;/em&gt; need not consider it. This is a result of misunderstanding. From the view point of &lt;em&gt;śāstras&lt;/em&gt; this is a &lt;em&gt;parva&lt;/em&gt; that should be observed by everyone. This does not belong either to the category called &lt;em&gt;naimittika karma&lt;/em&gt;, a rite which should be performed because of a &lt;em&gt;nimitta;&lt;/em&gt; Or a &lt;em&gt;kāmya karma&lt;/em&gt; a rite which is performed only for the fulfillment of a specific desire, which need not be observed otherwise. It happens to be a &lt;em&gt;nitya karma&lt;/em&gt; only, as it belongs to a category in which certain rituals are mandatory at some distinct times, and the blemish of sinfulness may occur if they are not observed. There is no doubt that it must be specially observed by &lt;em&gt;sanyāsis&lt;/em&gt;. But the &lt;em&gt;śāstras&lt;/em&gt; say that is the duty of all i.e. people belonging to all &lt;em&gt;Āśramas,&lt;/em&gt; to observe it to the extent possible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Names and their etymology:</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/02_Names_and_their_etymology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/02_Names_and_their_etymology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;02 Names and their etymology:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As this &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt; comes regularly for a period four months every year. it is called &lt;em&gt;‘cāturmāsya’&lt;/em&gt;. (&lt;em&gt;“Caturshu māseshu bhavah”&lt;/em&gt;). As all the four months of observance are the months of rainy season, it is called &lt;em&gt;“Varshartu Vrata”&lt;/em&gt; also.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Description of the time of observance:</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/03_Description_of_the_time_of_observance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/03_Description_of_the_time_of_observance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;03 Description of the time of observance:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt; should be begun on the day of &lt;em&gt;ekādaśī&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;dvādaśī&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;pūrṇimā&lt;/em&gt; of the bright half of &lt;em&gt;Āshādha māsa&lt;/em&gt;. It must be begun either on the days of &lt;em&gt;karkāṭaka saṅkramaṇa&lt;/em&gt; or, in case of difficulties, on the day of &lt;em&gt;Tulā saṅkramaṇa&lt;/em&gt;. Whatever may be the day it is begun, it should be concluded on the day of &lt;em&gt;utthāna dvādaśī&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;आषाढशुक्लद्वादश्यां पौर्णमास्यामथापि वा ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;चातुर्मास्यव्रतारम्भं कुर्यात् कर्कटसङ्क्रमे ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अभावे तु तुलार्केऽपि मन्त्रेण नियमं व्रती ॥ (वराह पुराण)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Few objections</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/04_Few_objections/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/04_Few_objections/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A few objections pertaining to the observance of this &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt; and answers to them.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;avaidikatā&#34;&gt;avaidikatā&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(a) The name of this &lt;em&gt;yajna&lt;/em&gt; called &lt;em&gt;cāturmāsya&lt;/em&gt; appears both in &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;smṛtis&lt;/em&gt;. But it is not the famous &lt;em&gt;cāturmāsya&lt;/em&gt; mentioned in the &lt;em&gt;purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;s that is being currently practiced. When we study the &lt;em&gt;vedaśāstras,&lt;/em&gt; we find that there are some season-related &lt;em&gt;vidhis,&lt;/em&gt; which have to be observed on the full moon days of the months of &lt;em&gt;caitra, phālguṇa, Āshāḍha&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;kārtika&lt;/em&gt;. They are called &lt;em&gt;‘vaiśva deva’&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;varuṇa praghāsa,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;śākhamedha&lt;/em&gt;. Other than this, there is a fourth (&lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt;) by name &lt;em&gt;‘śunāsīrīya’&lt;/em&gt;. These are the four &lt;em&gt;cāturmāsya&lt;/em&gt;s prescribed in the &lt;em&gt;Śrutis&lt;/em&gt;. This alone is the &lt;em&gt;vaidika cāturmāsya&lt;/em&gt; that has been prescribed by &lt;em&gt;Āpstamba, Āśwalāyana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;yājnavalkya&lt;/em&gt; and other &lt;em&gt;smṛtikāras&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 The modalities of the *vrata*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/05_The_modalities_of_the_vrata/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/05_The_modalities_of_the_vrata/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;05 The modalities of the &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Those who observe the &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt; should go on fast, worship &lt;em&gt;Śrī Nārāyaṇa&lt;/em&gt; and pray him “O Lord! I am observing this &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt; in your &lt;em&gt;Sānnidhya&lt;/em&gt;. This can be completed without hurdles, only with your blessings. In case my life departs from the body in the middle of this &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt;, let me obtain the fruits, of the &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt; then also with your blessings.” And, reducing the worldly activities as much as possible, one should worship Lord &lt;em&gt;Nārāyaṇa&lt;/em&gt; who is delightful in the posture of sleep, with meditation, stotra and worship etc. One should follow &lt;em&gt;Brahmacarya&lt;/em&gt;. One should give up &lt;em&gt;Rāga&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;dvesha&lt;/em&gt;. Lies should not be uttered. Robes suitable to the &lt;em&gt;vratadīksha&lt;/em&gt; should be put on. One should abstain from violence to animals. Food prohibited by scriptures and causing disturbance to the &lt;em&gt;Samyama&lt;/em&gt; should not be consumed. Liquor and meat should be given up during all the four months. It is good to give up some particular food items during some months. For example, One should not use vegetables in &lt;em&gt;śrāvaṇa māsa,&lt;/em&gt; curds in &lt;em&gt;bhādrapadamāsa&lt;/em&gt;, milk in &lt;em&gt;āśvayuja māsa&lt;/em&gt; and pulses in &lt;em&gt;kārtika māsa.&lt;/em&gt; (These are respectively called the &lt;em&gt;śākavrata, dadhivrata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;kshīravrata&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;dhānyavrata)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 The benefits of observing *Cāturmāsya*:</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/06_The_benefits_of_observing_chAturmAsya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/06_The_benefits_of_observing_chAturmAsya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;06 The benefits of observing &lt;em&gt;Cāturmāsya&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Those who have observed the &lt;em&gt;vrata&lt;/em&gt; with a &lt;em&gt;Kāmyadṛshti&lt;/em&gt; giving up jaggery, oil, pungent oil, betel nut and betel leaves, ghee, fruits, vegetable dishes curds and milk, will obtain the benefits of sweet voice, beautiful body, destruction of enemies, enjoyment of material pleasures, loveliness, intelligence and progeny of many of sons, cooked food and sweet dishes food and attainment of the &lt;em&gt;goloka&lt;/em&gt; respectively. If one gives up these for the love of God, he will obtain devotion to God through the restraint of senses. By observing &lt;em&gt;Brahmacarya&lt;/em&gt; one will develop strength of the body, the senses, the mind, and intellect, and the accomplishment of &lt;em&gt;dhyāna yoga&lt;/em&gt;. By worshipping God who is in the posture of sleep the &lt;em&gt;jnāna, bhakti&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Vairāgyas&lt;/em&gt; of the person will increase. &lt;em&gt;Gṛhasthas&lt;/em&gt; obtain enjoyments which are not opposed to &lt;em&gt;yoga&lt;/em&gt;, by worshipping God who in the posture of just woken up from sleep.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 *Cāturmāsya* of *sanyāsis*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/07_chAturmAsya_of_sanyAsis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/rangapriya-on-festivals/03_ChAturmAsya/07_chAturmAsya_of_sanyAsis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;07 &lt;em&gt;Cāturmāsya&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;sanyāsis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sanyāsis&lt;/em&gt; have some more distinct &lt;em&gt;Vidhis&lt;/em&gt; in addition to the dos and don’ts regarding food.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;sanyāsi&lt;/em&gt; should undertake the observance on the full moon day of the month of &lt;em&gt;āshāḍha&lt;/em&gt;. If there are difficulties, he is allowed to take the vow till the next &lt;em&gt;pañcamī&lt;/em&gt;. If that &lt;em&gt;pañcamī&lt;/em&gt; also passes (without the vow) he will be subjected to &lt;em&gt;Prāyaścitta.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अनेन विधिना भिक्षुः आषाढ्यां सुसमाहितः ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;प्रायश्चित्तेन युज्येत पाम्यूर्ध्वं व्रजेद्यदि ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
