<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/pUjA/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/pUjA/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>IndoEuropean expansions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/pUjA/articles/MT_lekhAH/2022-04-25_indo-european-expansions-and-iconography-revisitin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/pUjA/articles/MT_lekhAH/2022-04-25_indo-european-expansions-and-iconography-revisitin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2022/04/25/indo-european-expansions-and-iconography-revisiting-the-anthropomorphic-stelae/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Indo-European expansions and iconography: revisiting the anthropomorphic stelae&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;was-there-an-early-indo-european-iconography-the-anthropomorphic-stelae&#34;&gt;Was there an early Indo-European iconography? The anthropomorphic stelae&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is no linguistic evidence for the presence of iconic or temple worship among the early Indo-Europeans. However, after their migrations, when they settled in the lands of sedentary peoples, they adopted a range of religious icons often stylistically influenced by local traditions. Nevertheless, there are some clear iconographic features of their deities and other divine entities that shine through these local styles (to be discussed in later notes).+++(5)+++ This suggests that, even if iconic worship was not the central focus of their religion, they had definitive visualizations for their deities that emerged early in IE tradition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early temples and iconic worship</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/pUjA/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-02-23_early-temples-and-iconic-worship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/pUjA/articles/MT_lekhAH/2008-02-23_early-temples-and-iconic-worship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2008/02/23/early-temples-and-iconic-worship/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is nearly inconceivable for the average modern Hindu to imagine his religion as being aniconic. Worship at temples is an average Hindu’s major or only of religious activity, and it is not uncommon for practically every Hindu to keep some household images or pictures of deities. Yet, there is hardly any sign of temples or worship in temples in the vedic saMhitA-s, which are dominated by fire and soma rituals. Even in the itihAsa-s, while temples are mentioned several times, their description is not given much prominence. For example, in the rAmAyana&#xA;(5.43.1-5) hanumAn is mentioned as breaking a large and lofty temple in&#xA;lankA, but no other specific details of it are provided. The temple in the nikumbhilA grove in lankA is mentioned as a spot where meghanAda was to perform a fire rite for invincibility, but again hardly any details of this temple are mentioned. In the great bhArata too temples are mentioned, but are hardly prominent in its enormous bulk that otherwise covers an extraordinary diversity of topics. In itihAsas as a whole, references to temples, typically termed chaitya, are an incidental element in the context of describing holy tIrtha-s or urban centers (see below). The earliest available works in the dravidian languages, the tamiL puranAnuru and akanAnuru also do not display any notable dilation on temples, despite having several religious themes in them. The mAnava dharma shAstra and other early dharma works too are either silent or limited in their allusions to temples. In fact, the MDS recommends against brAhmaNa-s who earn their living as temple priests from being employed as a sacrificial invitees (3.152) or as recipients of brahminical donations (3.180).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The worship of the pa~nchAkSharI vidyA of shiva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/pUjA/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-20_the-worship-of-the-panchakshari-vidya-of-shiva/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/pUjA/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-20_the-worship-of-the-panchakshari-vidya-of-shiva/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/09/20/the-worship-of-the-panchakshari-vidya-of-shiva/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Late in the evening the my clansmen and me left by an uncomfortable bus&#xA;journey through the drAviDa country to the outpost of aunts N and H.&#xA;Their clansmen had been killed by fiery abhichAras of their shatrus, but&#xA;they took the help of our learned co-ethnic, a master of the&#xA;mantra-shAstra to save themselves. While in gavalakuNDa he was a student&#xA;of the descendent of that great exponent of samaya-vidyA of the east.&#xA;Then he had come to know numerous tantriks and became a great exponent&#xA;of the mantra shAstra. His network of mantra-vid-s was immense and he&#xA;had an enormous collection of mantra manuscripts. At my teacher’s&#xA;behest, I had obtained from him an old copy of the mantra-mahodadhi of&#xA;mahIdhara, the savant of vArANasI and the shArada-tilaka tantraM. In his&#xA;secular existence he was a village school master, who taught all&#xA;subjects in his ramshackle school from around 9.30 AM to 3.30 PM 5 days&#xA;a week. In his free-time he was also a medicine-man doling out minor&#xA;tantric preparations for free. Form the outpost of our aunts’ we went to&#xA;see this savant in the village of Karur, arriving there late at night.&#xA;The next two days we spent in deep discussion of the mantra-shAstra and&#xA;paddhatI-s, left alone by our disinterested clansmen. He had given the&#xA;same line of my clan as aunts N and H several copies of texts but they&#xA;were sadly lost when a mantra performance of theirs back-fired on them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>mahAvaiShNava krama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/pUjA/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-08-05_mahavaishnava-krama/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/pUjA/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-08-05_mahavaishnava-krama/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/08/05/mahavaishnava-krama/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Both the avaykta and the nR^isiMha-tApini explain that the yantra with&#xA;the ugra viShNu formula should be tied as an amulet. The&#xA;nR^isiMha-tApini explains the structure of the great yantra of viShNu&#xA;that simultaneously encompasses :1) the bIja of nR^isiMha and the&#xA;praNava. 2) the sudarshana chakra mUla mantra. 3) the nArAyaNa&#xA;aShTAkSharI 4) the vAsudeva dvAdashAkSharI 5) the ShoDasha mAtR^ika&#xA;bIja-s 6) the ugra viShNu formula.The formal worship of the yantra and&#xA;viShNu embodied in it may be done thus.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
