<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;04 Descriptive Studies on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;04 Descriptive Studies on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Newar Buddhist *Homa* Ritual Traditions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/01_Newar_Buddhist_Homa_Ritual_Traditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/01_Newar_Buddhist_Homa_Ritual_Traditions/</guid>
      <description>Todd Lewis and Naresh Bajracharya
INTRODUCTION In addition to the wealth of Sanskrit manuscripts from their private and monastic archives, which provided the textual foundations of modern Buddhist studies, the Newars of the Kathmandu Valley likewise perform a rich repertoire of rituals also originating in later Indic Buddhism. Among them are a large variety of homa rituals done in a Buddhist modality, each with its specific details of performance and purposes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 The *Navarātra Homa*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/02_The_Navartra_Homa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/02_The_Navartra_Homa/</guid>
      <description>LIVER, ENCHANTMENT, AND ENGENDERING THE DIVINE ŚAKTIS
Nawaraj Chaulagaini
INTRODUCTION This essay discusses the homa rituals as performed during the annual navarātra (literally, “nine-day festival,” also known as the navadurgāpūjā) in the former Nepalese royal palaces of Gorkhā and Hanumānḍhokā during the rule of the Śāha kings (ca. 1559–2008). The homa was part of a series of navarātra rituals observed in the lunar fortnight of Āśvina (September–October).1 The rituals were carried out for the propitiation of the goddess Kālī, who is often portrayed in the violent and terrifying form of the goddess Durgā (consort of the god Śiva) and represented in various forms such as divine icons (images), plants, virgins, concentric magical/mystical diagrams (yantras), mantras, and weapons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Fire on the Mountain</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/03_Fire_on_the_Mountain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/03_Fire_on_the_Mountain/</guid>
      <description>THE SHUGENDŌ SAITŌ GOMA
Richard K. Paynei
INTRODUCTION Shugendō (種験道) is a religious tradition that centers on the practice of austerities in remote mountainous settings.1 Several mountains in Japan—Fuji, Omine, Haguro, for example—provided the ritual worlds in which various Shugendō confraternities practiced and served to define the different confraternities from one another. Contemporary practitioners (shugenja 種験者, or gyōja 行者, also popularly called yamabushi 山伏) claim that its origins date back to the earliest history of Japan,2 and the tradition continues to play an important part in contemporary Japanese religious culture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 *Agnihotra* Rituals in Nepal</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/04_Agnihotra_Rituals_in_Nepal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/04_Descriptive_Studies/04_Agnihotra_Rituals_in_Nepal/</guid>
      <description>Michael Witzeli
TODAY FIVE GROUPS of brahmins reside in the Kathmandu Valley:1 the Newari-speaking Rājopādhyāya; the Nepali-speaking Pūrbe, who immigrated in the last centuries before the Gorkha conquest (1768–1769 C.E.), the Kumaĩ; the Newari- and Maithili-speaking Maithila; and the Bhaṭṭas from South India, who serve at the Paśupatināth temple. Except for the Bhaṭṭas, all are followers of the White Yajurveda in its Mādhyandina recension. It could therefore be expected that all these groups, with the exception of the Bhaṭṭas, would differ from each other in language and certain customs brought from their respective homelands, but that they would agree in their (Vedic) ritual.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
