<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Dharmasastra Works and Writers on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p2/Dharmasastra_Works_and_Writers/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Dharmasastra Works and Writers on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p2/Dharmasastra_Works_and_Writers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>List of Authors</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p2/Dharmasastra_Works_and_Writers/Appendix_B_List_of_Authors_on_dharmashAstra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p2/Dharmasastra_Works_and_Writers/Appendix_B_List_of_Authors_on_dharmashAstra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Appendix B List of Authors on Dharmaśāstra&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;APPENDIX B&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;LIST OF AUTHORS ON DHARMASÁSTRA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While preparing this list, great difficulties were experienced in stating all the works composed by an author. In the case of such names as Ananta, Krsna, Gangadhara, Nārāyaṇa, Rama kļṣṇa, Śhaṅkara which are extremely common, the only method that could be followed, in the absence of materials to identify the authors bearing these names, was to place the same name several times in the list against the work composed by that author. Since the authors themselves very often convey no more informa tion than their own names and since some of the reports on the search for mss. do not give even what little information about the author can be gathered from the ms. of his work, Aufrecht also was compelled to follow this method. In order to avoid repetition and save space, I have not repeated in this list the in formation that was given under the works contained in the list A. Dates are given principally under the names of authors and sometimes under works also. For further information readers will have in many cases to refer to the works put down as com posed by an author. In the case of authors who have written on several sastras, their works on dharmaśāstra alone have been mentioned. Wherever possible parentage has been noted and dates assigned. In a few cases information which became avail able after list A was prepared has been incorporated here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>List of Works</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p2/Dharmasastra_Works_and_Writers/Appendix_A_List_of_Works_on_dharmashAstra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v1p2/Dharmasastra_Works_and_Writers/Appendix_A_List_of_Works_on_dharmashAstra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Appendix A List of Works on Dharmaśāstra&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;APPENDIX A.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;List of Works on Dharmaśāstra It is necessary to say a few words about the methods followed in preparing this list of the works on dharmaśāstra. Purely srauta works have generally been excluded, except where they have been profusely quoted or relied upon by dharmaśāstra writers. Works of the Tantra class and the Purāṇas have been passed over, inas-much as they form in themselves independent and extensive branches of Sanskrit literature requiring an exhaustive and detailed treatment, which from considerations of space had to be abandoned here. All individual prayogas, māhātmyas, vidhis, vratas, śāntis, stotras have been omitted, except where the names of the authors are well-known or there is some importance or peculiarity attaching to them. Purely astrological works on jātaka, and tājika have not been included, but works of the muhūrta class that are closely connected with everyday religious practices have been included. Though the gshyasūtras and their commentaries were not dwelt upon in the body of the present work, they have been included in this list as their subject-matter is closely allied to dharmaśāstra. Only works up to about 1820 A. D. have been entered here. Works on politics ( arthaśāstra ) have also been included. I am afraid that all the restrictions set out above have not been rigorously observed in the following and crave the indulgence of scholars in this respect. I must gratefully acknowledge, as everyone engaged in preparing a similar list on any branch of post-Vedic literature must do, my indebtedness to the monumental Catalogus Cata logorum of Dr. Aufrecht. But even that catalogue leaves many things doubtful and necessarily gives meagre information. For removing such doubts I was compelled to read and compare the the original catalogues of Sanskrit mss. such as that of the India Office, the Notices of Sanskrit mss. by Dr. Mitra and M. M. Haraprasada. Besides the third part of Aufrecht&amp;rsquo;s Catalogue was published in 1903. Since then several other catalogues, such as the Descriptive Catalogues and Triennial Catalogues of the Madras Govt. mss. Library, Notices of mss. (new series, part III) by M. M. Haraprasada Śāstri, Catalogue of Palmleaf and Paper mss. of Nepal Durbar Library by M. M. Haraprasada Śāstri, Hultzsch&amp;rsquo;s Report (part III ), Catalogue of Central Provinces Sanskrit mss. by Rai Bahadur Hiralal and Catalogue of the mss. collected by&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
