<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 Vratas and Utsavas on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 Vratas and Utsavas on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Vrata in the Ṛgveda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/01_Vrata_in_the_gveda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/01_Vrata_in_the_gveda/</guid>
      <description>SECTION 1 VRATAS (Religious Vows) and UTSAVAS (Religious Festivals)
CHAPTER I VRATA IN THE ṚGVEDA
Meaning of Vrata Vrata is one of many Sanskrit words, the use and history of which extend over several thousand years. The derivation and semantic development of the word vrata have been the subject of great controversies. These questions have been dealt with by me at some length in the JBBRAS, vol. 29 (1954) pp. 1-28.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Vrata in Vedas, Sūtras and Smṛtis</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/02_Vrata_in_Vedas_sUtras_and_smRtis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/02_Vrata_in_Vedas_sUtras_and_smRtis/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER 11
11
VRATA in Vedic Literature, Sūtras and Smr̥tis ; definition and importance of Vratas.
After dealing with the etymology and semantic development of the word &amp;lsquo;vrata&amp;rsquo; from the passages of the Ṛgveda in which the word occurs, it is now time to tarn to the other Vedic Samhitās and the Brāhmaṇas for finding out how that word is dealt with in them. Some of the Ṛgvedic verses occur in other Vedic Samhitās.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Vratādhikārin and related topics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/03_vratAdhikArin_and_related_topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/03_vratAdhikArin_and_related_topics/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER III
Persons entitled to engage in Vratas, objects desired by means of Vratas, classifications of Vratas and literature on Vratas, times for Vratas
One important matter is that of vratādhikāriṇaḥ (persons entitled to engage in a vrata). Persons of all castes including śūdras are entitled to perform vratas. Devala states: 1 &amp;rsquo;there is no doubt that (men of) all varṇas are released from sins by observing vratas, fasts and restrictive rules of behaviour and by mortification (lit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Individual Vratas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/04_Individual_Vratas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/04_Individual_Vratas/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER IV
Individual vratas; Caitra Pratipad, Rāmanavami,
Akṣayya-tṛtiya, Paraśurāmajayanti, Daśaharā,
Sāvitri-vrata.
The Mahābhārata1 prescribes how to set about a vrata. &amp;ldquo;Taking in one&amp;rsquo;s hand a copper vessel full of water and turning one&amp;rsquo;s face to the north one should undertake the upavāsa, or whatever else he resolves in his mind to undertake as a vrata.&amp;rsquo; Devala2 also says &amp;lsquo;without taking food (the previous night), after taking a bath and having performed ācamana (ceremonial sipping of water) and after having declared before the Sun and other devatās (his intent) a person should perform a vrata&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Ekādaśī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/05_ekAdashI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/05_ekAdashI/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER V
The most important tithi in the month of Āṣāḍha is Ekādaśī. A voluminous literature has grown round Ekādaśī in the Purāṇas and medieval digests. There are separate treatises on Ekādaśī written by medieval writers, such as the Ekādaśīviveka of Śūlapāni and the Ekādaśītattva of Raghunandana: Besides, such medieval digests as Kālaviveka (pp. 425-451), Hemādri on Kāla pp. 145–288, Kālanirṇaya of Mādhava (pp. 233–275), Vratarāja pp. 361-475, Kāla-tattvavivecana (pp. 98–172) devote hundreds of pages to discussions on Ekādaśī.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Cāturmāsya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/06_chAturmAsya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/06_chAturmAsya/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER VI
CĀTURMĀSYA
On Āṣāḍha-śukla ekādaśī or dvādaśī or paurṇimā1 or on the day when the Sun enters the Zodiacal sign Cancer, cāturmāsya vrata is to be observed. Whenever it may be begun it is to be finished on Kārtika-śukla 12. The performer should observe a fast that day, worship Viṣṇu (image) and pray as follows: (Garuḍapurāṇa I. 121. 2–3) &amp;lsquo;O God! I have undertaken this vrata in your presence; may it succeed without obstacles if you become favourable to me; after I undertake this vrata if I die when it is half-finished, may it become completely fulfilled through your favour&amp;rsquo;!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Vratas in Śrāvaṇa month</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/07_Vratas_in_shrAvaNa_month/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/07_Vratas_in_shrAvaNa_month/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER VII
Vratas called Nāgapañcami, Manasāpūjā,
Rakṣābandhana, Krṣṇajanmāṣṭami
In the month of Śrāvaṇa there are several important vratas, one of which is Nāgapañcami on the 5th of the bright half of Śrāvaṇa. The Nāgapañcami is observed in different ways in all parts of India. Some hold that, instead of Akṣayyatṛtiyā, Nāgapañcami is the one half auspicious day out of 3 1/2 most auspicious days in the year. The Bhaviṣyapurāṇa, Brāhmaparva (chapter 32 verses 1-39), expatiates on Nāgapañcami.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Vratas in Bhādrapada month</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/08_Vratas_in_bhAdrapada_month/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/08_Vratas_in_bhAdrapada_month/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER VIII
Vratas of Haritālikā, Gaṇeśacaturthi,
Ṛṣipañcami, Anantacaturdaśī.
Haritālikā Vrata On the 3rd tithi of the bright half of Bhādrapada occurs the Haritālikāvrata for women alone. This vrata is not found in the Kr̥tyakalpataru on vrata or in Hemādri. It is described only in the later medieval digests like the Nirṇayasindhu (p. 133), Vratārka (folios 44 6-49 b), Vratarāja (pp. 103-110) and Ahalyākāmadhenu (folios 282-295). It may, however, be noted that the Rājamārtaṇḍa of Bhoja (first half of 11th century A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Navarātra or Durgotsava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/09_navarAtra_or_Durgotsava/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/09_navarAtra_or_Durgotsava/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER IX
Navarātra or Durgotsava
From the 1st of Āśvina bright half to the 9th is celebrated the Durgāpūjā festival, otherwise called Navarātra, observed all over India in some form or other. Some of the works1 provide that Durgotsava must be celebrated in both Śarad (Āśvina-śukla) and Vasanta (in Caitra-śukla). But it is the Durgotsava2 of Āśvina that is celebrated in a grand style, particularly in Bengal, Bihar and Kāmarūpa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Vijayādaśamī and Divāḷi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/10_vijayAdashamI_and_divALLii/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/10_vijayAdashamI_and_divALLii/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER X
Vijayādaśamī and Divali
Vijayādaśamī The 10th tithi of Aśvina-śukla is called Vijayā-daśamī. It is elaborately described in Hemādri (on vrata, vol. 1. pp. 970-973), Nirṇayasindhu (pp. 69-70), Puruṣārtha-cintāmaṇi (pp. 145-148), Vratarāja (pp. 359-361) and Kālatattva-vivecana (pp. 309-312), Dharmasindhu (p. 96). As Daśami (10th tithi) is not mentioned in the Yugmavākya the Kālanirṇaya relies on a verse that in the bright half that tithi which exists at sunrise should be accepted for performance of rites and in the dark half the one that exists at sunset.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 Makarasaṅkrānti and Mahāśivarātri</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/11_makarasankrAnti_and_mahAshivarAtri/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/11_makarasankrAnti_and_mahAshivarAtri/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XI
Makarasaṅkrānti and Mahaśivarātri
_Makara-saṅkrānti This is a very important religious observance and festival. About 70 years ago (in the author&amp;rsquo;s boyhood) it occurred on the 12th or 13th January according to the several Indian almanacs then current, but now it falls, owing to the procession of the equinoxes, on the 13th or the 14th of January in the month of Pauṣa. Saṅkrānti means &amp;rsquo;the (apparent) passage of the sun from one rāśi (sign of the Zodiac) to the next following&amp;rsquo; and hence the rāśi in which the Sun enters is designated as the saṅkrānti of that name.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 Holikā and Grahaṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/12_holikA_and_grahaNa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/12_holikA_and_grahaNa/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XII
Holikā and Grahaṇa (eclipse)
Holi or Holikā Holikā. Holi or Holikā is a festival of unmixed gaiety and frolics throughout India, though all parts do not observe it in the same way. One element, viz. bonfire, is present almost everywhere except in Bengal. Swinging of Kṛṣṇa image on Phālguna Full Moon is done in Bengal, but it is not observed in several other parts of India. The number of days during which this festival is observed also varies from province to province.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 List of Vratas and Utsavas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/13_List_of_Vratas_and_Utsavas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/13_List_of_Vratas_and_Utsavas/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XIII
List of Abbreviations used in the following
List of Vratas
AK = Ahalyākāmadhenu (ms). BB = Bhujabalanibandha of Bhoja (ms). BHP = Bhāgavatapurāṇa. BHAV = Bhaviṣyapurāṇa. BHAVU = Bhaviṣyottarapurāṇa. BR = Brahmāṇḍa-purāṇa. BRAH = Brahmapurāṇa. BRV = Brahmavaivarta, Br. S. = Br̥hat-samhitā of Varāhamihira. DE = Devipurāṇa. DNS = Dvaitanirṇaya-siddhanta-sangraha. DS – Dharmasindhu. DT = Durgotsavatattva. DV = Durgotsavaviveka of Sūlapāṇi. ET= Ekādaśitattva. GAR = Garuḍapurāṇa. GK = Gadādharapaddhati ( Kālasāra portion).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
