<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;00 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;00 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Chronological Table</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/Chronological_Table/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/Chronological_Table/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHRONOLOGICAL TABLE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(of important works and authors referred to in this volume)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;N. B. Some dates, particularly of ancient works, are conjectural and only tentative. 4000 B. C-1000 B.C. -The period of the Vedic Samhitas, Brā.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;hmanas and Upanigads. It is possible that some hymns may go back to &amp;amp; period even earlier than 4000 B. O. and that some Upaniṣads (even out of those that are regarded as the principal and the earliest&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/List_of_Abbreviations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/List_of_Abbreviations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;LIST OF ABBREVIATIONS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A. I R. = All India Reporter (edited by Mr. V. V.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chitaley of Nagpur ). Ait. Br. = Aitareya Brahmaṇa. All. = Indian Law Reports, Allahabad Series. Anan, or Anand. = Anandasrama Press edition, Poona. Āp. Dh.S. &amp;gt; Apastamba-dharmasutra. Ap. gr. = Āpastamba-gphya-sūtra. ĀP. M. P. = Apastamba-mantra-patha. Ap. Sr. = Āpastamba-srauta-sūtra. Ā§v. gr. = Aśvalāyana-grhya-sūtra. Āśy. Śr. = Asvaldyana-srauta-sūtra. A. S. W. 1. = Archaeological Survey of Western India&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preface</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/Preface/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/Preface/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PREFACE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is a little over ten years since the first volume of my History of Dharmaśāstra was published. In the preface to that volume I expressed the hope that time and health permitting I might issue in a few years the second volume dealing with the development of the various subjects comprised in Dharmaśāstra, For several years thereafter whatever leisure I could seouro from professional work was devoted to the collection and orderly assortment of the vast Literature on Dharmasastra. After my return from a few months&amp;rsquo; visit to Europe in 1937 I commenced the work of writing the second volume. It soon became apparent to me that to compress within the limits of a single volume the development of the thousand and one topios that fall within the purview of Dharmaśāstra would present only a sorappy and faint outline of the whole field. To add to the difficulties of my task my old painful complaint ( duodenal ulcer) recurred with far greater virulence than before, so much so that, partly on medical advice and partly out of despair, in October 1938 I gave up the work altogether. When relief did not come even after six months&amp;rsquo; total abstinence from literary labours I resumed, in spite of my extremely painful complaint, the work of writing, for fear that otherwise the extensive materials that I had been collecting for nearly two decades might be entirely lost to the world of Sanskrit scholars and that my labours might be altogether wasted. Being afraid that my strength and resolu tion may not last till the completion of the rather ambitious undertaking, I decided upon bringing out in two volumes the development of the various subjects comprised in Dharmaśāstra. The present volume contains the treatment of varṇa and Aśrama, the samskāras, āhnika and acāra, dāna, pratiṣtha and utsarga, and srauta (vedic) sacrifices. The next volume (the last) will deal with the following topics: vyavahāra (Law and procedure), āśauca (impurity on birth and death), sraddha, prāyasoitta, tirtha, vrata, kāla, sānti, the influence of the Pūrva. mimams. and other sāstras on Dharmaśāstra, customs and usages modifying Dharmasastra, the pbilosophical background of Dhermaśāstra, and future developments in Dharmasastra. Looking to my past performance I am unwilling to make any promise about the time when the next volume may be&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synopsis of Contents</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/Synopsis_of_Contents/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/Synopsis_of_Contents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SYNOPSIS OF CONTENTS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NT NIS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAP. I.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-18 Topics of dharmaśāstra. Various divisions of dharma. Dharmas common to all ( sadharana-dharma). Truth, love, charity, self-restraint. Standard of moral values. Four puruṣ ārthas (goals of human existence ) and their gradation. Limpits of Āryā varte. Bharatavarṣa. CHAP, II.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;19&amp;ndash;104 Varna. High eulogy and condemnation of caste system, Characteristic features of moderu casto system. History of the word varṇa. Arya and dāsa or dasyu. Vis in the Rgveda. Position of Sūdra in Vedic Literature. Position of the three higher varṇas inter se. Professions and crafts in Vedic Samhitās. Rathakāra and Niṣada. Propositions deducible from Vedic Literature. List of various crafts and a vocations culled from Vedic Literature. Ramifications of caste traced by dharmaśāstra writers to mixed unions. Two postulates as to castes in dharma śāstra writers. Anuloma and pralloma castes. Jāti. Status of children of mixed castes. Varnasankara. Jūlyut karṣa and Jātyapakarṣa. Professional castes and guilds. List of castes mentioned by works from 500 B. C. to 1000 A, D. Revolt against the caste system in the Mahābhārata. A fow of the castes mentioned by medieval works. CHAP. III.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Table Of Cases Cited</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/Table_Of_Cases_Cited/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/Table_Of_Cases_Cited/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TABLE OF CASES CITED&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;502&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Amrit v. Hari&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;8658&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;| Hirabbarthi v. Bai Javer 952 Angaji u. Narayan&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;914 Honama v. Timannabbat 586n. Asita Mohan v. Nirode Moban 75&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Iadi v, Gbania&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;502 Aunjona Dasi v. Prahlada&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In Re Pyro&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;888n. Cbandra&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;538&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the matter of Ram Kumari 6210. Bai Diwali v, Moti&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;603 Ishwari Prasad v. Rai Hari Bai Gulab v. Jivanlal&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;452n.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Prasad&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;75 Bai Jivi v. Narsingh&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Table of Contents</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/Table_of_Contents/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/Table_of_Contents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TABLE OF CONTENTS OF VOL. II&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;LIST OF ABBREVIATIONS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;vii-s&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHRONOLOGICAL TABLE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;xi-xii&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SYNOPSIS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;xiii-xxili&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;LIST OF WORKS CONSULTED&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Xxxiv-xlv&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;TABLE OF CASES CITED&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;xlvi-xlvii&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;HISTORY OF DHARMAŚĀSTRA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-1255&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;APPENDIX OF LONGER EXTRACTS IN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SANSKRIT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1257-1278&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;GENERAL INDEX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1279-1358&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;INDEX OF IMPORTANT WORDS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1359-1866&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ERRATA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1367–1368&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Works Consulted</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/Works_Consulted/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v2p1/00/Works_Consulted/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;D. EWORKS CONSULTED&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(with references to editions &amp;amp;c.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;N. B. Works referred to only once or twice and most of those already set out on Pp. 19a, 1790, 195n, 3210, 624r. 713n have been omitted.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;TEXTS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vedic Samhitās Atharvaveda-S. P. Pandit&amp;rsquo;s edition. Kathaka Samhita.-edited by Dr. Sohroeder. Maitriyani Sambita-edited by Dr. Schroeder. Rgveda-Prof. Max Mūller&amp;rsquo;s edition with the com. of Sāyaṇa&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;in four volumes. Samaveda&amp;ndash;Benfey&amp;rsquo;s edition and Satyavrata Samagrami&amp;rsquo;s edi&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
