<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Ritual on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/v4_shUdra/ritual/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Ritual on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/v4_shUdra/ritual/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>saMskAra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/v4_shUdra/ritual/saMskAra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/v4_shUdra/ritual/saMskAra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Only non-vedic rites of passage (saṃskāra-s) were permitted by most sūtrakāra-s.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As a consequence of not studying the veda-s, there were śūdra-s acquired only one formal āśrama - gṛhastha. So, no upanayana according to most thinkers.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;However,  the Baudhayana gṛhyasūtra (2.5.8 and 2.5.9) states the teacher to &amp;ldquo;[l]et him initiate [to school through Upanayana] a Brahmin in spring, a Kshatriya in summer, a Vaishya in autumn, a Sudra in the rainy season; or all of them in the spring.&amp;rdquo; and clearly allows initiation of shūdra-s.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;No saṃskāra-s could be performed with vaidika mantra-s. One had to use mantra-s from the purāṇa-s or tantra-s. This was observed in practice (eg. in rites of śivāji&amp;rsquo;s later successors).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Furthermore, several śūdra jāti-s had their own rites of passage, which never conflicted with the vedic stream.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;speacial-samskara-s&#34;&gt;Speacial saMskAra-s&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;आगमक-उपनयनम&#34;&gt;आगमिक-उपनयनम्&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;see &lt;a href=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/AjIva-saMskAraH/mantropadeshaH/upanayanam&#34;&gt;upavIta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>smRti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/v4_shUdra/ritual/smRti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/v4_shUdra/ritual/smRti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A śūdra could hear the smṛti-s, itihāsa-s and the purāṇa-s through a brAhmaṇa reader. Some dharmaśāstra-s (eg. śūdrakamalākara, govindarAja) prohibit him from reading it himself.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Certainly there are exceptions - including (quite defensibly) sanxepa-rAmAyaNa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;पठन्द्विजो वागृषभत्वमीयात्स्यात्क्षत्रियो भूमिपतित्वमीयात्। वणिग्जनः पण्यफलत्वमीयाज्जनश्च शूद्रोऽपि महत्त्वमीयात्॥ – वा॰रा॰ १.१.१००&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Similarly stotras would not be prohibited, post instruction by v1. They would be judged on a case by case basis, to be conservative.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There was no prohibition whatsoever on studying and enjoying derivative poetic works in any language including saṃskṛta.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Several sources point to śūdra-s reading (portions of) the smṛti-s, itihāsa-s and the purāṇa-s.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Indeed we find several śūdra poets and savants of the classical idiom. There are so many of them that we desist from listing them here, but interested readers may consult resources such as Śatāvdhānī Gaṇeśa’s video &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ff6mVQ_yn2s&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There was no -explicit- prohibition of a śūdra reading the  smṛti-s, itihāsa-s and the purāṇa-s himself, if he were capable of doing so (esp. after first listening to it from a v1).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vedic sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/v4_shUdra/ritual/vedic-sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/v4_shUdra/ritual/vedic-sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Śūdra-s could not consecrate vaidika fires and major perform vaidika sacrifices.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vedic (śrauta)  fire sacrifice vs non-vedic fire sacrifice&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This distinction is crucial to this restriction, and many people are terribly confused about it. Some think that a regular “homa” fire sacrifice conducted in a home or in a temple is a “vedic” sacrifice. In fact, keeping the seasonal household sacrifices apart, major vedic yāga-s are conducted in a special temporary shelter which is burnt down at the end of the sacrifice.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Very few people, brāhmaṇa-s included, have ever even seen a vedic fire sacrifice, and the ritual is largely extinct amongst many communities. These sarcrifices were rare even in mideval times.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;attenuation&#34;&gt;Attenuation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There are indications within the veda-s themselves that in early times, even śūdra-s could perform vaidika sacrifices. Also, Badarī and the Bhāradvāja śrauta sūtra disagreed with (or refined&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) later exclusion; as did the Apastamba śrauta sūtra&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This can’t be over-emphasized - the vedic stream did not have a monopoly on fire sacrifices! Śūdra-s could certainly perform non-vedic fire sacrifices. For example, here in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n4AV_Gv_59k&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;, a Japanese Buddhist is depicted performing a homa to a buddhist deity (most likely marīcī).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Śūdra-s could do the daily 5 mahā-yajña-s using a non-vedic fire, as needed.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;These might have referred to an ancient class of śūdra-s - or specific classes thereof (niṣāda-sthapati and rathakāra).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
