<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;गोरक्षा on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;गोरक्षा on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Context in conflict</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Context_in_conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Context_in_conflict/</guid>
      <description>Hindu vs Muslim The context of hindu-muslim conflict (with the latter using cow slaughter to stick it to the hindus - Shaykh Ahmad Sirhindi, Khwaja Moinuddin Chishti of Ajmer [NG15-B]) makes cow protection a particularly important issue. hindu-european conflict Dharampal writes in his book “The British Origin of Cow-Slaughter in India”: “‘It can be reasonably assumed that there was very little cow killing after about 1700 AD since the domination of Islam waned and converts to Islam did not take to eating of cow flesh.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cross-cultural comparison</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Cross-cultural_comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Cross-cultural_comparison/</guid>
      <description>Iran &amp;ldquo;The Zoroastrian religion forbids cow flesh for consumption. The cow also figures symbolically in several aspects of that religion, and cow urine is drunk at the Navjote sacrament. It is another matter that Westernized Anglophile Parsis have ignored the dietary laws among many other things. &amp;hellip; even until recently, cows were not a part of regular diet in Iran. It was during Westernization under the Qajar dynasty that the Brits &amp;amp; French introduced beef eating big time (which is now widespread in Iran).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Current situation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Current_situation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Current_situation/</guid>
      <description>Visceral reactions are an essential expression of a strong Hindu cultural immune system. The easier it is to identify the barbarian, the better the chances of survival of this very exalted &amp;ldquo;sanAtana&amp;rdquo; dharma. Current cow protection efforts Comfortable sanctuaries for cows (go-shAlA) examples - pANDuranga16. Dalit communities and beef &amp;ldquo;A recent mapping of the food habits of SC communities published by Swarajya Magazine clearly shows that though 80% of the SC communities are meat eaters, they discourage beef.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Royal enforcement</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Royal_enforcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/sAmAnya-dharmaH/animal-protection/go-raxA/Royal_enforcement/</guid>
      <description>It came to be a prime duty of the king to protect cows from slaughter in his domain. (गोब्राह्मणेभ्यश् शुभमस्तु नित्यम् …) Shivaji cut off hands of cow killers, gangAdevI decries wanton cow slaughter by the mlecCha-s. keraLa Duarte Barbosa, a 16th century Portuguese writer : “The King then asks him if he will maintain the customs and rules of the other Nayres (Nairs), and he and his kinsmen respond ‘ Yes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
