<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;GhorAngirasa on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;GhorAngirasa on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Birth progression</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/birth-progression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/birth-progression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GhorAngirasa/status/1338885970788114434&#34;&gt;https://twitter.com/GhorAngirasa/status/1338885970788114434&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;He who has purified his soul by good deeds and controlled his senses; such a shUdra should be attended upon with respect like a dvija; thus is the dictate of brahma&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ब्राह्मण्यं देवि दुष्प्रापं&lt;br&gt;&#xA;निसर्गाद् ब्राह्मणः शुभे ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;क्षत्रियो वैश्य-शूद्रौ वा&lt;br&gt;&#xA;निसर्गाद् इति मे मतिः ॥६॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;brAhmaNyam (brAhmaNa-ness) is difficult to obtain; it comes innately; so does kSatriyatvam, etc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;त्रेताग्नि-मन्त्र-विहितो&lt;br&gt;&#xA;वैश्यो भवति वै यदि ॥&#xA;स वैश्यः क्षत्रियकुले&lt;br&gt;&#xA;शुचौ महति जायते ॥३३॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gotra heredity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/gotra_heredity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/gotra_heredity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/GhorAngirasa/status/1868150128684749048&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ārșeya-heritage&#34;&gt;Ārșeya heritage&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What is central to the Brāhmaņya identity at least is the inheritance of Ārșeya heritage through kinship in a broad sense (going beyond shared blood). And this understanding of Brāhmaņyam in terms of Ārșeya patrilineal inheritance goes all the way back to at least the Samhitās of the Atharvaveda.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;adoption&#34;&gt;Adoption&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The existence of Kevalāńgirasas, Kevalabhārgavas &amp;amp; Dvyāmuṣyāyanas among Brāhmaņas already shows that Varņa/Gotra/Pravara is not biological. But it is still hereditary in the sense that it is an identity inherited patrilineally by virtue of ‘descent’ through kinship.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hereditary brAhmaNa priests</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/hereditary-brAhmaNa-priests/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/hereditary-brAhmaNa-priests/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is some deal of fluidity in varNa in contrast to jAti but brAhmaNa varNa was not fluid to same degree. Given the responsibility, it&amp;rsquo;s natural that the level scrutiny before one can be a brahman will be greater. It&amp;rsquo;s just about merit, or more? There is absolutely no escaping the hereditary component as far as &amp;ldquo;brAhmaNa&amp;rdquo; is concerned&amp;hellip;There is a finite number of gotras from which a brAhmaNa must have obtained patrilineal descent (svIkAra, adoption arrangements) between gotras were accepted. The old texts do emphasize the ARSeya (Of/from a RSi) root of a brAhmaNa - there is no denying this. Having clarified that, let me continue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knowledge &amp; ritual access</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/knowledge_ritual_access/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/knowledge_ritual_access/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: Angirasa Shreshta&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the most prevalent misconceptions extant in modern discourse is that the brāhmaṇa-s monopolized “religious resources” at the expense of others. Now, broadly speaking, we can identify two types of the aforementioned resources:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Knowledge: To what extent were jāti-s, belonging to varṇa-s apart from the brāhmaṇa, were able to access generic knowledge as well as knowledge specific to a particular sampradāya?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ritual: To what extent, Hindus, other than the brāhmaṇa-s, had access to ritual systems by way of dīkṣā (initiation)?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A survey of the relevant material will demonstrate that, far from the non-brāhmaṇa population being disenfranchised and deprived of knowledge and rituals, the brāhmaṇa-s constantly innovated new texts, paths and strategies to significantly circumvent any restrictions, which may have been in place. In section 2, we would note two fine examples of rigorous argumentation in the service of a more generous understanding of adhikāra (competency).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>shishu AngIrasa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/shishv-AngIrasa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/shishv-AngIrasa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-misinterpretation&#34;&gt;The misinterpretation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some quote:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“I am a reciter of hymns, my father is a healer, my mother a grinder of corn. We desire to obtain wealth through various actions”&amp;ndash; Rig Veda 9.112.3 Do they have the same Varna?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an incorrect pramANa. A simple glancing of svAmin sAyaNa’s bhASya and the context of the Rk would explain it. The draSTa is the child RSi - shishu A~Ngirasa as can be seen from the informal way he calls his parents tata and nanA. The sUkta occurs in the book of the somapavamAna. So the hymn is of course seen in that context. Here the child sees his father as the Rtvij and the mother pounding the flour to make the puroDAsha. Why go for unnecessarily wild fantasies? I have seen this example even in my school history book. Probably makes for good propaganda, but seeds weird ideas. - 𑀧𑀺𑀦𑀸𑀓𑀻@pinakasena&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>varNa vocation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/varNa_vocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/clan/theory/articles/GA/varNa_vocation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;archakatvam-paurohityam&#34;&gt;Archakatvam, paurohityam&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Varņa is now almost wholly back to being a ritual/metaphysical entity that comes to play in wholly private/familial/intra-communal settings (private: sandhyāvandana, familial: upanayana/vivāha, intra-communal: Yajņas, vedapārāyaņam, etc). It involves essentially zero interaction with anyone from a different Varņa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The huge exception are Āgamika temples &amp;amp; a much smaller exception is paurohityam performed for those outside Brāhmaņa-varņa. These are public-facing roles &amp;amp; the former is the most vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/GhorAngirasa/status/1580383350514065409&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
