<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 Vyavahāra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 Vyavahāra on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>11 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/11_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/11_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>VYAVAHARA
(LAW AND ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE)
CHAPTER XI
That to administer justice impartially and to punish the guilty were among the prime functions of the sovereign has been stated above (p. 57). The king was deemed to be the fountain (i. e. the distributor ) of justice. Kautilya 323 (I. 19) prescribes that the king was to look into the disputes of citizens and country people in the 2nd part of the day (divided into eight parts ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 Bhukti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/12_Bhukti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/12_Bhukti/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XII
BHUKTI or BHOGA (possession ).
According to Gaut. X. 39 a man becomes an owner by inheritance, purchase, partition, seizure (appropriation of forest trees and other things which have no owner ) and find ing (i. e. appropriation of lost property the owner of which is unknown). Gaut. (X. 40-41) adds that in the case of brāhmaṇas acceptance (of a thing donated) is an additional mode (of becoming an owner), that conquest in the case of a ksatriya and gain ( by trade or labour ) in the case of a vaisya or sūdra are also additional modes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 Witnesses</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/13_Witnesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/13_Witnesses/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XIII
WITNESSES (saksinah).
The word saksin occurs in the Svetasvataropanisad 76 (VI. 11) wliere it is applied tu the une immanent Spirit of the uni. verse as All-seving. Panini 477 V. 2. 91 explains the word sākṣin as meaning one who has directly seen&amp;rsquo;. Gaut. 478 XIII. 1, Kant. III. 11, Nar. IV. 147 state that when two persons litigate and there is a doubt or discrepancy between the two the deter mination of the truth in the dispute is due to witnesses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14 Ordeals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/14_Ordeals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/14_Ordeals/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XIV
ORDEALS
A brief history of ordeals may be get out here. Rg. I. 158. 4-5, wherein 561 the sage Dirghatamas, son of Ucatha, prays that the fire of faggots heaped tenfold may not burn him and that the rivers in which he was thrown bound hand and foot may not engulf him, are regarded by some as a reference to the ordeal of fire and water. Yet in those verses there is probably no reference to ordeals, but to the cruel treatment of Dirghatanas by dūsas headed by Traitana.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15 Decision</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/15_Decision/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/15_Decision/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XV
DECISION
The last (i. e. 4th) stage in a judicial proceeding is siddhi (Yaj. II. 8) or nirṇaya ( decision). If pratyākalita (as defined above on p. 298) is regarded as a pāda of vyavahāra (and since all are agreed that there are only four pādas) then the decision is not a pūda of a lawsuit but is the fruit thereof (V. P. p. 86). When the evidence has been led, the king (or chief justice ) should with the help of the sabhyas decide upon the success or failure of the plaintiff594, Nar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 Contracts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/16_Contracts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/16_Contracts/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XVI.
CONTRACTS
There are only three titles of law, viz, recovery of debts, the relation of husband and wife (stripunsayoga) and partition of wealth (dāyabhāga) that are of importance to modern Hindus, since to a very large extent they are oven now governed in these matters by the ancient Hindu Law as interpreted by the commentators. These three topics therefore have to be described in detail while other titles will not and cannot be allowed to occupy much space.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>17 Asvāmivikraya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/17_asvAmivikraya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/17_asvAmivikraya/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XVII ASVĀMIVIKRAYA ( sale by one not the owner ).
The different modes of the sources of ownership have already been referred to ( H. of Dh. vol. II. pp. 130 ff) and will be referred to again under dayabhāga. According to Nār. VII. 1 and Br. (SBE vol. 33 p. 335 verse 2) when 789 a person, who holds an open deposit, a sealed deposit, an article bailed for delivery to another, stolen property, an article borrowed for some festival, a pledge, or property lost by a stranger and found ( by him ), sells it in secret ( or behind the back of the owner ) it is to be considered as a sale by one who is not the rightful owner.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18 Sambhūya-samutthāna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/18_sambhUya-samutthAna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/18_sambhUya-samutthAna/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XVIII
SAMBHŪYA-SAMUTTHĀNA 801 (A joint undertaking, partnership).
Where traders or others (like actors, musicians or artisans) carry on a business jointly it is termed a partnership (Nar. VI. 1 and Kat. 624).802_Bx. (SBE Vol. 33 p. 336 verses 1-2) says that a man should carry on a joint business with other persons of good family, that are clever, active, intelligent (or educated), familiar with coins, skilled in ( controlling ) expenditure and income, honest and valiant ( or enterprising ) and that joint undertakings like trade should not be carried on by prudent men with persons (partners ) who are weak or lazy or afflicted with disease or are unlucky or destitute ( of money ), 803 The meaning is not that all the above qualities must exist in all partners, but that according to the nature of the undertaking some of these qualities will be absolutely necessary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>19 Dattānapākarma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/19_dattAnapAkarma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/19_dattAnapAkarma/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XIX
DATTĀNAPAKARMA (resumption of gift).
This title is also called dattāpradūnika 815 (lit. that which is concerned with the non-delivery or resumption of a gift ). Nār. VII. 1 defines it as that title where a man desires to resume what has been given by him because it has been improperly (in a manner opposed to law ) given by him. Nār. (VII. 2 ) divides this title into four topics viz, what may not be given, what may be given, what are valid gifts and what are invalid gifts, Nār.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>20 Vetanasyānapākarma and related topics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/20_vetanasyAnapAkarma_and_related_topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/20_vetanasyAnapAkarma_and_related_topics/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XX
VETANASYANAPĀKARMA, ABHYUPETYASUŚRŪSĀ
AND SVĀMIPĀLAVIVADA (Non-payment of wages, non-rendition of service, dispute
between master and herdsman ).
TH
The question about the payment or non-payment of wagen to those whose services are hired for work is dealt with under this title ( Nār. IX. 1). According to Bp. there 826 are three titles of law in which the question of hiring enters, viz. abhyupetya $usrūṣā, vetanasyānapākarma and svūnipūlavivāda. Manu and Kauṭ.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21 Saṁvid-vyatikrama and other titles</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/21_Savid-vyatikrama_and_other_titles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/21_Savid-vyatikrama_and_other_titles/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXI
TT
SAMVID-VYATIKRAMA AND OTHER TITLES
( Violation of compacts or conventions)
Nār. ( XIII. 1 ) employs the expression samayasyānapākarma. Manu VIII. 5 employs the first expression. Manu (VIII. 218-219) has both names in view, when he says &amp;lsquo;I shall now declare the rules applicable to those who violate samayas (conventions ). He who having entered into a compact (samvid) under (the sanction of) an oath with the inhabitants of a village or a district or with a group of traders or other persons breaks it through greed should be banished from the kingdom by the king.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>22 Sīmavivāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/22_sImavivAda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/22_sImavivAda/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXII
SĪMAVIVĀDA ( boundary disputes ).
This is called kṣetra javivāda 897 (disputes relating to fields ) by Nārada XIV. 1, who defines it as &amp;rsquo; dispute with regard to land in which questions about dikes or embankments, the boundaries of fields, ploughed land and fallow land have to be decided.&amp;rsquo; Nārada&amp;rsquo;s idea appears to be that the word &amp;lsquo;simavivāda&amp;rsquo; in Manu is only illustrative and is a compendious way of mentioning disputes about land in general.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>23 Vākpāruṣya and Daṇḍapāruṣya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/23_vAkpAruShya_and_daNDapAruShya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/23_vAkpAruShya_and_daNDapAruShya/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXIII
VAKPĀRUSYA AND DANDAPARUSYA
( Abuse and defamation; assault)
Vakpāruṣya, dandapārusya, steya, strisangrahana, sāhasa are five titles out of 18 that are concerned with what may be called criminal matters or crimes in modern nomenclature. Vide under sāhasa below.
Nār, XVIII. 1 defines vākpārusya as &amp;lsquo;abusive words that loudly proclaim censure of another&amp;rsquo;s country, caste, family and the like and that cause mental pain or offence to that man. Kat.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>24 Steya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/24_Steya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/24_Steya/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXIV
STEYA (theft).
In the Rg. there is frequent mention of taskara, stena and tāyu. In Rg. VI. 28. 3 the sage 948 says &amp;lsquo;may the cows not disappear from us, may a thief not injure them! In Rg. VIII. 29. 6 it is said &amp;ldquo;Pūṣan guards the ways and knows of concealed treasures as a thief does! From Rg. X. 4.6 it appears that thieves were desperate and bound people with ropes and (from Rg.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>25 Strīsaṅgrahaṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/25_strIsangrahaNa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/25_strIsangrahaNa/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXV
STRĪSANGRAHAŅA (Adultery or unlawful intercourse
with a woman ).
The Mit. ( on Yāj. 11.976 283 ) states that sangrahana means the unlawful coming together of a man and a woman for sexual enjoyment. Bp. (S. B. E. 33 p. 365 verses 1-2) says that sinful 977 sangrahaṇa is of three kinds, viz. brought about by force, deceit or sensual passion. The first (which is rape ) occurs when intercourse is had in a secluded place against the will of a woman, or with a woman who is intoxicated or is disordered in mind or is under a mistake or when she raises a cry; the second occurs when a woman is brought to one&amp;rsquo;s house by some trick or pretence, an intoxicant (such as Dhatura) is administered to her or her mind is brought under control ( by chants or otherwise ) and sexual intercourse takes place; the third occurs when intercourse takes place by conveying (passion ) to each other by means of the eyes ( glances) or by employing a go-between and when the parties are drawn to each other by the temptation of beauty or of wealth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>26 Dyūtasamāhvaya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/26_dyUtasamAhvaya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/26_dyUtasamAhvaya/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER xxvi
DYŪTASAMĀHVAYA
(Gambling and prize-fighting ) Manu IX. 223, Nār. XIX. 1 and Bṛ. (8. B. E. 33 p. 385 verse 3) define dyūta (gambling ) as that sport which is carried on with inanimate objects such as dice, pieces of leather, ivory and the like and in which there is a stake, while sport carried on with animate objects such as cocks, pigeons, rams, buffaloes and wrestlers is called samāhvaya.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>27 Dāyabhāga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/27_dAyabhAga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/27_dAyabhAga/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXVII
DAYABHAGA ( Partition of wealth )
The word dāya has been used even in the oldest period of the Vedic Literature. Rg. II. 32. 4 ( dadātu viram satadāyam ukthyam ) has already been quoted above (on p. 388). In Rg. X. 114, 10 ( śramasya dayam vibhajantyebhyah) the meaning of the word seems to be &amp;lsquo;a share&amp;rsquo; or &amp;rsquo; reward&amp;rsquo;. In the Tai. S. and the Brāhmanas the word dāya appears to be employed in the sense of paternal wealth&amp;rsquo; or simply &amp;lsquo;wealth&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>28 Dattaka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/28_Dattaka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/28_Dattaka/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXVIII
DATTAKA ( adopted son)
No branch of Hindu Law in modern times has been 80 fruitful in litigation&amp;rsquo; as adoption. There are instances, where, fifty years after a point in the law of adoption was deemed to have been settled by a Full Bench decision, the Privy Council intervened and overruled the Full Bench decision in spite of its usual practice to follow the rule of stare decisis. The medieval digests are full of varying interpretations of the same smrti toxts and the law of adoption differs from province to province according to the authoritative medieval works and modern case law.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>29 Order of Succession After the Son</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/29_Order_of_Succession_After_the_Son/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/29_Order_of_Succession_After_the_Son/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXIX
ORDER OF SUCCESSION AFTER THE SON
It has been stated above that daya is either apratibandha or sapratibandha and that sons, grandsons and great-grandsons take the first kind of daya. If a man has no son either aurasa or secondary (viz. the dattaka, the other kinds of sons being now forbidden or obsolete), then his property devolvos in a certain order. When a man dies sonless and is a member of a joint Hindu family then on the surviving coparceners the whole estate devolves except that after 1937 (by Act XVIII of 1937) his widow takes his place as to the joint family property.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 Strīdhana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/30_strIdhana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/30_strIdhana/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXX
STRĪDHANA
Stridhana ( woman&amp;rsquo;s property ). This subject abounds with differing views on several topics that fall under it, as will be Been below.
The germs of the topic of stridhana can be traced to the Vedic Literature. As Sir Gooroodas Bannerjee remarks (in : Marriage and Stridhana&amp;rsquo; p. 370 ), &amp;rsquo; nowhere were proprietary rights of women recognized so early as in India; and in very few ancient systems of law have these rights been so largely conceded as in our own&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>31 Maintenance and other topics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/31_Maintenance_and_other_topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v3/2_vyavahAra/31_Maintenance_and_other_topics/</guid>
      <description>CHAPTER XXXI
MAINTENANCE AND OTHER TOPICS
The subject of maintenance occupies an important place in modern Hindu Law. A brief statement of the law of the smrtis and the digests on this subject must be made here.
The liability to provide maintenance for certain persons arises under the ancient Hindu Law in either of two ways viz. (1) on account of bare relationship between the parties or (2) on the ground of the possession of property.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
