<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/AyurvedaH/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/AyurvedaH/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ayurveda name</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/AyurvedaH/articles/Ayurveda-name/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/AyurvedaH/articles/Ayurveda-name/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Emperor Ashoka, writing in the middle of the third century BCE, spoke of his diplomatic initiatives, which included foreign aid in the form of medical materiel and know-how:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Everywhere — in the territory of the Beloved of Gods, King Piyadasi, as well as in those at the frontiers, namely, Codas, Pandyas, Satiyaputras, Keralaputras, Tamraparnis, the Greek king named Antiochus, and other kings who are that Antiochus’s neighbours — everywhere the Beloved of Gods, King Piyadasi, has established two kinds of medical services: medical services for humans and medical services for domestic animals. (Rock Edict II)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muslim-borrowing</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/AyurvedaH/articles/muslim-borrowing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/AyurvedaH/articles/muslim-borrowing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1731331708803559659.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Arfa and her ilk today are seething over the image of Dhanvantari, the God of Ayurveda. But once upon a Time her Arab Masters had copied their knowledge of medicine from Sushruta, Charaka etc who credited all their work to the same Dhanvantari.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-rabban-al-tabari&#34;&gt;1. Rabban Al Tabari:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first encyclopaedia of medicine in Arabic was Rabban Al Tabari’s Firdous Al Hikmah.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;His work was highly influenced by Indian physicians such as Sushruta &amp;amp; Charaka.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>nikhil - vaccination exemption request</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/AyurvedaH/articles/nikhil_vaxx/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/AyurvedaH/articles/nikhil_vaxx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://nikhilsd.com/vaxx.pdf&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Covid-19 booster religious exemption request for the University of Michigan&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;23 January 2022&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Níkhila Sū́rya Dvibhā́ṣya&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The following was my (successful) request for a religious exemption from the Covid-19 booster mandated by the University of Michigan for all students. This page contains the prompt that I was required to answer, followed by my response; the rest of this document, slightly modified from the original, consists of an essay with scriptural citations that I wrote and attached to my response. Because I did not receive the booster, I am required to submit to weekly Covid-19 testing by the university.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
