<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;विशेष-धर्मः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;विशेष-धर्मः on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Attribute-based गुण-धर्मः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/guna-dharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/guna-dharma/</guid>
      <description>Also European sacral kingship here. daNDa - Punishment. Mostly federal monarchies at the state level. Examples of democracy 1000AD inscription in the Sundaravarada temple in Uttiramerur, near Kanchipuram (H) &amp;ldquo;The salient features were that a person should have a minimum educational qualification, should be above 35 years of age and below 70, should own a minimum of landed property, should have a residence built in his own land and finally, should be a tax payer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deviance</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/deviance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/deviance/</guid>
      <description>Sexual deviance For general context, see separate article.
Historical Hindu view On Homosexuality lesbian khajurAho panel, devadutt paTnayak article, wiki, kAmasUtra references (v1). Classical dharmashAstra writers deprecated it. जैह्म्यं च मैथुनं पुंसि जातिभ्रंशकरं स्मृतम् । । ११.६७ jAti, could of course, be recovered with a prAyashcitta. The prAyashcitta for dvija-s was a bath with clothes on: मैथुनं तु समासेव्य पुंसि योषिति वा द्विजः । गोयानेऽप्सु दिवा चैव सवासाः स्नानं आचरेत् । । ११.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fluid dharma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/dharma-fluid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/dharma-fluid/</guid>
      <description>Intro Fluidity while retaining core principles
Indian notions of dharma was very fluid. (../For a general context on the limits of codification and holy books, see here.)
Notes PV kANe&amp;rsquo;s notes on fluidity: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. RB15. Principles First Principles The explicitly and implicitly stated motivations of dharma (such as accomplishing comfort/ sukha of everyone in order to retain one&amp;rsquo;s comfort - quotes in this page) naturally enable people to redetermine the details of what constitutes dharma &amp;ldquo;from first principles&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
