<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Advice on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/advice/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Advice on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/advice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>K to men</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/advice/k_to_men/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/advice/k_to_men/</guid>
      <description>Intro Title: Marriage advice for Hindu snAtaka-s Date: Apr 2018 Background of author: practicing gRhya ritualist and gRhastha; engineer and scholar. Mate selection Mate selection is a tough problem. The best laid plans can still result in disastrous choices. I observe chatter amongst “soon to be married” Hindu-s with a neo-traditional bent (reminding me of myself at that stage). As a fairly experienced (but still young &amp;lt;10 married yrs) gRhastha on a successful (though hard-won) trajectory, let me shed light some light on mistakes I’ve personally made or seen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>K to women</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/advice/k_to_women/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/advice/k_to_women/</guid>
      <description>Intro Source here. Date: Aug 2020. Background of author: Femaile. Artist. From mithilA. Married 2 years, with 1 kid. I&amp;rsquo;m writing this thread on how should be a hindu woman&amp;rsquo;s acharan with whatever little understanding I have. Forgive me for any त्रुटि.
Disclaimers This is not moral policing or dictation to anyone, it&amp;rsquo;s my personal opinion and experience. Also this thread is concerning women so o please don&amp;rsquo;t ask why not men has to do, I&amp;rsquo;ll write on men some other day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>मरु-स्त्री-ब्राह्मणौ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/advice/maru-strI-brAhmaNau/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/visheSha-dharmaH/Ashrama/vivAhaH/articles/advice/maru-strI-brAhmaNau/</guid>
      <description>षड्वर्षीयो बालः - मरून्मत्ता परिणेतुम् इच्छति चेत् किं करणीयम्?
पिता - प्रायेण तिरस्करणीयं, जातिनियमात् - उत्तमां सजातीयां हीच्छामः। कदाचित् तु देवाः स्वयम् आगत्य परिणेतुं वदन्ति चेत् - तां हिन्दुकीं कुर्याः प्रथमम्।
बालः - देवा आगत्य भाषन्ते?
पिता - सन्ध्योपासन-नृत्य-गीतादिभिस् सेवसे चेत् पूर्णमनसा त्वया ऽधिकं भाषिष्यन्ते। तेनैव ब्रवीमि, कल्पयित्वा कार्यं कर्म, सावधानम्।</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
