<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 Vratas and Utsavas on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 Vratas and Utsavas on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Vrata in the Ṛgveda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/01_Vrata_in_the_gveda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/01_Vrata_in_the_gveda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECTION 1 VRATAS (Religious Vows) and UTSAVAS (Religious Festivals)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER I VRATA IN THE ṚGVEDA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning-of-vrata&#34;&gt;Meaning of Vrata&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vrata&lt;/em&gt; is one of many Sanskrit words, the use and history of which extend over several thousand years. The derivation and semantic development of the word vrata have been the subject of great controversies. These questions have been dealt with by me at some length in the JBBRAS, vol. 29 (1954) pp. 1-28. I shall here summarise the discussion contained therein.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Vrata in Vedas, Sūtras and Smṛtis</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/02_Vrata_in_Vedas_sUtras_and_smRtis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/02_Vrata_in_Vedas_sUtras_and_smRtis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER 11&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;11&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;VRATA in Vedic Literature, Sūtras and Smr̥tis ; definition and importance of Vratas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After dealing with the etymology and semantic development of the word &amp;lsquo;vrata&amp;rsquo; from the passages of the Ṛgveda in which the word occurs, it is now time to tarn to the other Vedic Samhitās and the Brāhmaṇas for finding out how that word is dealt with in them. Some of the Ṛgvedic verses occur in other Vedic Samhitās. In several such passages vrata appears to mean &amp;lsquo;divine ordinances&amp;rsquo; or &amp;rsquo;ethical patterns of conduct&amp;rsquo;. For example, the verse&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Ṛg. I. 22. 19 &amp;lsquo;Mark the deeds of Viṣṇu, the helpful friend of Indra, whereby he watches over his ordinances&amp;rsquo; occurs also in T. S. I. 3.6.2, Atharva VII. 26.6, Vāj. S. VI. 4; Ṛg. VIII. 11. 136 &amp;lsquo;O Agni! thou art a God that protects ordinances among (gods and) men, thou art to be praised in sacrifices&amp;rsquo; is also found in Atharva 19. 59. 1, Vāj. S. IV. 16, T.S. I. 1. 14. 4-5 and I. 2.3.1; Ṛg. I. 24.15 is found in Vāj. S. XII. 12 and Atharva VII. 83 (88) 3 and XVIII, 4. 69; Ṛg. X. 191. 3 is almost the same as Atharva&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; VI. 64.2, the latter substituting the word &amp;lsquo;vratam&amp;rsquo; for &amp;lsquo;manaḥ&amp;rsquo; in the former and thereby indicating that &amp;lsquo;vrata&amp;rsquo; means &amp;lsquo;resolve to undertake a religious observance&amp;rsquo;; Ṛg. VII. 103. 1, in which frogs that lie down silent for a year and begin to croak at the advent of the rains are compared to brāhmaṇas observing a religious vow, occurs in the Atharvaveda IV. 15. 13; Ṛg. X. 12. 5 is the same as Atharva XVIII. 1. 33; Ṛg. X. 2.4 is almost the same as Atharva XIX. 59.2; Ṛg. I. 84. 12 is equal to Atharva XX. 109. 3; in all of which the words &lt;em&gt;vratam&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;vratāni&lt;/em&gt; occur. Agni is frequently called &amp;lsquo;vratapāḥ&amp;rsquo; in the Ṛgveda (V. 2.8, VI. 8.%, VIII. 11. 1, X. 32.6) and also Sūrya is so called (Ṛg. I. 83.5.). In the other Samhitās Agni is styled ‘vratapā&amp;rsquo; as well as &amp;lsquo;vratapati&amp;rsquo; (protector or lord of vratas). Atharva XX. 25.5 (Sūryo vratapā) is the same as Ṛg. I. 83.5, Atharva XIX. 59.1 (tvam-Agne vratapā asi) is same as Ṛg. VIII. 11.1; Vaj. S. I. 5.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; says &amp;lsquo;O Agni, lord of vratas! I shall undertake a religious observance (or obligation).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Vratādhikārin and related topics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/03_vratAdhikArin_and_related_topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/03_vratAdhikArin_and_related_topics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER III&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Persons entitled to engage in Vratas, objects desired by means of Vratas, classifications of Vratas and literature on Vratas, times for Vratas&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One important matter is that of vratādhikāriṇaḥ (persons entitled to engage in a vrata). Persons of all castes including śūdras are entitled to perform vratas. Devala states: &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;rsquo;there is no doubt that (men of) all &lt;em&gt;varṇas&lt;/em&gt; are released from sins by observing vratas, fasts and restrictive rules of behaviour and by mortification (lit. heating) of the body. Women are also entitled to perform vratas. In fact the purāṇas and digests prescribe several vratas .for women alone. Manu, Viṣṇu Dh. S. and several purāṇas provide that a woman cannot perform a separate sacrifice, a separate vrata or a separate fast by herself, she is honoured in heaven by waiting upon her husband&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Viṣṇu Dh. S. ( 25. 16 )&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; further provides that a woman who observes a vrata in which a fast enters while her husband is alive deprives her husband of his life and herself goes to hell. Whatever act of benefit in the other world a woman does without the consent of her father, husband or son yields no fruit to her&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The medieval digests interpreted these verses as meaning that before performing a vrata, a maiden has to secure the consent of her father, a married woman of her husband and a widow of her son and that with the consent of the persons specified a woman could perform an independent vrata for herself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Individual Vratas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/04_Individual_Vratas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/04_Individual_Vratas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER IV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Individual vratas; Caitra Pratipad, Rāmanavami,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Akṣayya-tṛtiya, Paraśurāmajayanti, Daśaharā,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sāvitri-vrata.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Mahābhārata&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; prescribes how to set about a vrata. &amp;ldquo;Taking in one&amp;rsquo;s hand a copper vessel full of water and turning one&amp;rsquo;s face to the north one should undertake the &lt;em&gt;upavāsa&lt;/em&gt;, or whatever else he resolves in his mind to undertake as a vrata.&amp;rsquo; Devala&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; also says &amp;lsquo;without taking food (the previous night), after taking a bath and having performed &lt;em&gt;ācamana&lt;/em&gt; (ceremonial sipping of water) and after having declared before the Sun and other &lt;em&gt;devatās&lt;/em&gt; (his intent) a person should perform a vrata&amp;rsquo;. The Varāhapurāṇa&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; sets out the formula of &lt;em&gt;saṅkalpa&lt;/em&gt; ‘after passing the 11th tithi without any food, I shall partake of food the next day, O lotus-eyed one (Viṣṇu), O Acyuta, be thou my refuge&amp;rsquo;. The saṅkalpa is to be generally made in the case of a fast&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; or vrata in the morning; the first fifth part of a day comprising three ghaṭikās is called morning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Ekādaśī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/05_ekAdashI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/05_ekAdashI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER V&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The most important tithi in the month of Āṣāḍha is Ekādaśī. A voluminous literature has grown round Ekādaśī in the Purāṇas and medieval digests. There are separate treatises on Ekādaśī written by medieval writers, such as the Ekādaśīviveka of Śūlapāni and the Ekādaśītattva of Raghunandana: Besides, such medieval digests as Kālaviveka (pp. 425-451), Hemādri on Kāla pp. 145–288, Kālanirṇaya of Mādhava (pp. 233–275), Vratarāja pp. 361-475, Kāla-tattvavivecana (pp. 98–172) devote hundreds of pages to discussions on Ekādaśī. Endeavour would be made to write about most of the numerous matters relating to Ekādaśi, but everything would have to be compressed in as small a space as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Cāturmāsya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/06_chAturmAsya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/06_chAturmAsya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER VI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CĀTURMĀSYA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On Āṣāḍha-śukla ekādaśī or dvādaśī or paurṇimā&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; or on the day when the Sun enters the Zodiacal sign Cancer, cāturmāsya vrata is to be observed. Whenever it may be begun it is to be finished on Kārtika-śukla 12. The performer should observe a fast that day, worship Viṣṇu (image) and pray as follows: (Garuḍapurāṇa I. 121. 2–3) &amp;lsquo;O God! I have undertaken this vrata in your presence; may it succeed without obstacles if you become favourable to me; after I undertake this vrata if I die when it is half-finished, may it become completely fulfilled through your favour&amp;rsquo;! The vrata may be begun even when Jupiter or Venus has become invisible and the like. The performer has to give up some edible during the four months, viz. vegetables in Srāvaṇa, curds in Bhādrapada, milk in Āśvina and pulses in Kārtika. According to some authorities, he has to give up some or all vegetables for all the four months. The performer is asked to give up many other things also such as sleeping on a cot, meat, honey &amp;amp;c. When the vrata is finished, he invites brāhmaṇas, announces to them what restrictions he had undertaken, feeds them, gives them dakṣiṇā, and recites the prayer &amp;lsquo;O Lord! this vrata was undertaken by me in order to please you; O Janārdana! may it become complete through your favour, whatever defect there may be!&amp;rsquo; This vrata is even now observed, particularly by women. The Kr̥tyatattva (p. 435), Vratārka, Vrataprakāśa (folio 105a) and other medieval digests quote long passages from the Matsya, Bhaviṣyottara (1. 6-9) and other purāṇas about the results of giving up certain things in the Cāturmāsyavrata. A few passages are set out for sample: &amp;lsquo;a man secures a sweet voice by giving up jaggery, has charming limbs by giving up oil, by giving up ghee he secures beauty, by giving up fruits he becomes intelligent and has many sons, by giving up vegetables and leaves he secures well-cooked dishes, by giving up curds and milk he goes to the world of cows &amp;lsquo;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Vratas in Śrāvaṇa month</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/07_Vratas_in_shrAvaNa_month/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/07_Vratas_in_shrAvaNa_month/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER VII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vratas called Nāgapañcami, Manasāpūjā,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rakṣābandhana, Krṣṇajanmāṣṭami&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the month of Śrāvaṇa there are several important vratas, one of which is Nāgapañcami on the 5th of the bright half of Śrāvaṇa. The Nāgapañcami is observed in different ways in all parts of India. Some hold that, instead of Akṣayyatṛtiyā, Nāgapañcami is the one half auspicious day out of 3 1/2 most auspicious days in the year. The Bhaviṣyapurāṇa, Brāhmaparva (chapter 32 verses 1-39), expatiates on Nāgapañcami. Kr̥tyakalpataru (on vrata) pp. 87-90 and Hemādri (on vrata vol. I. pp. 557-560) quote several verses from the Bhaviṣyapurāṇa. Briefly, the Bhaviṣya &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; says: when men on the 5th bathe with milk the nāgas called Vāsuki, Takṣaka, Kāliya, Maṇibhadra, Airāvata, Dhṛtarāsṭra, Karkoṭaka and Dhanañjaya, these give &lt;em&gt;abhaya&lt;/em&gt; (freedom from danger) to their families. A legend is told (in Bhaviṣya I. 32) that Kadrū, mother of nāgas, laid a bet with her sister Vinatā about the colour of the tail of Indra&amp;rsquo;s horse called Uccaiḥ-śravas, Kadrū asserting that the tail was black though the horse was white and Vinatā saying that the body and tail were white and when the nāgas refused to practise the deceit whereby they were to become the dark hair in the horse&amp;rsquo;s tail, Kadrū cursed them that fire would burn them in the &lt;em&gt;sarpasattra&lt;/em&gt; of Janamejaya). Persons should make golden, silver or clay images of nāgas, should worship them with Karavira and Jāti flowers and incense etc., feed brāhmaṇas with ghee, &lt;em&gt;pāyasa&lt;/em&gt; etc. and should bathe nāgas with milk. The result would be that nāgas would bestow on the worshippers safety (from snake-bite). The Bhaviṣyottarapurāṇa (chap. 36) contains another method. On Śrāvaṇa 5th (bright half) a person should draw on both sides of his door with cowdung figures of serpents which should be worshipped with curds, dūrvā tendrils, kuśas and sandalwood paste, flowers and presents of food. They would have no danger from snakes. Vide Hemādri on Kāla p. 621, K. V. p. 413, K. R. p. 234. In Saurāṣṭra Nāgapañcami is observed in Srāvaṇa dark half.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Vratas in Bhādrapada month</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/08_Vratas_in_bhAdrapada_month/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/08_Vratas_in_bhAdrapada_month/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER VIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vratas of Haritālikā, Gaṇeśacaturthi,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ṛṣipañcami, Anantacaturdaśī.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;haritālikā-vrata&#34;&gt;Haritālikā Vrata&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the 3rd tithi of the bright half of Bhādrapada occurs the Haritālikāvrata for women alone. This vrata is not found in the Kr̥tyakalpataru on vrata or in Hemādri. It is described only in the later medieval digests like the Nirṇayasindhu (p. 133), Vratārka (folios 44 6-49 b), Vratarāja (pp. 103-110) and Ahalyākāmadhenu (folios 282-295). It may, however, be noted that the Rājamārtaṇḍa of Bhoja (first half of 11th century A.D.) devotes four verses to Haritālicaturthi on Bhādrapada 4th of bright half and says it is dear to Pārvati (two of them are quoted below in note).&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is very much in vogue among Mahārāṣṭra women. The following is a brief description. The woman should take an oil and myrobalan paste bath and wear fine silken clothes. After referring to the tithi &amp;amp;c. the woman should make saṅkalpa as noted below.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; She should bow to Umā and Śiva; she should offer worship to Umā by means of the 16 upacāras with appropriate mantras such as āvāhana (invoking to be present), āsana (seat), pādya, arghya &amp;amp;c. After offering flowers the performer should carry out worship of the limbs of Umā from the feet in the form &amp;lsquo;bow to Umā, I worship her feet&amp;rsquo; to the head. Then she should offer incense, lamp, naivedya, &lt;em&gt;ācamaniya&lt;/em&gt;, fragrant substances like camphor and sandalwood for rubbing on the hands, betelnut, _tāmbūla-, &lt;em&gt;dakṣiṇā&lt;/em&gt;, ornaments, &lt;em&gt;nirājana&lt;/em&gt; (waving of a lamp). She should then offer worship to the several names of Umā (such as Gauri, Pārvati &amp;amp;c.) and the several names of Śiva (such as Hara, Mahādeva, Śambhu &amp;amp;c.) and present a handful of flowers, and go round (pradakṣiṇā) the images of Umā and Maheśvara, make with an appropriate mantra in each case an obeisance &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and a prayer and donate presents placed in vessels of wickerwork together with auspicious substances.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 Navarātra or Durgotsava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/09_navarAtra_or_Durgotsava/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/09_navarAtra_or_Durgotsava/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER IX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Navarātra or Durgotsava&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the 1st of Āśvina bright half to the 9th is celebrated the Durgāpūjā festival, otherwise called Navarātra, observed all over India in some form or other. Some of the works&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; provide that Durgotsava must be celebrated in both Śarad (Āśvina-śukla) and Vasanta (in Caitra-śukla). But it is the Durgotsava&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of Āśvina that is celebrated in a grand style, particularly in Bengal, Bihar and Kāmarūpa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Vijayādaśamī and Divāḷi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/10_vijayAdashamI_and_divALLii/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/10_vijayAdashamI_and_divALLii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER X&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vijayādaśamī and Divali&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vijayādaśamī&#34;&gt;Vijayādaśamī&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The 10th tithi of Aśvina-śukla is called Vijayā-daśamī. It is elaborately described in Hemādri (on vrata, vol. 1. pp. 970-973), Nirṇayasindhu (pp. 69-70), Puruṣārtha-cintāmaṇi (pp. 145-148), Vratarāja (pp. 359-361) and Kālatattva-vivecana (pp. 309-312), Dharmasindhu (p. 96). As Daśami (10th tithi) is not mentioned in the &lt;em&gt;Yugmavākya&lt;/em&gt; the Kālanirṇaya relies on a verse that in the bright half that tithi which exists at sunrise should be accepted for performance of rites and in the dark half the one that exists at sunset.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Hemādri proposed (on vrata vol. I. p. 973) two simple rules (when 10th is &lt;em&gt;viddhā&lt;/em&gt;) that that tithi on which Śravaṇa-nakṣatra exists should be accepted and in all other cases 10th mixed with 9th be accepted. But the other digests introduce many other considerations and complicated rules follow. A few of them are given below. If the 10th tithi is mixed up with 9th and 11th, the day on which it is mixed with 9th should be accepted provided there is no Śravaṇa nakṣatra on the next. The Skanda says: Aparājitā-devi should be worshipped by men on the 10th towards the north-east and in the afternoon, when the 10th is mixed with 9th. Aparājita should be worshipped on that day for welfare and victory. Another verse &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is &amp;lsquo;A person should offer worship on the 10th tithi in Āśvina bright half and should not perform the worship of Aparājitā on Ekādaśī.&amp;rsquo; It must be remembered that the proper time for Vijayā-daśamī rites is aparāhṇa (afternoon) and &lt;em&gt;pradoṣa&lt;/em&gt;[^428b] is gauṇakāla (secondary time). If 10th extends over aparāhṇa on two days, the first (i. e. 10th mixed with 9th) should be accepted. If the 10th exists at pradoṣa time (but not at aparāhṇa) on two days, then the later (viz. 10th mixed with 11th) should be accepted;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 Makarasaṅkrānti and Mahāśivarātri</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/11_makarasankrAnti_and_mahAshivarAtri/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/11_makarasankrAnti_and_mahAshivarAtri/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Makarasaṅkrānti and Mahaśivarātri&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;_makara-_saṅkrānti_&#34;&gt;_Makara-&lt;em&gt;saṅkrānti&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a very important religious observance and festival. About 70 years ago (in the author&amp;rsquo;s boyhood) it occurred on the 12th or 13th January according to the several Indian almanacs then current, but now it falls, owing to the procession of the equinoxes, on the 13th or the 14th of January in the month of Pauṣa. Saṅkrānti means &amp;rsquo;the (apparent) passage of the sun from one rāśi (sign of the Zodiac) to the next following&amp;rsquo; and hence the rāśi in which the Sun enters is designated as the saṅkrānti of that name. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; When the Sun leaves the rāśi called Dhanus and enters the Makararāśi that is called Makarasaṅkrānti. The rāśis are twelve and the Saṅkrānti names with their western equivalents are given in the note. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There are only twelve saṅkrāntis even if there be an intercalary month in some year. Everyone of the twelve saṅkrāntis was regarded as a holy day. The Matsya-purāṇa (chap. 98 ) deals with the completion of Saṅkrānti-vrata. Briefly, it provides that on the day previous a person, whether male or female, should take food only once in the noon and on the Saṅkrānti day should brush his teeth and then take a bath with water mixed with sesame &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 Holikā and Grahaṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/12_holikA_and_grahaNa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/12_holikA_and_grahaNa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Holikā and Grahaṇa (eclipse)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;holi-or-holikā&#34;&gt;Holi or Holikā&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Holikā&lt;/em&gt;. Holi or Holikā is a festival of unmixed gaiety and frolics throughout India, though all parts do not observe it in the same way. One element, viz. bonfire, is present almost everywhere except in Bengal. Swinging of Kṛṣṇa image on Phālguna Full Moon is done in Bengal, but it is not observed in several other parts of India. The number of days during which this festival is observed also varies from province to province. Another item which is common to many parts of India is the sprinkling of friends with coloured water from bamboo or metal syringes or with red powder and this merriment is indulged in even now by persons in high places. In the Konkan men dressed as women accompanied by several persons go about with songs (often obscene) and music and dance. The only religious element is the worship of Kṛṣṇa in Bengal and in some provinces where bonfires are made a priest is engaged to perform pūjā before the bonfire, people go round the fire throwing cocoanuts in the burning wood and grass, taking them out half-burnt and distributing the singed kernel among the people present as &lt;em&gt;prasāda&lt;/em&gt;. In some parts people produce sounds by beating their mouths with the backs of their hands. It is not possible nor necessary to set out in this notice all the varying details of this festival throughout the whole of India.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 List of Vratas and Utsavas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/13_List_of_Vratas_and_Utsavas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p1/1_Vratas_and_Utsavas/13_List_of_Vratas_and_Utsavas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XIII&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;List of Abbreviations used in the following&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;List of Vratas&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;AK = Ahalyākāmadhenu (ms).&#xA;BB = Bhujabalanibandha of Bhoja (ms).&#xA;BHP = Bhāgavatapurāṇa.&#xA;BHAV = Bhaviṣyapurāṇa.&#xA;BHAVU = Bhaviṣyottarapurāṇa.&#xA;BR = Brahmāṇḍa-purāṇa.&#xA;BRAH = Brahmapurāṇa.&#xA;BRV = Brahmavaivarta,&#xA;Br. S. = Br̥hat-samhitā of Varāhamihira.&#xA;DE = Devipurāṇa.&#xA;DNS = Dvaitanirṇaya-siddhanta-sangraha.&#xA;DS – Dharmasindhu.&#xA;DT = Durgotsavatattva.&#xA;DV = Durgotsavaviveka of Sūlapāṇi.&#xA;ET= Ekādaśitattva.&#xA;GAR = Garuḍapurāṇa.&#xA;GK = Gadādharapaddhati ( Kālasāra portion).&#xA;HK = Hemādri&amp;rsquo;s Caturvarga-cintāmaṇi on Kāla.&#xA;HV = Hemādri&amp;rsquo;s Vratakhaṇḍa vol. I and II.&#xA;KAL = Kālikāpurāṇa.&#xA;KKN = Naiyatkālika Kāṇḍa of Kr̥tyakalpataru.&#xA;KKV = Vratakāṇḍa of Kr̥tyakalpataru.&#xA;KN = Kālanirṇaya of Mādhava.&#xA;KNK = Kālanirṇaya-kārikā.&#xA;KR = Kr̥tyaratnākara.&#xA;KSS = Kr̥tyasāra-samuccaya.&#xA;KT = Kr̥tyatattva of Raghunandana.&#xA;KTV = Kālatattva-vivecana.&#xA;KÜR = Kūrmapurāṇa.&#xA;KV = Kālaviveka of Jimūtayābana.&#xA;LIN = Liṅgapurāṇa.&#xA;MAR = Mārkaṇḍeya-purāṇa.&#xA;MAT = Matsyapurāṇa.&#xA;MB = Mahābhārata.&#xA;M. Bh. = Mahābhāṣya.&#xA;NA = Nirṇayāmṛta.&#xA;Nār = Nāradapurāṇa.&#xA;NM = Nilamatapurāṇa.&#xA;Nrs = Nr̥siṁha-purāṇa.&#xA;NS = Nirṇayasindhu.&#xA;Pad = Padmapurāṇa.&#xA;PC = Puruṣārtha-cintāmaṇi.&#xA;RM = Rājamartanda of Bhoja (ms).&#xA;RNP = Rājanitiprakāśa ( part of Viramitrodaya).&#xA;SM = Samayamayūkha.&#xA;SMK or SmK= Smṛtikaustubha ( on Tithi and Saṁvatsara ).&#xA;SP= Samayaprakāśa, part of Viramitrodaya.&#xA;SPR or SPr = Samayapradipa of Śrīdatta (ms)&#xA;TT = Tithitattva.&#xA;TV = Tithiviveka of Śūlapāṇi.&#xA;Vā= Vāmanapurāṇa.&#xA;Var= Varāhapurāṇa.&#xA;Vāyu = Vāyupurāṇa.&#xA;V. Dh. = Viṣṇu-dharmasūtra.&#xA;Vi. Dh. = Viṣṇudharmottara-purāṇa.&#xA;Viṣ= Viṣṇupurāṇa.&#xA;VK = Vrata-kośa.&#xA;VKD = Varṣakr̥tya-dipaka.&#xA;VKK = Varṣakriya-kaumudi.&#xA;VKR = Varṣakr̥tya of Rudradhara.&#xA;VKV = Vratakālaviveka.&#xA;VP= Vrataprakāśa ( part of Viramitrodaya) ms.&#xA;VR = Vratarāja.&#xA;VRK = Vratodyāpana-kaumudi.&#xA;VT = Vratatattva.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
