<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 Introduction on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 Introduction on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 INTRODUCING THE *HOMA*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/01_INTRODUCING_THE_HOMA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/01_INTRODUCING_THE_HOMA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since research on the &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; is important for both ritual studies and the study of Asian religions, it is a nexus of interaction for these two fields of study. It is important for ritual studies because this one ritual, despite particular sectarian inflections, has a history of more than two millennia, and the Indo-Iranian and Vedic rituals that form an important part of the source material for its development, extends that history to as much as four millennia. Over the course of its history, the &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; has spread out from the Indian subcontinent into several different religious cultures, and in addition to South Asia, it is also found in Central Asia, East Asia, Southeast Asia, as well as now in Europe and the Americas. It is, therefore, one of very few instances of a ritual that can be studied over the &lt;em&gt;longue durée&lt;/em&gt;, having undergone repeated ritual change and cultural adaptation while at the same time retaining an extensive and detailed textual record, and a clearly identifiable continuity of ritual practice.2&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 RITUAL, CEREMONIAL, FESTIVAL</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/02_RITUAL_CEREMONIAL_FESTIVAL/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/02_RITUAL_CEREMONIAL_FESTIVAL/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As described in the essays that comprise this collection, the &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; can be performed in a variety of different settings. In one case, for example, it is found as one element within a much larger complex of religious activities, such as the &lt;em&gt;Navarātra&lt;/em&gt; described by Nawaraj Chaulagain in his chapter. In other cases, the &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; is performed as a stand-alone ritual, such as in the Shugendō &lt;em&gt;saitō goma&lt;/em&gt; discussed by Richard Payne. Such wide-ranging differences in the context of a &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; performance may raise for some readers categorial concerns—what are we talking about when we say that the &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; is a ritual, or that it is an element of a larger ceremonial sequence, or that it is performed as part of a festival? In contrast to some other approaches, we assert that it is not in fact possible to draw clear distinctions between these kinds of activities. While the categories are inherently fuzzy, the reflections of some earlier scholars helps us to discern a conceptual landscape within which to negotiate our path between &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; as stand-alone ritual and as element in ceremonies or as part of a festival.10&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 STUDYING THE DYNAMICS OF RITUAL CHANGE: THE *LONGUE DURÉE*</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/03_STUDYING_THE_DYNAMICS_OF_RITUAL_CHANGE_THE_LONGUE_DURE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/03_STUDYING_THE_DYNAMICS_OF_RITUAL_CHANGE_THE_LONGUE_DURE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The theoretical movement away from functionalist explanations, which emphasized stability and the return to the norm, has opened consideration of change and disruption as the normal state of affairs. As Pamela J. Stewart and Andrew Strathern put it, “studies of ritual practices today take into account not only variation but also creativity and innovation. This is in line with a general shift towards the study of change as distinct from continuity.”23 Many of the studies of ritual change that have appeared following this movement away from functionalist presumptions of stability and homeostasis have examined a particular ritual as it changes over a relatively short period of time. This has involved rethinking the status of ritual as historical, rather than as part of an eternal, unchanging religious reality. John D. Kelly and Martha Kaplan have suggested that “Nowhere more than in the study of ritual has the turn to history raised fundamental questions for anthropology.”24 While ritual is frequently now discussed as process, practice, or performance, this needs to be qualified by a conception of any particular ritual as a historical entity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 HOW TO CROSS THE *LONGUE DURÉE*: TEXTS \&#43; ETHNOGRAPHY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/04_HOW_TO_CROSS_THE_LONGUE_DURE_TEXTS_ETHNOGRAPHY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/04_HOW_TO_CROSS_THE_LONGUE_DURE_TEXTS_ETHNOGRAPHY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the historical study of ritual, that is over the &lt;em&gt;longue durée&lt;/em&gt;, it is necessary to have recourse to texts. Philippe Buc has claimed, however, that dependence solely upon texts is methodologically problematic “because we do not have access to ritual practices, but only to texts depicting them (a given that renders impossible from the very start the use of certain kinds of anthropological models).”93 This is, however, one of the things that makes the &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; especially valuable for the longitudinal study of ritual change.94 First, there is an extensive ritual literature specifically on the &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt;—including not only descriptions but also prescriptions, that is, ritual manuals. This literature continues for well-over a millennium and a half, is found throughout the tantric world, and in several of the languages of that world. And, second, this literary record is complemented by several living religious traditions in which the &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; continues to be performed. These traditions are found in quite different religious cultures and are available for observation as a publicly performed ritual. It seems entirely plausible that were a ninth-century Śaivite tantrika to somehow observe a &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; performed in the Shingon temple in Sacramento, California, on a New Year’s morning in the twenty-first century he would recognize it as a variant of the ritual with which he was already intimately familiar.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 ORGANIZATION AND CONTENTS OF THIS COLLECTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/05_ORGANIZATION_AND_CONTENTS_OF_THIS_COLLECTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/05_ORGANIZATION_AND_CONTENTS_OF_THIS_COLLECTION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The essays of this collection are purposely not arranged according to any of the three systematics that are effectively normative for the study of religious traditions, whether in Asia or not. These three—chronological, geo-political, and sectarian—have become effectively naturalized as the proper categories for the study of religions. However, change is not chronologically uniform and developmental, religions engaged with power structures that were different from those familiar to us today (nation-states), and participants in traditions sometimes actively sought out other traditions for purposes of adaptation, appropriation, or rebuttal. For these reasons, the reader will not find the essays arranged in a chronological sequence, such as classic, medieval, and modern. Chronological divisions are usually more representative of political and military events, and constitute a presumptive framework into which the history of religious cultures is forced. More important, when considering the processes of ritual change, there is no reason to assume that there is a single, progressive history that can be used to structure a developmental sequence. Too often chronological periodization of this kind implicitly carries with it the sense of progressive development, that is, that later is somehow better. Nor are the essays grouped by geo-political categories—India, Nepal, Tibet, China, Japan. Such categories themselves often reflect contemporary power structures—both political and academic—rather than the connections between religious practices that concern us here. Geographical groupings frequently serve to minimize continuity across geo-political boundaries, emphasizing instead new developments supposedly more authentically responsive to the host culture. Lastly, the commonly deployed divisions of sectarian affiliation,111 such as Hindu and Buddhist, no matter how carefully nuanced within such divisions (whether Vedic, Brahmanic, Hindu, or Theravāda, Mahāyāna, Vajrayāna, for example), facilitate the kind of divisive specialization common to contemporary academia.112 Use of sectarian affiliation has frequently resulted in a kind of hermetic treatment, one in which changes in a tradition are understood solely in terms of its own preceding history, ignoring outside influences as part of the context of change.113 Such specialization promotes hermetic understandings of traditions, for example, only looking to earlier Buddhist sources for later Buddhist developments or representing Hinduism by the Bhagavadgītā. In the study of ritual per se and practice more generally, the kind of clear divisions commonly institutionalized in academia all too often inhibit the recognition of patterns that transcend those divisions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 CONCLUSION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/06_CONCLUSION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/06_CONCLUSION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Several significant themes run through these essays, though not necessarily evident in all of them. These include the interiorization of ritual. Although the psychologized character of contemporary society may lead us to presume that this means performing the ritual as a mental visualization, Indic religious culture gives greater emphasis to an embodied basis for such interiorization.119 This usually involves a psycho-physical symbolism, and in some cases includes equations between ritual actions and breathing, digestion, and sexual intercourse. Another theme, this one of value for tracing historical relations between different lineages of ritual practice are the categories of ritual functions, whether three, four, or five. These functional categories—protection, conquest, and so on—are directly coterminous with such matters as shapes of hearth, the colors used in the ritual, such as the practitioner’s garb, the time of day the ritual is to be performed, the direction that the ritual is to be oriented, the kind of wood to be used in building the fire, the selection of offerings to be made, and so on. The &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; has several different kinds of broader applications to which it is put in different ritual cultures. Important are, for example, the consecration of images, use in building rites, and in some traditions as the final ritual in a larger ceremonial complex. In addition to the set functions and applications, practice of the &lt;em&gt;homa&lt;/em&gt; is often taken to be conducive to liberation or awakening. Frequently, the symbolism involved includes the destruction of the practitioner’s attachments or obscurations by their identification with the offerings being made into the fire. Just as Agni consumes the offerings and purifies them so that they are acceptable to the deities, so the fire consumes and transforms the fetters binding the practitioner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 NOTES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/07_NOTES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/vishvAsaH/kriyA-nishchayaH/homaH/articles/homa-variations/01_Introduction/07_NOTES/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;REFERENCES&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;App, Urs. &lt;em&gt;The Birth of Orientalism.&lt;/em&gt; Philadelphia and Oxford: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bell, Catherine. &lt;em&gt;Ritual Theory, Ritual Practice.&lt;/em&gt; New York and Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1992.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bellah, Robert N. &lt;em&gt;Religion in Human Evolution: From the Paleolithic to the Axial Age&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge, MA, and London: Harvard University Press, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Beyer, Stephan. “Notes on the Vision Quest in Early Mahāyāna.” In Lewis Lancaster, ed. &lt;em&gt;Prajñāpāramitā and Related Systems: Studies in Honor of Edward Conze&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 329–340. Berkeley: The Group in Buddhist Studies, and the Center for South &amp;amp; Southeast Asian Studies at the University of California, Berkeley, and The Institute of Buddhist Studies, 1977.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
