<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;00 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;00 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Abbreviations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Abbreviations/</guid>
      <description>ABBREVIATIONS used in vol. V for works in English and Sanskrit.
On pp. 251-252 there is a list of abbreviations meant for the list of Vratas alone. Many of them will be included in this list also. A. B. O. R. I. - Annals of the Bhandarkar Oriental Re
search Institute, Poona. AIHT=&amp;quot; Ancient Indian Historical Tradition&amp;quot; by
Pargiter. Ait. Br. = Aitareya-brāhmaṇa.
A.T. 0. C.= All India Oriental Conference. A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chronological Table</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Chronological_Table/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Chronological_Table/</guid>
      <description>CHRONOLOGICAL TABLE of some important works and authors.
referred to in vol. V.
N. B. Some dates, particularly of ancient works, are
more or less conjectural. 4000 B. C.-1000 B. C.- The period of the Vedic Saṁ
hitās, Brālımaṇas and Upaniṣads ; some hymns of the Rgveda, of the Atharvaveda and verses in the Taittirīya Samhitā and Brāhmanas may possibly go back to a period earlier than 4000 B. C. and some of the Upaniṣads (even from among those that are regarded by most scholars as the earliest ones) may be later than 1000 B.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Corrections</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Corrections/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Corrections/</guid>
      <description>CORRECTIONS
Mistakes that can be easily detected and mis prints due to the loss or displacement of sach loose parts as anustāras or mātrās or diacritical dots ( as under t) that can be easily detected have generally not been included in this list. Page Line or note
384 20
read on Śa 7th ; when&amp;rsquo; 494 n. 719, 1. 7 read from&amp;rsquo; for &amp;lsquo;form&amp;rsquo;
„ .722, 1. 2 from bottom read.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Foreword</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Foreword/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Foreword/</guid>
      <description>FOREWORD
Professor Pandurang Vaman Kane, by his monu mental volumes on Dharmaśāstra, has placed us all under a deep debt of gratitude to him. His work is of lasting value. At a time when we are building an integrated Indian society, a dispassionate study of our Dharmasāstras is essential. By his work we are helped to understand what is living and what is dead in the heritage which has come down to us.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preface</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Preface/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Preface/</guid>
      <description>PREFACE TO VOLUME V
The fourth volume of the History of Dharmaśāstra was published in October 1953, i.e. more than eight years ago. This last volume was in the Press for more than five years. The delay is due to several causes This volume in two parts contains over 1700 pages. It is thus far more bulky than any of the previous volumes. Nonavailability of sufficient quantity of good printing paper was another cause.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publisher&#39;s Note</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Publishers_Note/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Publishers_Note/</guid>
      <description>PUBLISHER&amp;rsquo;S NOTE
It is with a sense of profound gratification that the Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institute presents to the public the second part of the fifth and last volume of the History of Dharmaśāstra by MM. Professor Dr. P. V. Kane, National Professor of Indology. With this part, this monumental literary project, which was conceived by the author more than thirty years ago, has been brought to a successful completion. This must, indeed, be regarded as a memorable event in the history of Indological studies and research in this country.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>References to Works Consulted</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/References_to_Works_Consulted/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/References_to_Works_Consulted/</guid>
      <description>References to pages of important works consulted
In former volumes lists of important works con sulted were set out at length. It is not necessary to do this in this volume because in each section lists of important Sanskrit works and English works and papers have been provided. Therefore, all that need be done is to bring together the pages of this volume where such lists are mostly mentioned.
Works in Sanskrit</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Synopsis of Contents</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Synopsis_of_Contents/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Synopsis_of_Contents/</guid>
      <description>BRIEF SYNOPSIS OF THE CONTENTS OF VOLUME Y
Pages
Section I. Vratas ( religious vows ) and Utsavas
(religious festivals )
1-462 Chapter I. Vrata in the Rgveda.
1-21 Chapter II. Vrata in the Vedic Literature,
Sūtras, Smśtis, definition and importance of Vratas.
22-50
Chapter III. Persons entitled to engage in
Vratas, .objects desired by means of Vra tas, classifications of Vratas, Literature on Vratas, times for Vratas.
51-80 Chapter IV.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Table of Contents</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Table_of_Contents/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v5p2/00/Table_of_Contents/</guid>
      <description>TABLE OF CONTENTS
Pages
i-vi &amp;hellip; vii &amp;hellip; si-xvii
xviii-XXV XXvi-xxix
Foreword Preface Chronological Table Abbreviations &amp;hellip; &amp;hellip; Brief synopsis of the contents References to pages of important works consulted Corrections Bistory of Dharmaśāstra, Vol. V, Pt. 2 &amp;hellip; Epilogue, Acknowledgements and Thanks &amp;hellip; Index &amp;hellip;
XXxi-xxxίν
718–1711 &amp;hellip; i–xxii &amp;hellip; 1-269</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
