<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;05 Purāṇas and Buddhism on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/05_purANas_and_Buddhism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;05 Purāṇas and Buddhism on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/05_purANas_and_Buddhism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>24 Influence of Purāṇas on Dharmaśāstra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/05_purANas_and_Buddhism/24_Influence_of_purANas_on_dharmashAstra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/05_purANas_and_Buddhism/24_Influence_of_purANas_on_dharmashAstra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECTION V&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXIV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Influence of Purāṇas on Dharmasastra&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literary works and society act and re-act on each other. The state of Indian society &amp;amp; few centuries before and after Christ, riven as it was by the growing strength and onslaught of Buddhism, Jainism and other dissenting sects and disturbed by invasions of the Greeks, Sakas, Pahlavas, Hūpas and other foreign tribes, gave much food for thought to those who were devoted to the Vedic religion and induced them to write works setting forth new ideologies and practices and effecting a re statement of the ancient Vedic and Smrti religion. When these works attained a position of authority and eminence, the endea vour of the followers of the Veda was to follow them as far as possible and to adapt their practices and religious rites to the requirements of the Purāṇas. We have to see how the Purāṇas Bet about their task of re-orientation. We must note that current Hindu religious practices, judging from the saṅkalpa made at the beginning of every rite, are meant to confer upon the per former the rewards declared by Śruti (Veda), Smrti and Purāpas (Sruti-smrti-purāpokta-phalaprāptyartham). The task was two fold, viz. (1) to undermine the power and prestige of Buddhism and Jainism and the influence of the numerous philosophical 1447 schools that had sprung up and (2) to wean away large sections of the masses from the attractive features of Buddhism and to convince them that they could secure in the re-orientated Hindu faith the same benefits, social and spiritual, as Buddhism promised and that the religious principles of the followers of Veda coincided with many of the teachings of Buddhism and were borrowed by Buddhism from Vedic practices. Ultimately Buddhism vanished from the land of its origin. The main causes of this disappearance of Buddhism from Bhārata will be stated at the end of this section, but this much may be said here at once that the Purāpas played a substantial role in bring&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 Causes of Disappearance of Buddhism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/05_purANas_and_Buddhism/25_Causes_of_Disappearance_of_Buddhism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/kANe/history/v5p2/05_purANas_and_Buddhism/25_Causes_of_Disappearance_of_Buddhism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER XXV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Causes of the Disappearance of Buddhism from India.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of Chapter XXIV (pp. 913-14, n 1448) above, it was stated that the Purāṇas had a large share in bringing about the final disappearance of Buddhism from India, the land of its birth. The disappearance of Buddhism from India was complete and seemed to be sudden and is a com plex problem. No single cause, nor even a few causes oan fully account for this phenomenon. A combination of causes, both internal and external, must have been in operation for a pretty long time to bring about this remarkable event. It may be admitted that some of the causes are more or less conjectural. In the first quarter of the 5th century A. D. Fa-Hian found Buddhism in a flourishing condition in India, while in the first half of the 7th century A.D. Yuan Chwang appears to say that the decline of Buddhism had set in. It-sing found Buddhism very much on the decline in the beginning of the 8th century A.D. An attempt will be made here to discuss briefly the goveral causes that have been put forward by scholars for explaining the almost total disappearance of Buddhism from India. A few of the contributions bearing on this subjeot may be noted here. &amp;lsquo;Religions of India&amp;rsquo; by A. Barth, translated by J. Wood (1882) pp. 133-139; Journal of Pali Texts Society (1896 pp. 87-92) on *Persecution of Buddhists in India&amp;rsquo; by Rhys Davids; Kern&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Manual of Buddhism&amp;rsquo;(in the German Grundriss pp. 133-134);&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
