<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Kalari origin</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/articles/kalari-origin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/articles/kalari-origin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tulu Nadu is considered as birthplace of Kalaripayattu. The highest form of Kalari Vidya said to have existed there. Many Nair and Brahmin practitioners of Tulu Nadan Kalari were imported into Kerala by the rulers to train their troops.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The four Nair families of Valluvanad which supplied Chavers (suicide fighters) to Valluvanad Raja in Mamankam trace their origins to Tulu Nadu and were experts in Tulu Nadan Kalari Vidya.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Quite interestingly the Dharmoth Panickers who were the commanders of the Nair forces of the Samuthiris of Calicut also have their origin in Tulu Nadu. It seems many important Nair families like them share Tulu origin.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>pAtaka confiscation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/articles/pAtaka-confiscation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/articles/pAtaka-confiscation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1741872288801452328.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In Manusmriti chapter 9, there is discussion about what the texts call Mahapatakas- great crimes that brings upon great Paapam (karmic demerit) to the performer and causes injury to society. These include murder, stealing, adultery, etc. In this context Manu says that the perpetrators if they refuse to perform expiation, they must be banished after confiscating all their property.  In this context, the text adds following verses:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;King shall not appropriate property of man guilty of heinous crime; if, through greed he takes it, he becomes tainted with that guilt—9.243&lt;br&gt;&#xA;He shall deposit such property in water &amp;amp; offer it to Varuṇa or bestow it on a Brāhmaṇa endowed with Vedic learning and character—9.244&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>śaṅkara-smr̥ti-notes</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/articles/shankara-smRti-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/articles/shankara-smRti-notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: akshay nair&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;nambutiri-paternal-uncle-shraddha&#34;&gt;nambUtiri-paternal-uncle-shrAddha&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In Shankarasmriti, the code of law which became popular in Kerala with rise of Namboothiri tradition, It is stated that the eldest son in a family must perform Pitr Karma for all his paternal uncles as well.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is since younger brothers of father mostly married into matrilineal castes like Kshatriya-Nairs and Ambalavasis, and they did not have any heir to perform Pitra Karma for them becuase children in these unions belonged to mother&amp;rsquo;s family and they performed Pitr Karma to their maternal uncles or karnavars instead of their fathers. Hence, the eldest son in a Namboothiri Brahmin household performed Pitr Karma to his paternal uncles along with his father.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tulu daivArAdhanam</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/articles/tulu-daivArAdhanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/articles/tulu-daivArAdhanam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/mangaluru/modern-lives-ancient-duties-how-tulunadus-youth-blend-careers-with-sacred-daivaradhane-traditions/articleshow/120090627.cms&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Modern lives, ancient duties: How Tulunadu&amp;rsquo;s youth blend careers with sacred &amp;lsquo;Daivaradhane&amp;rsquo; traditions&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Deepthi Sanjiv / TNN / Apr 8, 2025, 15:03 IST&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Daivaradhane, a spiritual tradition in Tulunadu, is being preserved by individuals from diverse professional backgrounds. Despite financial struggles, community members are pursuing education and excelling in various fields while upholding their ancestral roles as daivanarthakas and daiva patris. They balance modern careers with spiritual responsibilities, ensuring the continuation of this sacred practice for future generations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
