<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Olivelle on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Olivelle on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ArthashAstra trade</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/arthashAstra-trade/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/arthashAstra-trade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It was the middle of the first century of the common era, and in the prosperous city of Rome, the capital of the great Roman Empire, a brilliant intellectual was writing a book called &lt;em&gt;Natural History&lt;/em&gt;. His name was Pliny, best known as Pliny the Elder. He comments on Rome’s booming trade with India, deploring two of its adverse effects of globalisation. Indians loved Mediterranean red coral so much, Pliny complains, that coral had become scarce in the land of its origin. And Roman ladies loved Indian pearls and fine textiles so much that, to pay for them, much of Rome’s gold found its way to India. “So dearly do we pay for our women and our luxuries,” Pliny exclaims.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ashoka &amp; varNa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/ashoka_varNa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/ashoka_varNa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ashoka reveals that he was aware of the social and religious makeup of various countries. In Rock Edict XIII, for example, he says that there is no land where the two classes of religious people—Brahmins and Sramanas—are absent, but quickly adds an exception. They are not found in the Greek kingdoms beyond his north-western border. He notes, however: ‘Yet even where they are not found’—presumably in the Greek territories—‘there is no land where human beings are not devoted to one Pasanda or another.’+++(4)+++ So, Pasandas, discussed in Chapter 11, are found even among the Greeks. Here, Ashoka is making a broad-brush statement about a marked difference in the religions and religious organizations between his own country and the countries of West Asia.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>dharma dvija upavIta history</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/dharma-dvija-upavIta-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/dharma-dvija-upavIta-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a saying that goes: In life, familiarity breeds contempt. But in scholarship, familiarity breeds acceptance. This is an adage to which I wholeheartedly subscribe. Unfortunately, such acceptance does not always remain within the ivory towers of academia; it often seeps into popular imagination, infects common discourse, and is frequently transformed into common sense in statements that begin with, “Everybody knows…”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Much of the common wisdom about ancient India, I am afraid, is highly suspect, especially the view that ideas and institutions have existed since the hoary past, from time immemorial. The Sanskrit term &lt;em&gt;sanātana,&lt;/em&gt; much in vogue these days, has been co–opted to express these views. Today, I want to debunk some of these presuppositions in the hope that more people—not just scholars—will question what is peddled as received wisdom. To do this, we must subject these cultural constructs to historical and philological scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GArgI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/gArgI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/gArgI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;King Janaka, better known to Indians as the father of Sita, once invited learned Brahmins to celebrate a lavish ritual. Videha, the kingdom over which he ruled, was in the east and viewed as a backwater by the intellectual elite of the western regions of Kuru-Panchala, the bastion of Brahminical culture. Perhaps wanting to impress upon his guests the intellectual vibrancy of his own region, Janaka challenged the assembled Brahmins to a contest that would determine the most learned person among them, offering the winner a thousand cows with their horns and hooves adorned with gold.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jurist history - olivelle</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/jurist-history-olivelle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/jurist-history-olivelle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;विस्तारः (द्रष्टुं नोद्यम्)&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Patrick Olivelle is Professor Emeritus of Asian Studies at the University of Texas at Austin. He is known for his work on early Indian religions, law, and statecraft. Views are personal.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Edited by Prasanna Bachchhav)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kautilya’s &amp;lsquo;Arthashastra&amp;rsquo;, Manu’s laws—Ancient India had rich literature on jurisprudence&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was part of an editorial team that produced the &lt;em&gt;Cambridge Comparative History of Ancient Law&lt;/em&gt;, which was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/cambridge-comparative-history-of-ancient-law/178F6A118ECB178E303D5D5F8DFDAFAB&#34;&gt;just published&lt;/a&gt;. As I was writing the chapter on ‘Legal Procedure’, it became obvious that ancient India produced some of the richest literature on this topic, vastly more copious and sophisticated than that of any other ancient civilisation. In the process, the Indian jurists created a well-developed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.in/Sanskrit-Dictionary-Law-Statecraft/dp/9384082643&#34;&gt;technical vocabulary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>kauTilya actors</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/kauTilya-actors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/kauTilya-actors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The prominence of the entertainment industry—from Bollywood to Hollywood, from Beyoncé to &lt;a href=&#34;https://time.com/6307420/taylor-swift-eras-tour-money-economy&#34;&gt;Taylor Swift&lt;/a&gt;—in today’s economies is obvious. &lt;em&gt;Time Magazine&lt;/em&gt; wrote, “If Taylor Swift were an economy, she’d be bigger than 50 countries.” When Beyoncé held a concert in Sweden, the national &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/06/15/business/beyonce-inflation-sweden.html&#34;&gt;inflation rate surged to 9.7 per cent&lt;/a&gt; because of the increased demand for hotels and restaurants.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Humans, even ancient humans, needed to pass the time, to keep themselves entertained as they sat around a campfire in the evenings. Storytellers, dancers, drummers, singers—these were common to all ancient societies. The question I want to address today is: How did ancient Indians entertain themselves?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MaitreyI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/maitreyI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/maitreyI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A woman is either a mother or a wife—this was the commonly held view of women in most ancient societies, including India. In an earlier column, we met sage Yajnavalkya as he debated with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://theprint.in/opinion/theprint-purana/gargi-vachaknavi-indias-first-woman-philosopher-who-shut-up-men-in-king-janakas-court/1908896/&#34;&gt;philosopher Gargi&lt;/a&gt;, an independent, intelligent, and self-confident woman who broke this mould.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here, I want to introduce you to two other women in another, more intimate Yajnavalkya episode. They are Maitreyi and Katyayani, the sage’s two wives. Interestingly, this story is repeated twice in the _Brihadaranyaka, _the oldest of the Upanishads, with many variants.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Panchatantra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/panchatantra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/panchatantra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Perhaps no other book from ancient India has been, and continues to be, loved more by people in India and across the globe than the &lt;em&gt;Panchatantra&lt;/em&gt;. Even those who do not know its name have been exposed to its charming stories that their mothers told them when they were children. Its fame was such that travellers and storytellers took this little gem of a book on a journey around the world. Franklin Edgerton, who attempted to reconstruct the original text from the extant versions, commented on the popularity of the &lt;em&gt;Panchatantra&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>YudhiShThira vs ashoka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/yudhiShThira_vs_ashoka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/dharmaH/nibandhaH/en/olivelle/yudhiShThira_vs_ashoka/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Violence has been deeply ingrained in societies throughout human history. &lt;em&gt;The Cambridge World History of Violence&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/services/aop-cambridge-core/content/view/3B6796C6FCBC36ACD5663C9646C1C26B/9781107120129int1_1-18.pdf/general_introduction_violence_in_world_history.pdf&#34;&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt;: “A number of scholars…have argued that violence and war are part of human nature, a part of our biological makeup.” The emergence of a distinct warrior ideology, coupled with professional warrior classes, marked a new epoch in this history of inter-group violence. Political violence in ancient India is admirably illustrated by Upinder Singh in her brilliant book, &lt;em&gt;Political Violence in Ancient India&lt;/em&gt;. Beyond the political, there is also religious violence in the ritual sacrifice of animals and culinary violence in killing animals for food.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
