<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;प्रयोजनम् on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/prayojanam/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;प्रयोजनम् on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/prayojanam/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Benefits</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/prayojanam/benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/prayojanam/benefits/</guid>
      <description>Survival, thriving and competitive advantage From the point of view of nature, in the context of competing cultural memes, the ultimate value of dharma memeplex is the fitness benefit it provides to the society.
In all likelihood, as the wise have noted (20151212), it was this memeplex (esp: notion of dharma, shAstra-s and a strong brahma-kShatra social system) that was instrumental in its votaries sweeping away and dominating all resistance across vast swathes of geography and time; while assimilating and adapting new entrants and peripheral practices of other pagans.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goal</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/prayojanam/goal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/prayojanam/goal/</guid>
      <description>Hindu self-cultivation gives one joy, satisfaction, and strength to follow and achieve the various goals of life(puruShArtha), including dharma. This includes attainment of mystic &amp;ldquo;highs&amp;rdquo; as a matter of course. With spiritual practices and saMskAra-s, a hindu gets both intellectual and emotional appreciation for his place in the world-tree.
Spiritual highs One needs joy, satisfaction, and strength to follow and achieve the various goals of life, including dharma. Spirituality (a focus on the development and maintenance of &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; mental states) is then an essential component of hindu self cultivation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intellect, sentiment Record</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/prayojanam/intellect-sentiment-record/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/vishvAsaH/meta-dharma/prayojanam/intellect-sentiment-record/</guid>
      <description>Scholasticism, intellectual and sentimental life. The beauty and depth that is the dharmic civilization and traditions is considered elsewhere.
Consider the list of individual heroes involved in scholarly pursuit. Contributions were abundant in the fields of Psychology, philosophy and physical training (remember the yoga-Asanas and the many martial arts). &amp;ldquo;If we look at the old Hindu education system it clearly had a mechanism to fast-track scientific talent which the modern Indian system woefully lacks.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
