<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1.2 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1.2 on कल्पान्तरे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>065 Dhāreśvara Bhojadeva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/065_dhAreshvara_Bhojadeva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/065_dhAreshvara_Bhojadeva/</guid>
      <description>Dhāresvara Bhojadeva The Mit. (on Yāj. II. 135) says that Dhāreśvara tries to re concile the conflicting texts about the right of the widow to succeed to her husband&amp;rsquo;s estate by saying that she succeeded if her husband was separate and if she was willing to submit to niyoga. On the same verse the Mit. says that following Mānu IX. 217 Dhāreśvara placed the paternal grand-mother immediately after the mother as an heir and even before the father.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>066 Devasvāmin</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/066_devasvAmin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/066_devasvAmin/</guid>
      <description>Devasyamin The Smṛticandrikā tells us that Devasvā min composed like Srīkara and Sambhu a work in the nature of a digest of smrtis (smrtisamuccaya ). Vide note 748 above. The com mentary of Nārāyana of the Naidhruva gotra, son of Divākara, on the Asvalāyanagrhyasūtra788 says that it relies upon the bhāsya of Devasvāmin on the same work Gārgya Nārāyana, son of Narasimha, in bis commentary on the Asvalāyana srautasūtra, tells us that he follows the bhāsya of Devasvāmin thereon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>067 Jitendriya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/067_Jitendriya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/067_Jitendriya/</guid>
      <description>Jitendriya Jitendriya is one of those writers who at one time held an eminent position but in course of time sank into unmerited oblivion. The works of Jimūtavāhana bear abundant testi mony to the fact that Jitendriya wrote an extensive work on dharmaśāstra. In his Kālaviveka (p. 380 ) Jimūta vāhana says that Jitendriya797 wrote on the topic of kāla (i. e. on determining doubtful points about the months, the tithis, samkrāntis, &amp;amp;c, and the religious rites to be performed on them ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>068 Bālaka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/068_bAlaka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/068_bAlaka/</guid>
      <description>Balaka Balaka like Jitendriya is no more than a name to us. Jimūta vāhana&amp;rsquo;s works make frequent reference to him. He held the view that the daughter&amp;rsquo;s son, not being expressly mentioned as an heir by Yāj., came in after those expressly mentioned from the widow to the brother.305 The Dāyabhāga notices that Balaka read a text of Apastamba in a wrong way.s06 Balaka said that the words of Saṅkha &amp;lsquo;svaryatasya aputrasya bhrātrgāmi dravyam&amp;hellip;jyesthā vā patnī&amp;rsquo; apply either to a widow belonging to a caste other than her husband&amp;rsquo;s or to a very young widow or in case her husband was undivided or re-united.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>069 Bālarūpa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/069_bAlarUpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/069_bAlarUpa/</guid>
      <description>Balarupa In the Smrtisāra of Harinātha (I. O. cat. No. 301, folio 128a ff) there is a long passage setting out the views of Bālarūpa on the question of the succession to a childless man. In the Vivadacandrasil of fisaru-misra the opinions of Bala 808 बालकेनाप्युक्तं न टेकेन भ्रात्रा विद्यादिना लब्धेऽपरेषामधिकारसंभवः प्रमाणा
भावादित्यन्तेन । दायभाग p. 190 ( P. 120 of Jivananda ). 809 अतो यबालकवचनं यथा मुद्दापचारे मापप्रतिनिधों मुद्गानां माषाणां च</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>070 Yogloka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/070_Yogloka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/070_Yogloka/</guid>
      <description>Yogloka Yogloka like Jitendriya and Balaka is a writer about whom we know only from the works of Jimītavāhana and Raghunandana. He is the last of the series of writers enume rated in one place by the Kalaviveka as having dealt with the subject of kālu (vide note 611 above). The Vyavahāra mātṛkā of Jimūtavāhana very frequently $15 cites the views of Yogloka and generally twits him with thinking himself as being a logician or a new-fangled (navu-tārkikai-manya) logician.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>071 Vijñāneśvara</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/071_vijnAneshvara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/071_vijnAneshvara/</guid>
      <description>Vijñanesvara The Mitāksarā of Vijñāneśvara occupies a unique place in the Dharmaśāstra literature. Its position is analogous to that of the Mahabhāsya of Patanjali in grammar or to that of the Kāvyaprakāśa of Mammaṭa in Poetics. It represents the essence of dharmaśāstra speculation that preceded it for about two thousand years and it became the fountain head from which flowed fresh streams of exegesis and developments. Under the decisions of the Courts in British India, the Mitā ksarā is of paramount authority in several matters of Hindu Law (such as adoption, inheritance, partition etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>072 Kāmadhenu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/072_kAmadhenu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/072_kAmadhenu/</guid>
      <description>Kamadhenu This was an early and large digest on various branches of Dharmaśāstra. Unfortunately no ms, of it has been recovered so far, but it has been profusely quoted by a large number of writers on the several topics of Dharmaśāstra. Unexpected light has been thrown on it hy the publication of the Bralima cārikāṇla of the Kalpataru, composed by Laksmidhara, the chief muntriin of the Gāhadvāla king Govindachandra of Kanyakuhja ( Kanoj ) and Banaras.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>073 Halāyudha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/073_halAyudha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/073_halAyudha/</guid>
      <description>Halāyudha Several Halāyudhas flourished at different times. Chro nology being rather uncertain those of them that have some bearing on Dharinaśāstra would be dealt with in one place. though an attempt will be made to assign to them approxi mately definite times as far as possible. दौ देवे&amp;hellip;कमुभयत्र वा ॥ यदप्येकैकमुभयत्र वेत्ययं विधिरेव न भवतीति तेनैवोक्तं तत्तु शम्भुप्रभृतिभिर्निबन्धकारः पराकृतमिति अम्माभिर्नाद्रियते । चतुर्वर्ग० III. I. p. 1148 ; TC M7 Eigula THEIGHTÀ TUTTAR</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>074 Bhavadevabhaṭṭa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/074_bhavadevabhaTTa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/074_bhavadevabhaTTa/</guid>
      <description>Bhavadevabhatta The Vyavahāratattva of Raghunandana and the Vira mitroda ya tell us that Bhavadevabhatta composed a work call ed Vyavahāratilaka on judicial procedure. The Vyavahāra tattva 868 tells us that Bhavadeva read &amp;lsquo;astavyasta padavyāpi&amp;rsquo; instead of &amp;lsquo;yadvyastapadamavyāpi&amp;rsquo; in Kātyāyana&amp;rsquo;s verses
867 कर्को व्याख्यदिदं गभीरवचनैः सूत्रं यतोस्मादभूद् दुर्बोधं च ततो हलायुध इति
व्याख्यत्तथा यस्फुटम् ॥ 868 &amp;lsquo;अस्तव्यस्तपदव्यापि अनन्वितार्थपदव्याप्तमिति व्यवहारतिलके भवदेवभट्टः।
TERRITT (p. 297, vol. II, Jivananda ); vacaa Fogg146641 पीति पाठं लिखित्वानन्वितार्थपदव्याप्तमिति व्याख्यातं व्यवहारतिलके । वीरः</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>075 Prakāśa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/075_prakAsha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/075_prakAsha/</guid>
      <description>Prakasa The Vivādaratnākara of Candleśvara cites the views of Prakāśa scores of times ( e. g. pp. 131, 145, 456, 460,462, 474, 485, 504 etc.). Frequently Prakāsa is coupled with Pārijāta (vide Vivādaratnākara Pp. 145, 2+1, 260, 286, 456 ). On p. 602 of the V. R. the two ( Prakāsa and Pārijāta ) are cited as differing from each other. On pp. 286 and 465 of the V. R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>076 Pārijāta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/076_pArijAta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/076_pArijAta/</guid>
      <description>Parijāta Several works bear the appellation Pārijāta such as the Vidhānapārijāta ( composed in 1625 A. D. ), the Madanapāri. jāta ( about 1375 A. 1).) and the Prayogapārijāta ( between 1400-1500 ). But there was an ancient work called Pārijāta quoted by even some of the earliest nibuni hakāries. The Vivādaratnākara regarded the Kaljataru, Parijata Halā yudha and Prakāśa as its most eminent predecessors.893 The Dānaratnākara 90+ quotes several times the views of Pārijāta on gifts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>077 Govindarāja</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/077_govindarAja/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/077_govindarAja/</guid>
      <description>Govindaraja The commentary of Govindarāja on the Manusmrti was published by Rao Saheh V. N. Mandlik and a portion of it was published by Dr. Jolly in the Manutīkāsangraha. In his commentaryse on Manu III. 247 and 248 he tells us that he has treate&amp;rsquo;l at greater length the subject of those verses in his own work called Smrtimanjari. Kullūka897 in his comment on Manu IV. 212 twits Govindarāja with haviny explained &amp;ldquo;ugra&amp;rsquo; in one way in his commentary on Manu and in a different way in his Manjarī.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>078 The Kalpataru of Lakṣmīdhara</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/078_The_Kalpataru_of_laxmIdhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/078_The_Kalpataru_of_laxmIdhara/</guid>
      <description>78 The Kalpataru of Laksmidhara The Kr̥tyakalpataru or Kalpataru of Laksmidliara exer cised great influence over the Dharmaśāstra writers of Mithila, Bevgal and Northern India in general. It was an extensive work divided into fourteen kāndas. For the first volume of the H. of Dh. published in 1930 the author could secure mss. of only three kāndas viz. Dāna, Rājadharma and Vyavahāra. On reading the account of the Kalpataru in H.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>079 Jīmūtavāhana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/079_jImUtavAhana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/079_jImUtavAhana/</guid>
      <description>Jimutavahana Jimutavāhana is the first of the triumvirate of Bengal writers on dharmuśwstra, the other two being Sūlapāṇi and Raghunandana. Only three works of his are known and they have all been printed viz: the Kālaviveka (B. I. series, 1905), the Vyavahāramātrkā (published in the memoirs of the Bengal Asiatic Society, vol. III., No. 5, pp. 277-353, edited by the late Ṣir Asutosh Mukerji), the Dāyabhāga (published several times ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>080 Aparārka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/080_aparArka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/080_aparArka/</guid>
      <description>Aparārka On the smṛti of Yajñavalkya Aparāditya wrote a voluminous commentary styled Aparārka-Yajñavalkiya-dharmaśastra-nibandha (published in two volumes by the Ānandāśrama Press, Poona, 1903 and 1904). In a verse1 at the end and in the colophons the author is called Aparāditya, a Śilāhāra king, born in the family of Jimutavāhana of the Vidyadhara race. In the introductory[^l020] fifth verse also the author is styled &amp;lsquo;an ornament of the family of Jimūta&amp;rsquo; and is highly eulogised for his devotion to Śiva and his brilliant intellect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>081 Pradīpa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/081_pradIpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/081_pradIpa/</guid>
      <description>Pradipa The Smṛtyarthasāra of Sridhara enumerates the Pradipa among its authorities after the Kamadhenu.1035 The Smstican drikā in a highly paronomastic verse appears to refer to a work called Pradipa.1036 The Sarasvativilāsa 037 quotes the view of the Pradipa that even the suretyship debt of a person must be paid by his grandson. The Jivatpitska nirṇaya1038 of Ramakrsna (about 1600 A. D.) quotes the Pradipa on the question that when brothers are separated they should perform separately the annual sraddha of their father and other ancestors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>082 The Smṛtyarthasāra of Śrīdhara</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/082_The_smRtyarthasAra_of_shrIdhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/082_The_smRtyarthasAra_of_shrIdhara/</guid>
      <description>The Smṛtyarthasāra of Sridhara
This well-known work was published by the Anandāśrama Press, Poona, in 1912 A. D. The principal topics discussed by it are : the acts allowed in former ages but forbidden in the kali age; the number of samskāras, the detailed treatment of Upanayana, the duties of Brahmacārin, holidays, marriage, its various forms, prohibitions on the ground of sapinda relation, discussion about gotra and pravara, daily duties such as sauca, acamana brushing the teeth, bathing, the five yajñas, daily saṁdhyā, daily worship; detailed treatment of śrāddha, proper time, articles, and brā hmanas to be invited at it, various kinds of śrāddha, discussion about various tithis; intercalary month; forbidden and allowed food; purification of various substances and of one&amp;rsquo;s own body; impurity on birth and death; rites after death; rules about sam nyasa; prayaścittas for various grades of sins and lapses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>083 Aniruddha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/083_Aniruddha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/083_Aniruddha/</guid>
      <description>Aniruddha Aniruddhabhattha is one of the early and eminent Bengal writers on Dharmaśāstra. His Hāralatā was published in the Bibliotheca Indica Series (1909) and his Pitļdayitā alias Karmo. padesinipaddhati was recently published by the Sanskrit Sahitya Parishad at Calcutta (No. 6).
The Hāralatā deals with impurity on birth and death, with the acts allowed to be done or forbidden during impurity, with periods of impurity on death in a distant land or on the deaths of infants and women, with rules when two periods of impurity overlap each other, with impurity on the death of sapindas, the meaning of sapinda, persons who have not to observe periods of impurity, cremation and burial, offering of water to the deceased, observances during mourning, persons entitled to perform rites after death, observances after the period of mourning, persons to whom no water should be offered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>084 Ballālasena and Lakṣmaṇasena</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/084_ballAlasena_and_laxmaNasena/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/084_ballAlasena_and_laxmaNasena/</guid>
      <description>Ballālasena and Lakṣmaṇasena These two famous kings of Bengal ( father and son ) com piled five works on Dharmaśāstra viz. Acārasagara, Pratisthā sāgara, Vratasāgara, Dānasāgara, and Adbhutasāgara. Of these, all except Adbhutasāgara, were compiled by Ballālasena; the fifth, Adbhutasāgara, was begun by Ballālasena, but it was completed by Lakṣmanasena.
When the first edition of the H. of Dh. (first volume ) was published in 1930, the only published work of Ballālasena was</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>085 Harihara</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/085_Harihara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/085_Harihara/</guid>
      <description>Harihara From quotations in the Vivādaratnākara it appears that Hari hara wrote on vyavahāra. For example, the Vivādaratnākara first quotes (on p. 220) the definition of samsarapa&amp;rsquo; given by Bṛhaspati and then cites three verses of Kātyāyana defining a catusaptha and a rājamārga and prescribing punishments for causing obstruction and committing nuisance thereon. Then it notices that the verse
yas-tatra&amp;rsquo; cited by it from Kātyāyana is cited by Harihara as from Prajāpati when the topic immediately preceding is</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>086 The Smṛticandrikā of Devaṇṇabhaṭṭa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/086_The_smRtichandrikA_of_devaNNabhaTTa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/086_The_smRtichandrikA_of_devaNNabhaTTa/</guid>
      <description>The Smṛticandrikā of Devannabhatta This is a well-known digest on Dharmaśāstra. An English translation of the portion of it which is concerned with dāyabhāga was published in 1867 by T. Krisnasvami Iyer at Madras. The text has been published by Mr. J. R. Gharpure ( up to śrāddha) in Bombay and also in the Mysore Government Oriental Series ( up to āśauca ). In the following Mr. Gharpure&amp;rsquo;s edition has been used and the Mysore edition for āśauca section.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>087 Haradatta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/087_Haradatta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/087_Haradatta/</guid>
      <description>Haradatta Haradatta&amp;rsquo;s fame stands very high as a commentator. He wrote a commentary called Anakulā on the Apastamba-gļhya-sūtra (D.C. Ms. No. 2 of 1866-68), a commentary on the Apastambiya mantra-pātha ( vide Dr. Winternitz&amp;rsquo;s ed. of 1897, p. XIII.), a com mentary called Anāvila on the Asvalāyana-gļhya-sūtra ( published in the Trivandrum Series ), a commentary called Mitāksarā on the Gautamadharmasūtra and a commentary named Ujjvalā on the dharmasūtra of Āpastamba.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>088 Hemādri</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/088_hemAdri/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/088_hemAdri/</guid>
      <description>Hemādri Hemādri and Madhava are the Castor and Pollux in the galaxy of daksinātya writers on Dharmaśāstra. Hemādri is a very voluminous writer. He is the author of the Caturvarga cintamani, an encyclopedia of ancient religious rites and observances. From ancient times in India the goals of human life (puruṣārthas ) were said to be four viz. Dharma, Artha, Kama and Mokșa ( and were spoken of as Caturvarga&amp;rsquo;). Moksa could be attained only by a few men but as to the other three ( spoken of as Trivarga ) all could secure them, according to their abilities and activities (vide Manu II.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>089 Kullūkabhaṭṭa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/089_kullUkabhaTTa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/089_kullUkabhaTTa/</guid>
      <description>Kullikabhatta Kullūka&amp;rsquo;s commentary on the Manusmṛti styled the Man varthamuktavali is the most famous of all commentaries on Manu. It has been printed several times. In the following the Nirnayasāgara edition of 1909 has been relied upon. Kullūka&amp;rsquo;s commentary is concise and lucid and his remarks are always to the point. He avoids all unnecessary discussions and is never prolix. He was not however original. He drew upon the com mentaries of Medhātithi and Govindarāja and incorporated a great deal from them into his own work without acknowledgment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>090 Śrīdatta Upādhyāya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/090_shrIdatta_upAdhyAya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/090_shrIdatta_upAdhyAya/</guid>
      <description>Śrīdatta Upadhyāya Mithilā has made extremely valuable and substantial contri butions to Dharmaśāstra Literature. From the days of the Yajñavalkya smrti down to modern times the land of Mithilā has produced writers whose names are illustrious. Sridatta Upadhyāya
1133 एको लुब्धस्तु साक्षी स्यादिति कुल्लूकभट्टधृतपाठः, एको लुब्धस्त्वसाक्षी स्यादिति
BUCTURETTET 7 : 1 500 (vol. IIp. 213 ); FIAT: समभागा एव भवेयुर्नोद्धारः कस्यचिद् देय इति कुल्लूकभट्टः । दायतत्त्व ( vol.
II. p.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>091 Caṇḍeśvara</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/091_chaNDeshvara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/091_chaNDeshvara/</guid>
      <description>Candeśvara Candesvara is the most prominent figure among Maithila nibandhakāras on Dharmaśāstra. He compiled an extensive digest called Smstiratnākara or simply Ratnākara. This digest was divided into seven sections viz, on kṛtya, dāna, vyavahāra, śuddhi, pūjā, vivāda and grhastha. 1143 Out of these the Vivāda ratnākara dealing with dāyabhāga and the other titles of law (vyavahārapadas ) has been printed in the B. I. Series and has been translated into English by Mr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>092 Harinātha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/092_harinAtha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/092_harinAtha/</guid>
      <description>Harinātha Harinātha is the author of a digest called Smstisāra on several topics of dharmaśāstra. No part of this work has been yet printed. In the India Office there are two mss. of the Smstisāra (1. O. Cat. p. 448, No, 1488 and p. 449, No. 1489). The first cites 67 authorities ( pramāpakah) on Dharmaśāstra, out of which the Karmapradipa, the Kalpataru, the Kamadhenu, Kumāra, Gapeśvaramiśra, Vijñāneśvara, Vilamba (?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>093 Mādhavācārya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/093_mAdhavAchArya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/093_mAdhavAchArya/</guid>
      <description>Madhavācārya A vast mass of literature has accumulated on the history of Sayana, Madhava, Vidyaranya, the foundation of Vijayanagara, the relations of these three with the founding of the city of Vijayanagara and their relations with the kings of Vijayanagara, the identity of Madhava and Vidyāranya and so on. It is not possible to discuss the whole mass of evidence. Attention will have to be fixed in this work mainly on the contributions of Madhavācārya to Dharmasastra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>094 Madanapāla and Viśveśvarabhaṭṭa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/094_madanapAla_and_vishveshvarabhaTTa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/094_madanapAla_and_vishveshvarabhaTTa/</guid>
      <description>94 Madanapala and Viśyeśvarabhatta
The Madanapārijāta compiled under the patronage of king Madanapala by Viśvesvarabhatta is a famous work. Like Bhoja, Madanapala seems to have been a great patron of learning and several works are attributed to him. At least four works on dharmaśāstra are ascribed to him (i. e. were written under his patronage ) viz. the Madanapārijāta, Smṛtimahārnva or Madana mahārṇava, Tithinirṇayasāra and Smṛtikaumudi. Four more works are ascribed to Madanapala that deal with subjects other than those of Dhasmasastra viz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>095 Madanaratna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/095_Madanaratna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/095_Madanaratna/</guid>
      <description>Madanaratna The Madanaratna is an extensive digest on Dharmaśāstra but only one part of it has been edited by the present author for the Anup Sanskrit Library of Bikaner and published in 1948. The Introduction to that edition (pp. VIII-IX ) may be consulted for more information. In the colophons of mss. it is also called Madanaratnapradipa or simply Madanapradipa. The work was divided into seven1228 sections called uddyotas on samaya (or kala), ācāra, vyavahāra, prāyaścitta, dāna, śuddhi, śānti.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>096 Vidyāpati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/096_vidyApati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/096_vidyApati/</guid>
      <description>Vidyāpati In the first edition of the History of Dharmasāstra, Vidyāpati was not dealt with in the body of the text, but some information about him and his works was given in the list of authors on pp. 739–40. It is thought advisable that a separate section be de voted to Vidyapati in this revised edition, Dr. Umesh Mishra published in Hindi1235 a life of Vidyapati; he gives the pedigree which shows that he was fourth in descent from Dhireśvara, uncle of Candeśvara.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>097 Vyavahāranirṇaya of Varadarāja</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/097_vyavahAranirNaya_of_varadarAja/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/097_vyavahAranirNaya_of_varadarAja/</guid>
      <description>Vyavahāranirṇaya of Varadarāja Twelve years after the first volume of the History of Dharmaśāstra was published in 1930), Prof. K. V. Rangaswami Aiyangar and his pupil Mr. A. N. Krishna Aiyangar published in the Adyar Library Series ( Madras ) an edition of the Vyava hāranirṇaya of Varadarāja based on nine mss. One remarkable feature of the work is that it has no Mangala śloka at the beginning. Prof. Aiyangar suggests that this is so because it is only a part of a large work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>098 Śūlapāṇi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/098_shUlapANi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/098_shUlapANi/</guid>
      <description>Sūlapāṇi Jimūtavahana, Sūlapini and Raghunındana are the three leading and very eminent writers on Dharmaśāstra from Bengal, Rai Bahadur Manomohan Chakravarti in his learned and long paper • Contributions to the History of Snısti in Bengal and Mithila &amp;rsquo; in J. A. S. B. ( New Series) Vol. XI (1915) deals with Bengal authors on Smsti in pp. 311-406 and deals with Sūlapāni in pp. 336–343 giving a very interesting account of his works and time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>099 Rudradhara</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/099_Rudradhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/099_Rudradhara/</guid>
      <description>Rudradhara This is a well-known Maithila writer on Dharmasastra, who composed several works. His Suddhi-viveka has been published several times (at Benares in 1866, in 1878, and by the Venkateśvara Press in Bombay, samvat 1978). That work is divided into three paricchedas and deals with purification from impurity on birth and death, the persons liable to undergo purifications, the mean ing of the word putra, purification of the body and of various substances when polluted, purification of cooked food and water and women in their menses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>100 Misarumiśra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/100_misarumishra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/100_misarumishra/</guid>
      <description>Misarumiśra Misarumiśra is famous for his works called Vivādacandra and Padārtha-candrikā (on the Nyāya-Vaiseșika system ). There is a ms, of the Vivādacandra in the Deccan College (No. 57 of 1883-84). That work deals with the titles of Law (vyavahāra padas ) such as ļṇādāna (recovery of debt), nyāsa (deposit), asvāmivikraya, sambhūya-samutthana (partnership), dāyavibhāga, stridhana; and then with procedure, viz. the plaint, reply, pramānas, witnesses, possession etc. It frequently quotes the Ratnākara ( on vivāda and vyavahāra ) of Candeśvara and several times criticizes him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>101 Vācaspatimiśra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/101_vAchaspatimishra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/101_vAchaspatimishra/</guid>
      <description>Vācaspatimiśra Vacaspatimiśra is the foremost nibandha writer on Smṛti in Mithilā. His Vivadacintamani had been recognised by the High Courts in India and by the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council as a work of paramount authority on matters of Hindu Law in Mithila. 278 His literary activity was closely connected with the reigns of two kings of Mithilā, viz. Bhairavendra or Bhairavasimha ( also styled Harinārāyana ) and his son Rāma bhadra (called also Rūpanārāyana ), both of the Kameśvara dynasty.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>102 Daṇḍaviveka of Vardhamāna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/102_daNDaviveka_of_vardhamAna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/102_daNDaviveka_of_vardhamAna/</guid>
      <description>Dandaviveka of Vardhamāna In the first edition of this History, Vardhamana was not dealt with, because none of his works was then available to me in print. His Dandaviveka was first published in 1931 in the Gaikwad Oriental Series (Buroda ) edited by Mahamahopā
Vardlaināna
855
dhyāya Kamalakrsna Smṛtitirtha of Bhatpara in West Bengal with an exhaustive Introduction in English and a brief one in Sanskrit.
The work deserves special mention in this history since it is probably the only extensive extant Sanskrit work (in 356 pages) on the law of crimes and punishments alone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>103 Nṛsiṃhaprasāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/103_nRsiMhaprasAda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/103_nRsiMhaprasAda/</guid>
      <description>Npsimhaprasāda This is an encyclopaedic work on dharmaśāstra, no part of which had been printed when the first volume of the H. of Dh. was published in 1930. Since then, however, four parts of it have been published in the series called Princess of Wales Sarasvatibhavana Texts (the General editor being M. M. Gopinath Kaviraja ) viz. Vyavahārasāra (edited by Pandit Vinayaksastri Tillu, Sanskrit College, Benares ), Prāyaścitta-sāra (edited by Pandit Nandakishore Sharma and Nandakumar Sharma Sahitya charya ), Śrāddhasāra ( ed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>104 Pratāparudradeva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/104_pratAparudradeva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/104_pratAparudradeva/</guid>
      <description>Pratāparudradeva The Sarasvativilāsa was compiled by Pratāparudradeva, a king of the Gajapati dynasty who ruled at Cuttack (Katakanagari) in Orissa. The Dayabhāga portion of this work was published with an English translation by Rev. Thomas Foulkes in 1881. When the materials for the first volume were being collected, this work dealing with Vyavabāra was in the Press. It was edited by Dr. R. Sham Sastry and was published as a volume in the Oriental Library Publications of the University of Mysore.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>105 Dharmatattvakalānidhi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/105_dharmatattvakalAnidhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/105_dharmatattvakalAnidhi/</guid>
      <description>Dharmatattvakalānidhi or Prthvicandrodaya Vyavahāraprakāśa.
This work was not dealt with in the first edition published in 1930 but brief references were made to it in Appendix A pp. 566 and 584 and Appendix B p. 712. Since then a small portion of the very large digest on Dharmaśāstra named above has been published in 1962 ) as Vol. No. 21 of the Bharatiya vidyā series edited by Mr. J. H.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>106 Govindānanda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/106_govindAnanda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/106_govindAnanda/</guid>
      <description>Govindānanda Govindananda wrote several works out of which four have been printed in the Bibliotheca Indica series, viz. : the Dāna kaumudi, śuddhikaumudi, Sraddhakaumudi, Varṣakriyā-kaumudi. The last work deals with tithinirṇaya, vratas on several tiihis all the year round, festivals like Durgotsava, Kojāgara etc. Besides these be wrote a commentary called Arthakaumudi on the Suddhidipikā of Srinivasa which was printed in Bengali characters, and also a commentary called Tattvārtha-kaumudi on Sulapāṇi&amp;rsquo;s Prāya ścittaviveka (published by Jivananda at Calcutta ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>107 Raghunandana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/107_Raghunandana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/107_Raghunandana/</guid>
      <description>Raghunandana Raghunandana is the last great writer of Bengal on dharma śāstra. He compiled an encyclopædic work on the different branches of dharmaśāstra styled Smṛtitattva, divided into 28 sections called tattvas. He cites the names of over 300 authors and works in his encyclopaedia, which have been collected together by M. M, Chakravarti (JASB for 1915 pp. 363-375). His wonderful mastery over smrti material and his erudition displayed in the Smsti-tattva earned for him the appellation smārtabhattācārya or simply smārta&amp;rsquo; from later writers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>108 Nārāyaṇabhaṭṭa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/108_nArAyaNabhaTTa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/108_nArAyaNabhaTTa/</guid>
      <description>108 Nārāyaṇabhatta
Nārāyaṇabhatta 1364 was the most famous of the celebrated family of the Bhattas of Benares. For a biography of the Bhātta
1364
The work of Śhaṅkarabhatta is called Gadhi-vamśānucarita. The first leaf of the ms, is missing and the work comes abruptly to an end. Even in ancient times there appears to have been
a rivalry between the two great sages of the ægveda viz. Vasiṣtha (to whom and his family are ascribed the verses in the VII Mandala of the Rgveda ) and Viśvāmitra (to whom are ascribed the verses of the 3rd Mandala of the same Veda ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>109 Ṭoḍarānanda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/109_oDarAnanda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/109_oDarAnanda/</guid>
      <description>Todarānanda Rājā Țodaramalla, the celebrated finance minister of Akbar, compiled an extensive encyclopædia of civil and religious law, astronomy and medicine. I gave in the first edition some in formation about this work gathered from several sources. No part of the work had been printed when the first edition of the first volume was published in 1930. In 1945 Pandit K. Madhav Krishna Sarma contributed a paper on Todarānanda to the Journal of the G.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>110 Nandapaṇḍita</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/110_nandapaNDita/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/110_nandapaNDita/</guid>
      <description>Nandapandita Nandapandita was a voluminous writer on dharmaśāstra. An account of his principal works on dharmaśāstra is given below, particularly because most of them are yet unpublished. He was also called Vināyaka as stated in his commentary ( named Suddhi-candrika) on the Sadasiti (also called Aśaucanirṇaya ) of Aditya of the Kausika-gotra. Nandapandita came of the Dharmādhikari family of Benares and is described as the son of Dharmadhikāri Ramapandita. There were several families in Benares famous for their learned works on Dharmaśāstra and other branches such as the Bhātta family (to which belonged Bhattanārāyaṇa, Kamalākara and Nilakantha ), the Dharmādhi kāri family and the Sesa family.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>111 Kamalākarabhaṭṭa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/111_kamalAkarabhaTTa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/111_kamalAkarabhaTTa/</guid>
      <description>Kamalākarabhatta Kamalākarabhatta was one of the foremost scions of the Bhatta family. He was a grandson of the famous Nārāyaṇa bhatta and a son of Rāmakssṇabhatta. He was one of three brothers, the eldest being Dinakara alias Divakara1439 and the youngest was Laksmanabhatta,1420 who studied under Kamala karabhatta. Kamalākarabhatta&amp;rsquo;s father Ramakrśna also was a very421 learned man and a profound mimarnsaka and his mother Umā immolated hereself as a sati.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>112 Nīlakaṇṭhabhaṭṭa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/112_nIlakaNThabhaTTa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/112_nIlakaNThabhaTTa/</guid>
      <description>Nilakanthabhaṭṭa In my introduction to the Vyavabāramayukha (Poona, 1926) pp. V-XLIV, I have dealt exhaustively with the personal H. D. 118
938
history of Nilakantha, his works, their contents, their position in dharmaśāstra literature, the period of Nilakantha&amp;rsquo;s literary activity and his position in modern Hindu Law. In the following a brief résumé of the conclusions there arrived at is given.
Nilakantha was a grandson of Nārāyanabhatta and a son of Śhaṅkarabhatta.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>113 The Vīramitrodaya of Mitramiśra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/113_The_vIramitrodaya_of_mitramishra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/113_The_vIramitrodaya_of_mitramishra/</guid>
      <description>The Vīramitrodaya of Mitramiśra The Viramitrodaya is a vast digest composed by Mitramisra embracing almost all branches of Dharmasastra. Excepting the Caturvarga-cintamani of Hemādri, this work is probably the largest known on dharmaśāstra. But it surpasses in interest and usefulness even Hemādri&amp;rsquo;s work since it deals with vyavahāra also. It was divided into sections called prakāśus. When the first edition of the His. of Dh. was published in 1930, the prakāśas on vyavahāra, Paribhāṣı, samskāra, rājaniti, āhnika.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>114 Anantadeva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/114_Anantadeva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/114_Anantadeva/</guid>
      <description>Anantadera Anantadeva compiled a vast digest called Smrtikaustubha divided into several sections on suriskiras, ācāra, riadharma, dāna, utsarga, pratisthā, tithi and samvatsara. The section on sans kāras and that on rajadharma are also called Saniskāra-kaustu bha and Rajadharma-kaustele. Euch Kaustubha is subdivided into parts called didhiti. The Savskūra-haustubha is the most popular and most well-kaowo of his. It has been printed several times, the best editions being that of the Nirnayasagara Press (1913) and that issued at Baroda ( 1914) under the patron age of H.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>115 Nāgojibhaṭṭa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/115_nAgojibhaTTa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/115_nAgojibhaTTa/</guid>
      <description>Nāgojibbaṭṭa The learning of Nāgojibhatta was of an encyclopaedic character. Though his special forte was Vyakaraṇa ( grammar) he wrote standard works also on poetics, dharmaśāstra, yoga and other sāstras. The number of works ascribed to him is very large. Aufrecht in his Cat. Catalogorum, part I pp. 283 284 mentions 47 works as composed by him. Dr. P. K. Gode in volume III of his Studies in Indian Literary History&amp;rsquo; pp.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>116 Bālakṛṣṇa or Bālambhaṭṭa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/116_bAlakRShNa_or_bAlambhaTTa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/116_bAlakRShNa_or_bAlambhaTTa/</guid>
      <description>Bālakṣsna or Bālambhatta The Lakṣmivyākhyāna alias the Bālambhatti is a commentary on the Mītāksarā of Vijñāneśvara, ascribed to a lady named Laksmidevi. The commentary is a voluminous one and displays uneven workmanship. The commentary on the acāra section of the Mitāksarā is the most learned part of the whole book and is almost an independent work. The late Mr. J. R. Gharpure published all the three parts on acara (pp.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>117 Kāśīnātha-Upādhyāya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/117_kAshInAtha-upAdhyAya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/117_kAshInAtha-upAdhyAya/</guid>
      <description>Kāśīnātha-Upādhyāya Kasinātha Upadhyāya or Bābā Padhye composed an extensive work called Dharmasindhusāra or Dharmābdhisāra, which is popularly known as Dharmasindhu. It is now the leading work in matters of religious observances in the Deccan and has been referred to even in judicial decisions. 1526 It has been published several times. In the following the Nirnayasagara edition of 1936 has been used. He says that he consulted former nibandhas and, following the order of the subject-matters in the Nirnaya sindhu, composed the work which sets forth only the establi shed conclusions after eliminating the original smsti texts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>118 Jagannātha Tarkapañcānana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/118_jagannAtha_tarkapanchAnana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/118_jagannAtha_tarkapanchAnana/</guid>
      <description>Jagannātha Tarkapancānana
After the British took over the administration of Bengal from the Nabobs, attempts were made to compile easily acce ssible digests of the personal law of the Hindus. It appears that Warren Hastings conceived the idea that a compilation of laws applicable to Hindus should be prepared and called together
5
1530 637TIETT: piha: Tien Tha: 1 À Àreit at TTTHHEINTHENA
stiferastā parastfaceaizti sfat &amp;amp;c. &amp;rsquo; ria p.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>119 Conclusion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/119_Conclusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kalpAntaram/kANe/v1p2/119_Conclusion/</guid>
      <description>Conclusion In the foregoing pages most of the classical works and the most prominent writers on Dharmaśāstra during a period of about twenty-five centuries have been passed in review. The number of authors and works on dharmaśāstra is legion. All these numberless authors and works were actuated by the most laudable motives of regulating the Aryan society in all matters, civil, religious and moral, and of securing for the members of that society happiness in this world and the next.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
